<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!--
-
- phpMyAdmin XML Dump
- version 2.10.1
- http://www.phpmyadmin.net
-
- Host: localhost
- Generation Time: Jun 09, 2009 at 12:31 PM
- Server version: 5.0.51
- PHP Version: 5.2.8
-->

<!--
- Database: 'bpasanek_metabase_backup'
-->
<bpasanek_metabase_backup>
  <!-- Table metaphor -->
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>17025</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>0</WorkID>
        <Metaphor></Metaphor>
        <Text></Text>
        <Category></Category>
        <SubCategory></SubCategory>
        <Context></Context>
        <Provenance></Provenance>
        <DoE>0000-00-00</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory></SSCategory>
        <Type></Type>
        <Theme></Theme>
        <Comments></Comments>
        <Dictionary></Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>17084</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>0</WorkID>
        <Metaphor></Metaphor>
        <Text></Text>
        <Category></Category>
        <SubCategory></SubCategory>
        <Context></Context>
        <Provenance></Provenance>
        <DoE>0000-00-00</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory></SSCategory>
        <Type></Type>
        <Theme></Theme>
        <Comments></Comments>
        <Dictionary></Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>14968</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>5599</WorkID>
        <Metaphor></Metaphor>
        <Text> Hindostan's golden shores, with hallow'd waves;&lt;BR&gt; Where palms gigantic rear their tufted heads,&lt;BR&gt; And nature in colossal vegetation spreads,&lt;BR&gt; Where rich ananas court the Indian's eye,&lt;BR&gt; And groves of citrons fan the fev'rish sky,&lt;BR&gt; Where rattling canes around the riv'lets play,&lt;BR&gt; And the centennial aloe drinks the day!&lt;BR&gt; In their deep shades bid Lucidorus smile,&lt;BR&gt; His heavy sense of &lt;i&gt;distant&lt;/i&gt; hours beguile.&lt;BR&gt; Bid him not think, because I gaily write,&lt;BR&gt; That heavy hours to him, to me, are light;&lt;BR&gt; My native spirits, bounding from repose,&lt;BR&gt; Bear me, unwilling, where Castalia flows.&lt;BR&gt; I love to weep, love the soft feast of grief,&lt;BR&gt;&lt;b&gt;Court &lt;/b&gt;mournful thoughts, nor ever wish relief;--&lt;BR&gt;&lt;i&gt;Sadness&lt;/i&gt; I woo, yet still the phantom flies,&lt;BR&gt; And &lt;i&gt;joy&lt;/i&gt; seduces, whilst I ask for sighs.&lt;BR&gt; But Hymen frowns, and joy no longer cheers,&lt;BR&gt; Weeping, I sink--Thalia drinks my tears:&lt;BR&gt; He tears my heart; she my rapt soul inspires;&lt;BR&gt; He chills with grief; she fills me with her fires.&lt;BR&gt; Thus, Lucidorus! pass &lt;i&gt;my&lt;/i&gt; distant hours--&lt;BR&gt; By turns subdued, the slave of rival powers;&lt;BR&gt; And thus hath nature in my little frame&lt;BR&gt; Still various been, and variously the same.&lt;BR&gt; My heart so keenly feels, 'twere death to live,&lt;BR&gt; Did not bright spirits its strong sense relieve.&lt;BR&gt; Through THESE capricious, desultory, gay,&lt;BR&gt; As though I felt not, glides th' unconscious day;&lt;BR&gt; Through THIS I droop, I sadden, and complain,&lt;BR&gt; Dragging, with pensive steps, life's length'ning chain.&lt;BR&gt; In blithesome mood &quot;&lt;i&gt;More Ways than One&lt;/i&gt;&quot; had birth,&lt;BR&gt; Offspring of brilliant morns, and eves of mirth;&lt;BR&gt; The laughing muse in sprightliest vein was by,&lt;BR&gt; And &quot;quips, and cranks,&quot; lay lurking in her eye.&lt;BR&gt; O! may her spirit from its pages dart,&lt;BR&gt; Dance o'er your nerves, and live within your heart!</Text>
        <Category>Government</Category>
        <SubCategory>Throne</SubCategory>
        <Context>Dedication</Context>
        <Provenance>Searching &quot;throne&quot; and &quot;mind&quot; in HDIS (Drama)</Provenance>
        <DoE>2004-07-14</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory>Raising</SSCategory>
        <Type>Metaphor</Type>
        <Theme></Theme>
        <Comments></Comments>
        <Dictionary></Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>12968</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>4866</WorkID>
        <Metaphor></Metaphor>
        <Text>&amp;nbsp; His baser Parts he maim'd with many a Wound;&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; But far above his utmost Reach were pight&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; The Forts of Life: ne ever to confound&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; With utter Ruin, and abolish quite&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; A Power so puissant by his single Might&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; Did he presume to hope: Himself alone&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; From lawless Force to free, in bloody Fight&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; He stood; content to bow to Custom's Throne,&lt;BR&gt; So Reason mote not blush his sovran &lt;b&gt;Rule&lt;/b&gt; to own.&lt;BR&gt;</Text>
        <Category></Category>
        <SubCategory></SubCategory>
        <Context>Canto I</Context>
        <Provenance>Searching &quot;rule&quot; and &quot;reason&quot; in HDIS (Poetry)</Provenance>
        <DoE>2004-06-22</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory></SSCategory>
        <Type></Type>
        <Theme></Theme>
        <Comments>&amp;bull;An allegorical poem. The knight fights a giant. I can't parse these final lines... REVISIT.</Comments>
        <Dictionary></Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>8959</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>3493</WorkID>
        <Metaphor></Metaphor>
        <Text>2&lt;i&gt;7: &lt;/i&gt;Consider the lilies how they grow: they toil not, they spin not; and yet I say unto you, that Solomon in all his glory was not arrayed like one of these. &lt;BR&gt;&lt;i&gt;28: &lt;/i&gt;If then God so clothe the grass, which is to day in the field, and to morrow is cast into the oven; how much more will he clothe you, O ye of little faith? &lt;BR&gt;&lt;i&gt;29: &lt;/i&gt;And seek not ye what ye shall eat, or what ye shall drink, &lt;b&gt;neither be ye of doubtful mind&lt;/b&gt;. &lt;BR&gt;(Luke 12:27-29)</Text>
        <Category>Usage</Category>
        <SubCategory></SubCategory>
        <Context></Context>
        <Provenance>Searching KJV at UVA's Electronic Text Center</Provenance>
        <DoE>2003-06-19</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory></SSCategory>
        <Type></Type>
        <Theme></Theme>
        <Comments>&amp;bull;Only usage of &quot;mind&quot; in Luke. I should delete this reference because I have not included similar &quot;of mind&quot; references from elsewhere in the NT. REVISIT&lt;BR&gt;</Comments>
        <Dictionary></Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>9387</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>3613</WorkID>
        <Metaphor></Metaphor>
        <Text>&lt;BR&gt; Nothing puts a man so much out of tune as &lt;i&gt;discontent&lt;/i&gt;.  A little mudd will defile a whole cistern of fair water. A  fretting spleen like a mist that puts out heavens eye  obscures the soul with cloudy  fumes, and makes the minde so intent upon her misery that she  never seeks for a redresse. &lt;i&gt;Society&lt;/i&gt; cannot cure this disease; for it disturbs all  conversation.&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt; View Document Image [88] &lt;BR&gt; A &lt;i&gt;froward&lt;/i&gt; man offends all, and all offend him. But  those discontents are most irksome which may not be  revealed: for then the heart  withers and consumes without hope of comfort. &lt;i&gt;Good  Counsel&lt;/i&gt; is restorative;  the want of which drives men into a desperate ruine.  &lt;i&gt;Sorrow smothered up&lt;/i&gt;  murders the patient, and like an undermining  Pioner digs for destruction.&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;(pp. 142-3, in. 74)&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;</Text>
        <Category>Fire</Category>
        <SubCategory></SubCategory>
        <Context>Meditation XCI</Context>
        <Provenance>EEBO</Provenance>
        <DoE>2004-03-08</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory></SSCategory>
        <Type>Metaphor</Type>
        <Theme></Theme>
        <Comments>&amp;bull;REVISIT. Fix formatting Rich passage. This was a quick skim to see how the genre of meditations works. I plucked out only the most striking metaphors of mind. </Comments>
        <Dictionary></Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>9092</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>3493</WorkID>
        <Metaphor></Metaphor>
        <Text>&lt;i&gt;13: &lt;/i&gt;And one of the company said unto him, Master, speak to my brother, that he divide the inheritance with me. &lt;BR&gt;&lt;i&gt;14: &lt;/i&gt;And he said unto him, Man, who made me a judge or a divider over you? &lt;BR&gt;&lt;i&gt;15: &lt;/i&gt;And he said unto them, Take heed, and beware of covetousness: for a man's life consisteth not in the abundance of the things which he possesseth. &lt;BR&gt;&lt;i&gt;16: &lt;/i&gt;And he spake a parable unto them, saying, The ground of a certain rich man brought forth plentifully: &lt;BR&gt;&lt;i&gt;17: &lt;/i&gt;And he thought within himself, saying, What shall I do, because I have no room where to bestow my fruits? &lt;BR&gt;&lt;i&gt;18: &lt;/i&gt;And he said, This will I do: I will pull down my barns, and build greater; and there will I bestow all my fruits and my goods. &lt;BR&gt;&lt;i&gt;19: &lt;/i&gt;And &lt;b&gt;I will say to my soul, Soul, thou hast much goods laid up for many years; take thine ease, eat, drink, and be merry&lt;/b&gt;. &lt;BR&gt;&lt;i&gt;20: &lt;/i&gt;But God said unto him, Thou fool, this night thy soul shall be required of thee: then whose shall those things be, which thou hast provided? &lt;BR&gt;&lt;i&gt;21: &lt;/i&gt;So is he that layeth up treasure for himself, and is not rich toward God. &lt;BR&gt;(Luke 12:13-21)</Text>
        <Category>Usage</Category>
        <SubCategory></SubCategory>
        <Context>Parable</Context>
        <Provenance>Searching KJV at UVA's Electronic Text Center</Provenance>
        <DoE>2003-07-15</DoE>
        <DoR>2003-10-23</DoR>
        <SSCategory></SSCategory>
        <Type></Type>
        <Theme></Theme>
        <Comments>&amp;bull;Speaking to own soul. Also: &quot;this night thy soul shall be required of thee.&quot;</Comments>
        <Dictionary></Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>8960</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>3494</WorkID>
        <Metaphor></Metaphor>
        <Text>&lt;i&gt;15: &lt;/i&gt;But he that is spiritual judgeth all things, yet he himself is judged of no man. &lt;BR&gt;&lt;i&gt;16: &lt;/i&gt;&lt;b&gt;For who hath known the mind of the Lord, that he may instruct him? But we have the mind of Christ. &lt;/b&gt;&lt;BR&gt;(1 Corinthians 2:15-16)</Text>
        <Category>Usage</Category>
        <SubCategory></SubCategory>
        <Context></Context>
        <Provenance>Searching KJV at UVA's Electronic Text Center</Provenance>
        <DoE>2003-06-19</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory></SSCategory>
        <Type></Type>
        <Theme></Theme>
        <Comments>&amp;bull;Paul uses &lt;i&gt;nous&lt;/i&gt; only 21 times. Most of these usages appear in Romans.&lt;BR&gt;</Comments>
        <Dictionary></Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>8966</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>3497</WorkID>
        <Metaphor></Metaphor>
        <Text>&lt;i&gt;1: &lt;/i&gt;If there be therefore any consolation in Christ, if any comfort of love, if any fellowship of the Spirit, if any bowels and mercies, &lt;BR&gt;&lt;i&gt;2: &lt;/i&gt;&lt;b&gt;Fulfill ye my joy, that ye be likeminded, having the same love, being of one accord, of one mind&lt;/b&gt;. &lt;BR&gt;&lt;i&gt;3: &lt;/i&gt;Let nothing be done through strife or vainglory; but &lt;b&gt;in lowliness of mind let each esteem other better than themselves&lt;/b&gt;. &lt;BR&gt;&lt;i&gt;4: &lt;/i&gt;Look not every man on his own things, but every man also on the things of others. &lt;BR&gt;&lt;i&gt;5: &lt;/i&gt;&lt;b&gt;Let this mind be in you, which was also in Christ Jesus&lt;/b&gt;: &lt;BR&gt;&lt;i&gt;6: &lt;/i&gt;Who, being in the form of God, thought it not robbery to be equal with God: &lt;BR&gt;&lt;i&gt;7: &lt;/i&gt;But made himself of no reputation, and took upon him the form of a servant, and was made in the likeness of men: &lt;BR&gt;&lt;i&gt;8: &lt;/i&gt;And being found in fashion as a man, he humbled himself, and became obedient unto death, even the death of the cross. &lt;BR&gt;(Philippians 2:1-8)</Text>
        <Category>Usage</Category>
        <SubCategory></SubCategory>
        <Context></Context>
        <Provenance>Searching KJV at UVA's Electronic Text Center</Provenance>
        <DoE>2003-06-19</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory></SSCategory>
        <Type></Type>
        <Theme></Theme>
        <Comments>&amp;bull;Paul uses &lt;i&gt;nous&lt;/i&gt; only 21 times. Most of these usages appear in Romans. But here the KJV Philippians contains 8 references to mind.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;bull;Note that Paul repeatedly uses &quot;of one mind.&quot; Christians are of one mind in Christ. See JC's commandment in Mt 22:37. See also Phil. 4:2, &quot;I beseech Euodias, and beseech Syntyche, that they be of the same mind in the Lord.&quot; See also 1 Pet. 3:8 and elsewhere.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;bull;There are several things going on in the above passage (none of which qualify clearly as &quot;figuration&quot;): REVISIT. Break into 3 entries?&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;</Comments>
        <Dictionary></Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>15771</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>5938</WorkID>
        <Metaphor></Metaphor>
        <Text>ALONZO.&lt;BR&gt;Yes, amiable youth, I remember you well. You are the bold person who ventured to expostulate with Pizarro, when he pronounced sentence of death upon me. Your form is indelibly engraven on my &lt;b&gt;heart&lt;/b&gt;.</Text>
        <Category>Visual Arts</Category>
        <SubCategory>Engraving</SubCategory>
        <Context></Context>
        <Provenance>Searching &quot;engrav&quot; and &quot;heart&quot; in HDIS (Drama)</Provenance>
        <DoE>2005-03-09</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory></SSCategory>
        <Type>Metaphor</Type>
        <Theme></Theme>
        <Comments></Comments>
        <Dictionary></Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>16036</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>6047</WorkID>
        <Metaphor></Metaphor>
        <Text>As Reason, fairest daughter of the skies,&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; Explor'd the vale, where mortal mis'ry lies;&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; Led on by fortitude, with eye serene,&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; She mark'd each object of the varying scene;&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; In every maze of busy life she found&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; Some hidden snare, some agonizing wound;&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; For each her hand display'd a precious balm,&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; Whose pow'r divine the tortur'd soul could calm;&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; Till midway, on a rock of dreadful height,&lt;BR&gt; The Cave of cureless woe assail'd her wond'ring sight!&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; On the bleak threshold, with'ring and forlorn,&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; Heart-wounded Melancholy sat reclin'd!&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; The rude blast scatter'd her dishevell'd hair;&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; Round her cold brow the deadly nightshade twin'd!&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; Near, on a craggy point, stood wild despair,&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; Whose pangs supreme all lesser miseries scorn!&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; And as the gaunt tormentor, smiling, view'd&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; The pensive child of Sorrow, soul-subdu'd;&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; With taunting mien, she beckon'd from below&lt;BR&gt; The fierce, relentless bands of desolating woe!&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; First, swift as lightning up the flinty steep&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; Impatience flew, barefooted, out of breath;&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; Scorning the perils of the dreadful sweep;&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; Heedless of wounding thorns, and threat'ning Death.&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; Eager to rush the foremost of the train,&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; She fear'd not danger, and she felt not pain:&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; With longing eye she view'd the tow'ring height;&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; From peak to peak, quick climbing with delight,&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; She pass'd the fatal cave; then turning short,&lt;BR&gt; Fell headlong from the rock, of ev'ry fiend the sport!&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; Then horror darted forth, in wild amaze!&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; Her hair erect, with pois'nous hemlock bound;&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; Her straining eye-balls flashing fires around,&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; While nature trembled at her potent gaze!&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; Swift to the dizzy precipice she flew,&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; As, aiming with impetuous force to throw&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; Her giant form amidst the gulph below!&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; When, from an ivy'd nook obscure, pale fear &lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; Peep'd forth, slow whisp'ring to her startled ear,&lt;BR&gt; &quot;Think not the pow'r of death thy mis'ries will subdue!&quot;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; Then Horror bent her blood-shot eyes below,&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; Where, by a group of demons compass'd round,&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; Lay suicide accurs'd! from many a wound&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; On his bare bosom did life's fountain flow!&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; Now shame, with cheeks by burning blushes fir'd,&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; And skulking Cowardice, in haste retir'd!&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; While conscience plac'd beneath his fev'rish head&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; A pillow dire, with thorns and nettles spread;&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; And guilt, with all the scorpions of her train,&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; Oped to his fainting eyes eternity of Pain!&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; Then luxury approach'd on couch of down!&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; Drawn by her offspring, folly and disease,&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; Flush'd Pleasure decking her with roseate crown,&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; And bow'd obedience, ever prone to please,&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; Waiting her nod! languid she seemed, and pale,&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; Restless, and sated with voluptuous fare;&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; Beside her pillow, hung with trappings rare,&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; Stood trembling palsy, ready to assail;&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; And writhing agony, and slow decay,&lt;BR&gt; And hood-winked vice abhorr'd, that shunn'd the eye of day.&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; Next, with a solemn, slow, and feeble pace,&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; Came silent poverty, in tatter'd vest!&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; The frequent tears, that glisten'd on her breast,&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; Had fretted channels down her meagre face!&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; A rabble crew of idiots dinn'd her ear:&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; While mean reproach came smiling in the rear.&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; With firm, yet modest look, she pass'd along;&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; Nor sought relief, nor mark'd the taunting throng;&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; While her wrung heart, still scorning to complain,&lt;BR&gt; Suppress'd the rending groan, and throbb'd with proud disdain.&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; Close at her heels, insidious envy crept;&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; The imp, deform'd and horrible in shape,&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; Mock'd, when the slow-consuming victim wept,&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; Pointing, and grinning, like a wither'd ape:&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; About her throat, the asp detraction clung,&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; Scatt'ring destructive poisons from her tongue!&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; She wav'd a blasted laurel o'er her head,&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; Stol'n from the sacred ashes of the dead;&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; Inly she pin'd; while in her panting breast,&lt;BR&gt; Shrunk ignorance struck its fangs, to banish gentle rest.&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; In a lone corner, almost hid in shade,&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; With downcast eye, sat unrequited love! &lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; As from their hollow cell the slow tears stray'd,&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; A willow garland for his brow he wove!&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; Low at his feet, bare Madness laid his head,&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; Rattling his chains, upon his flinty bed!&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; Rous'd from his stupor by the clanking sound,&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; The pensive youth gaz'd fearfully around;&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; And wond'ring to behold such mis'ry near,&lt;BR&gt; Forgot his mournful wreath, and dropp'd a pitying tear.&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; Now, lab'ring up the flinty winding road,&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; Laden with treasure, bending to the ground,&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; Appear'd lean avarice! the pond'rous load&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; Seem'd his weak shoulders every step to wound:&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; One thread-bare garb hung on his aged form;&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; Scant covering from the bleak and wintry storm!&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; Before him famine went, a thing decay'd;&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; And dark suspicion, grasping at a shade!&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; While fraud, low crawling, mock'd the reptile's art,&lt;BR&gt; Pilfer'd the scatter'd gold, and wrung the miser's heart!&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; Next came deceit, with smooth and fawning tongue,&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; Glozing with praises every thing debas'd;&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; To shield her breast, a flattering mirror hung;&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; A tinsel zone shone dazzling round her waist!&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; Her hand, conceal'd beneath her flimsy vest,&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; Clasp'd a keen dagger, ready to destroy;&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; Content she seem'd, though, in her cunning breast,&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; Her coward soul shrunk from the touch of joy;&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; Her humble voice the list'ning ear beguil'd,&lt;BR&gt; While, with infernal art, she murder'd as she smil'd.&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; Now through the cavern rush'd with iron hand&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; Oppression insolent! his arm he rais'd,&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; Waving his spear, with absolute command,&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; While ev'ry subject fiend retir'd, amaz'd!&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; At awful distance, trembling, prostrate round,&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; The sons of pining slav'ry kiss'd the ground;&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; Till, darting forward, o'er the abject crowd,&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; With voice exulting, menacing, and loud,&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; Insatiate vengeance snatch'd the up-rais'd lance,&lt;BR&gt; While bold oppression's arm fell nerveless at his glance.&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; Next Pride came forward, gorgeously array'd;&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; His brow a starry wreath of gems compress'd;&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; In his right hand a sceptre he display'd;&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; A robe of costly ermine wrapp'd his breast!&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; Enthron'd, sublime, above the wond'ring race,&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; Immortal beauties seem'd to deck his face!&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; His eye assum'd pre-eminence of sway;&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; He reign'd the gilded idol of the day;&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; Till death, his dread supremacy to shew,&lt;BR&gt; Struck at the vaunting wretch, and laid his sceptre low.&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; Now, rattling o'er the teeming plains afar,&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; Came glitt'ring wealth, in his resplendent car!&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; His rapid course swift-footed Toil pursu'd&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; With sinewy limbs, and brown sun-freckled breast;&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; The lord of luxury his vassal view'd,&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; And, smiling, lifted high his haughty crest!&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; But, when neglected toil at length retir'd,&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; The short-liv'd glories of his brow expir'd;&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; Around his eager eyes he roll'd in vain;&lt;BR&gt; Ingratitude appear'd, and claim'd her turn to reign!&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; At her approach, the fatal cavern rung:&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; Loud shouts of horror rent the vaulted stone!&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; All lesser Fiends their heads in sorrow hung;&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; Omnipotent in ill, she grasp'd the infernal throne! &lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; Then reason&lt;b&gt; &lt;/b&gt;mark'd her blest associate fly;&lt;BR&gt; And shudd'ring at the scene, re-sought her native sky!</Text>
        <Category>Population</Category>
        <SubCategory></SubCategory>
        <Context>I've included the entire poem</Context>
        <Provenance>HDIS</Provenance>
        <DoE>2004-07-27</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory></SSCategory>
        <Type>Allegory</Type>
        <Theme></Theme>
        <Comments>&amp;bull;INTEREST. Poem-length extended allegory. </Comments>
        <Dictionary></Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>9612</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>3718</WorkID>
        <Metaphor></Metaphor>
        <Text>GOODV.&lt;i&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;/i&gt;No more; I'm thine, and here I seal my heart to thee for ever.</Text>
        <Category>Writing</Category>
        <SubCategory>Seal</SubCategory>
        <Context>Act IV</Context>
        <Provenance>Searching &quot;seal&quot; and &quot;heart&quot; in HDIS (Drama)</Provenance>
        <DoE>2005-04-24</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory></SSCategory>
        <Type>Metaphor</Type>
        <Theme></Theme>
        <Comments></Comments>
        <Dictionary></Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>13949</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>5187</WorkID>
        <Metaphor></Metaphor>
        <Text>if the King were to incorporate six hundred men into a regiment, there would not be six hundred and one Beings therefore, one for the regiment, and one for each of the men [so] neither when a multiple of atoms is run together to form a human body, is there a Being more than there was before: nor would a Being be lost out of nature upon its dissolution.</Text>
        <Category>Population</Category>
        <SubCategory>Regiment</SubCategory>
        <Context></Context>
        <Provenance>Reading Martin's and Barresi's  &lt;i&gt;Naturalization of the Soul &lt;/i&gt;(116)</Provenance>
        <DoE>2004-10-25</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory></SSCategory>
        <Type>Disanalogy; Personification</Type>
        <Theme></Theme>
        <Comments>&amp;bull;Look up actual passage. REVISIT.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;bull;This is a Rylean category mistake.</Comments>
        <Dictionary>Inhabitants</Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>11262</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>4321</WorkID>
        <Metaphor></Metaphor>
        <Text>LUCINDA &lt;BR&gt;Pshaw! I have a very great value for Mr. Bevil but have absolutely put an end to his pretensions in the letter I gave for him. But my father, in his heart, still has a mind to him, were it not for this woman they talk of. And I am apt to imagine he is married to her, or never designs to marry at all.&lt;BR&gt;(Act III, scene i, p. 249)</Text>
        <Category>Usage</Category>
        <SubCategory></SubCategory>
        <Context>Lucinda and Phillis discuss suitors and matches</Context>
        <Provenance>Reading</Provenance>
        <DoE>2003-07-22</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory></SSCategory>
        <Type></Type>
        <Theme></Theme>
        <Comments>&amp;bull;Having a mind in one's heart! Ha!</Comments>
        <Dictionary></Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>14760</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>5515</WorkID>
        <Metaphor></Metaphor>
        <Text>My mind forms no process, surely, to determine, that this table, on which I now lean, is made of wood--or that this pen, with which I now write, was [end page 127] once a feather. I transfer no idea of truth, by any association, in making these discoveries----my mind has no emplyment in making them--it remains passive--and decides at once, the very instant it views them. It is &lt;i&gt;not&lt;/i&gt;, because I have found by experience, that when I made such conclusions, &quot;I have not been deceived&quot;--which leads me to affirm that this pen was a feather, and that this table, is wood--I know both, by a knowledge, which &lt;i&gt;no reasoning was &lt;/i&gt;EVER&lt;i&gt; emplyed to attain&lt;/i&gt;. I associate no circumstance with them. We never throw away our reason, by using it &lt;i&gt;unnecessarily&lt;/i&gt;. If a child, of two years old, sees me enter the room, he instantly believes in my being present--he emplys no reasoning to inform himself that he sees me. He does not believe that he sees me, &lt;i&gt;because he has found, on prior occasions, that when his eyes gave him that information, they did not deceive him&lt;/i&gt;.--far from it--he believed his eyes, &lt;i&gt;the first instant he was ever sensible of the presence of any object&lt;/i&gt;. He forms no induction whatever. [...]&lt;BR&gt;(pp. 127-8)&lt;BR&gt;</Text>
        <Category>Usage</Category>
        <SubCategory>Writing</SubCategory>
        <Context></Context>
        <Provenance>Gale's Eighteenth Century Collections Online (ECCO).</Provenance>
        <DoE>2005-07-18</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory></SSCategory>
        <Type>Metaphor</Type>
        <Theme>Writing to the Moment</Theme>
        <Comments>&amp;bull;INTEREST. Writing to the moment. Another &quot;writing to the moment&quot; moment can be found at (204).</Comments>
        <Dictionary></Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>14687</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>5484</WorkID>
        <Metaphor></Metaphor>
        <Text>My wife is neither one nor t'other: there is something about her too gentle for either; but, I think, her pensive softness deserts more readily to Rouill&amp;eacute;'s side than to mine, though one should imagine his manner the more distant from hers of the two. Rouill&amp;eacute; jokes me on this: he calls her the middle stage between us; but says, it is up hill towards my side. &quot;A solitary castle, and a still evening (said he) would make a Julia of me; but to be Montauban, I must have a fog and a prison.&quot; &lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;Perhaps, if we consider matters impartially, these men have the advantage of us: the little cordialities of life are more frequently in use than its greater and more important duties.&lt;b&gt; Somebody, I think, has compared them to small pieces of coin, which, though of less value than the large, are more current amongst men; but the parallel fails in one respect: a thousand of those &lt;/b&gt;&lt;i&gt;livres &lt;/i&gt;&lt;b&gt;do not constitute a &lt;/b&gt;&lt;i&gt;louis; &lt;/i&gt;&lt;b&gt;and I have known many characters possessed of all that the first could give, whose minds were incapable of the last. &lt;/b&gt;In this number, however, I mean not to include Rouill&amp;eacute;. &lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;We have another guest, who illustrates my meaning better, the widow of Sancerre, whom you introduced to my acquaintance, a long time ago, in Spain. She was then nothing; for Sancerre considered all women nothing, and took care that, during his life, she should be no exception to the rule. He died; she regained her freedom; and she uses it as one to whom it had been long denied. She is just fool enough to be a wit, and carries on a perpetual crusade against sense and seriousness. I bear with her very impatiently: she plagues me, I believe, the more. My wife smiles, Rouill&amp;eacute;  laughs at me; I am unable to laugh, and ashamed to be angry; so I remain silent and stupid. &lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;Sometimes I cease to think of her, and blame myself. Why should I allow this spleen of sense to disqualify me for society? --Once or twice I almost muttered things against my present situation--  Julia loves me; I know she does: she has that tenderness and gratitude, which will secure her affection to a husband, who loves her as I do; but she must often feel the difference of disposition between us. Had such a man as Rouill&amp;eacute; been her husband--not Rouill&amp;eacute; neither, though she seems often delighted with his good humour, when I cannot be pleased with it. --We are neither of us such a man as the writer of a romance would have made a husband for Julia. --There is, indeed, a pliability in the &lt;b&gt;mind&lt;/b&gt;s of women in this article, which frequently gains over opinion to the side of duty. --Duty is a cold word. --No matter, we will canvass it no farther. I know the purity of her bosom, and, I think, I am not unworthy of its affection. &lt;BR&gt;(pp. 79-94)</Text>
        <Category>Usage</Category>
        <SubCategory>Money</SubCategory>
        <Context>Vol II, Letter 33 &lt;BR&gt;Montauban to Segarva</Context>
        <Provenance>HDIS</Provenance>
        <DoE>0000-00-00</DoE>
        <DoR>2003-10-23</DoR>
        <SSCategory></SSCategory>
        <Type>Analogy</Type>
        <Theme></Theme>
        <Comments></Comments>
        <Dictionary></Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>15155</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>5681</WorkID>
        <Metaphor></Metaphor>
        <Text>PERISH th' illiberal thought which would debase&lt;BR&gt;The native genius of the sable race!&lt;BR&gt;Perish the proud philosophy, which sought&lt;BR&gt;To rob them of the powers of equal thought!&lt;BR&gt;Does then th' immortal principle within&lt;BR&gt;Change with the casual colour of the skin?&lt;BR&gt;Does matter govern spirit? or is mind&lt;BR&gt;Degraded by the form to which 'tis joined?&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;No: they have heads to think, and hearts to feel&lt;BR&gt;And souls to act with firm, thought unerring zeal;&lt;BR&gt;For they have keen affections, kind desires,&lt;BR&gt;Love strong as death, and active patriot fires;&lt;BR&gt;All the rude energy, the fervid flame,&lt;BR&gt;Of high-souled passions, and ingenuous shame:&lt;BR&gt;Strong but luxuriant virtues boldly shoot&lt;BR&gt;From the wild vigour of a savage root.&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;Nor weak their sense of honour's proud control,&lt;BR&gt;For pride is virtue in a pagan soul;&lt;BR&gt;A sense of worth, a conscience of desert,&lt;BR&gt;A high, unbroken haughtiness of heart:&lt;BR&gt;That self-same stuff which erst proud empires swayed,&lt;BR&gt;Of which the conquerors of the world were made.&lt;BR&gt;(ll. 1-22, pp. 330-1)&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;</Text>
        <Category>Usage</Category>
        <SubCategory></SubCategory>
        <Context>Excerpted in Lonsdale</Context>
        <Provenance>Reading</Provenance>
        <DoE>2003-07-28</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory></SSCategory>
        <Type></Type>
        <Theme></Theme>
        <Comments>&amp;bull;&quot;Sable&quot; minds: watch More's racialism construct them. I should look at the complete poem for richer metaphors.</Comments>
        <Dictionary></Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>9790</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>3798</WorkID>
        <Metaphor></Metaphor>
        <Text>Rule Sixteen&lt;BR&gt; &lt;BR&gt;&lt;i&gt;As for things which do not require the immediate attention of the mind, however necessary they may be for the conclusion, it is better to represent them by very concise symbols rather than by complete figures. It will thus be impossible for our memory to go wrong, and our mind will not be distracted by having to retain these while it is taken up with deducing other matters.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;BR&gt; &lt;BR&gt;Moreover, as we said, &lt;b&gt;we should not contemplate, in one and the same visual or mental gaze, more than two of the innumerable different dimensions which it is possible to depict in the imagination&lt;/b&gt;. It is therefore important to retain all the others in such a way that they readily come to mind whenever we need to recall them. It seems that memory has been ordained by nature for this very purpose. But because memory is often unreliable, and in order not to have to squander one jot of our attention on refreshing it while engaged with other thoughts, human ingenuity has given us that happy invention - the practice of writing. Relying on this as an aid, we shall leave absolutely nothing to memory but put down on paper whatever we have to retain, thus allowing the imagination to devote itself freely and completely to the ideas immediately before it. We shall do this by means of very concise symbols, so that after scrutinizing each item (in accordance with Rule Nine), we may be able (in accordance with Rule Eleven) to run through all of them with the swiftest sweep of thought and intuit as many as possible at the same time&lt;BR&gt;(Rule 16, p. 66-7)</Text>
        <Category>Usage</Category>
        <SubCategory>Vision</SubCategory>
        <Context>Rule Sixteen</Context>
        <Provenance>Past Masters</Provenance>
        <DoE>2003-10-01</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory></SSCategory>
        <Type></Type>
        <Theme></Theme>
        <Comments>&amp;bull;Not published in Descartes lifetime. First Dutch translation in 1684. First Latin in 1701.&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;</Comments>
        <Dictionary></Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>9786</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>3798</WorkID>
        <Metaphor></Metaphor>
        <Text>Secondly, when an external sense organ is stimulated by an object, the figure which it receives is conveyed at one and the same moment to another part of the body known as the 'common' sense, without any entity really passing from the one to the other. &lt;b&gt;In exactly the same way I understand that while I am writing, at the very moment when individual letters are traced on the paper, not only does the point of the pen move, but the slightest motion of this part cannot but be transmitted simultaneously to the whole pen. All these various motions are traced out in the air by the tip of the quill, even though I do not conceive of anything real passing from one end to the other. &lt;/b&gt;Who then would think that the connection between the parts of the human body is less close than that between the parts of the pen? What simpler way of portraying the matter can be imagined?&lt;BR&gt;(Rule 12, p. 41)</Text>
        <Category>Usage</Category>
        <SubCategory>Writing to the Moment</SubCategory>
        <Context>Rule Twelve</Context>
        <Provenance>Past Masters</Provenance>
        <DoE>2003-10-01</DoE>
        <DoR>2003-10-23</DoR>
        <SSCategory></SSCategory>
        <Type></Type>
        <Theme>Writing to the Moment</Theme>
        <Comments>&amp;bull;Not published in Descartes lifetime. First Dutch translation in 1684. First Latin in 1701.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;bull;Writing to the moment. REVISIT. Set alongside examples in Locke and Hume, etc. &lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;</Comments>
        <Dictionary></Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>9386</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>3614</WorkID>
        <Metaphor></Metaphor>
        <Text>Some would have this word &lt;i&gt;Ira, Anger&lt;/i&gt;, to be derived from &lt;i&gt;uro&lt;/i&gt;, to &lt;i&gt;burn:&lt;/i&gt; because it burns and consumes all before it. It consumes the &lt;i&gt;lodging&lt;/i&gt; wherein it lies, the &lt;i&gt;heart&lt;/i&gt;; it consumes the &lt;i&gt;object&lt;/i&gt; whither it goes; and looks death and destruction upon every thing in the way. So the &lt;i&gt;Philosopher&lt;/i&gt; defines it, &lt;i&gt;A burning (or boyling) of the blood&lt;/i&gt;, or an &lt;i&gt;exuberancy of heat about the heart&lt;/i&gt;. Or you may derive our word &lt;i&gt;Anger&lt;/i&gt; from &lt;i&gt;Ango&lt;/i&gt;; which first sagnifies to &lt;i&gt;strangle&lt;/i&gt; or &lt;i&gt;suffocate&lt;/i&gt;; and then by Metaphor to &lt;i&gt;torment, vex, grieve&lt;/i&gt;, or &lt;i&gt;trouble&lt;/i&gt;, as well the &lt;i&gt;mind&lt;/i&gt; as the &lt;i&gt;body&lt;/i&gt;. And this reaches to both: it destroys the vital parts, and hinders the due operation and exercise of the intellectual faculties: it puts all out of frame and order. So the moral definition fits very well; which terms this troublesome grief [...], &lt;i&gt;appetitum recontristationis&lt;/i&gt;, an appetite (or desire) of interchangable sorrow, of continual distraction. Others would have &lt;i&gt;Ira&lt;/i&gt; come from &lt;i&gt;Ire&lt;/i&gt;, to &lt;i&gt;go&lt;/i&gt;, because the angry man goes out of himself and runnes mad: but whither he will go, or where he will stop, God knows; for the devil drives him. If he be so mad to increase the flames, let him enjoy his fiery death alone. Let him &lt;i&gt;live&lt;/i&gt; like the &lt;i&gt;Salamander&lt;/i&gt;, and &lt;i&gt;die&lt;/i&gt; like the &lt;i&gt;Phaenix. Oh sweet revenge!&lt;/i&gt; I would be loath with my load of mutual wrath to increase the Funeral Peal. It is the sweetest revenge to forget an injury. If thou be angry indeed, let not the &lt;i&gt;person&lt;/i&gt; but his &lt;i&gt;sin&lt;/i&gt; offend thee.  &lt;i&gt;Be angry, and sin not.&lt;/i&gt; Be &lt;i&gt;angry&lt;/i&gt; with sin, or else you &lt;i&gt;sin&lt;/i&gt; in not being angry. Be angry with &lt;i&gt;any thing&lt;/i&gt; but sin, and you cannot but &lt;i&gt;sin&lt;/i&gt; in being angry. Be angry and sin not, be not angry and sin. Consider betimes what thou hast done or said in thy inconsiderate wrath which with too late repentance thou mayst wish were now made void. &lt;i&gt;Whosoever is angry with his brother without a cause shall be in danger of judgement&lt;/i&gt;,  saith our Saviour. When the blood begins to revel in your veines, give this sudden check to that rebellious motion. I am strangely affected now; but I shall be of another minde by and by. Why should I deliver that in &lt;i&gt;anger&lt;/i&gt; which cannot be unsaid when I am &lt;i&gt;pleased&lt;/i&gt;? why should I do that now in these mad fits which will vex me when I am well in my wits? After a &lt;i&gt;showre&lt;/i&gt; of wrath comes a &lt;i&gt;flood&lt;/i&gt; of grief. Cannot &lt;i&gt;Religion&lt;/i&gt;, and &lt;i&gt;Piety&lt;/i&gt;, and &lt;i&gt;Conscience&lt;/i&gt; obtaine that of me at this instant which a little time will enforce.&lt;BR&gt;(pp. 142-3, in. 74)&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;</Text>
        <Category>Fire</Category>
        <SubCategory></SubCategory>
        <Context>Meditation LXXXII</Context>
        <Provenance>EEBO</Provenance>
        <DoE>2004-03-08</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory></SSCategory>
        <Type>Metaphor</Type>
        <Theme></Theme>
        <Comments>&amp;bull;INTEREST. On metaphor and passion. Tubbe plays an etymological game here. REVISIT. Rich passage.</Comments>
        <Dictionary></Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>16880</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>6395</WorkID>
        <Metaphor></Metaphor>
        <Text>The climate of the mind is positively English in its variableness and instability. Frost, sunshine, hopeless drought and refreshing rains succeed one another with bewildering rapidity. Herbert is the poet of this inner weather. Accurately, in a score of lyrics unexcelled for flawless purity of diction and appositeness of imagery, he has described its changes and interpreted, in terms of a mystical philosophy, their significance. Within his limits he achieves a real perfection. (13)</Text>
        <Category>Weather</Category>
        <SubCategory>Climate</SubCategory>
        <Context></Context>
        <Provenance>Reading Norton Critical Edition of Seventeenth Century British Poetry, 1603-1660</Provenance>
        <DoE>2006-12-15</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory></SSCategory>
        <Type>Metaphor</Type>
        <Theme></Theme>
        <Comments></Comments>
        <Dictionary>Weather</Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>16831</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>6364</WorkID>
        <Metaphor></Metaphor>
        <Text>The meaning of a proper name is the object itself which we designate by using it; the idea which we have in that case is wholly subjective; in between lies the sense, which is indeed no longer subjective like the idea, but is yet not the object itself. The following analogy will perhaps clarify these relationships. Somebody observes the Moon through a telescope. I compare the Moon itself to the meaning; it is the object of the observation, mediated by the real image projected by the object glass in the interior of the telescope, and by the retinal image of the observer. The former I compare to the sense, the latter is like the idea or experience. The optical image in the telescope is indeed one-sided and dependent upon the stand point of observation, but it is still objective, in as much as it can be used by several observers. (p.60)</Text>
        <Category>Optics</Category>
        <SubCategory>Telescope</SubCategory>
        <Context></Context>
        <Provenance>Reading Ayer's A Dictionary of Philosophical Quotations</Provenance>
        <DoE>2003-12-05</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory></SSCategory>
        <Type>Analogy</Type>
        <Theme></Theme>
        <Comments></Comments>
        <Dictionary></Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>9114</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>3535</WorkID>
        <Metaphor></Metaphor>
        <Text>The terrible lightning fierce flashes and impressions, are&lt;BR&gt; shewed in the bloody suffusions of our eyes when we are&lt;BR&gt; in a heat and furie.... The violent and gathering rage&lt;BR&gt; of blustering winds, tempestuous stormes and gusts, are not&lt;BR&gt; onely exhibited, but also fore-shewed by exhaled crudities&lt;BR&gt; and by the hissing, singing and ringing noyses of the eares.&lt;BR&gt; The humor and moistnesse that fals like a current or streame&lt;BR&gt; into the emptie spaces of the throat, the throtle and the&lt;BR&gt; chest, resembleth raine and showers... (2nd rev. ed. [1631],&lt;BR&gt; pp. 6-8). </Text>
        <Category>Weather</Category>
        <SubCategory></SubCategory>
        <Context></Context>
        <Provenance>Searching UVA's online &lt;i&gt;Dictionary of Ideas&lt;/i&gt;</Provenance>
        <DoE>2004-05-24</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory></SSCategory>
        <Type></Type>
        <Theme></Theme>
        <Comments>&amp;bull;Poking around on internet I came across this. In the UVA entry there is more about man as a &quot;little world.&quot; REVISIT. READ Crooke.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;bull;NOTE, resolve date issue: 1615 or 1618? All the citations taken from Bamborough were dated 1618. I've changed them throughout to 1615. REVISIT.</Comments>
        <Dictionary></Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>10278</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>3953</WorkID>
        <Metaphor></Metaphor>
        <Text>The Words of the Text are these: Go ye, therefore, and Teach all Nations, Baptizing them in the Name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Ghost. &lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;The Quakers will not own that the Baptism here mentioned was the Outward, or Water-baptism: Which I will endeavour to make very plain, that it was; and that in the first place, &lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;From the Signification and Etymology of the word Baptize. &lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;1. The word is a Greek word, and only made English by our constant usage of it: It signifies to Wash, and is applied to this Sacrament of Baptism, because that is an outward Washing. &lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;To Wash and to Baptize are the very same; and if the word Baptize had been rendred into English, instead of, Go and BAPTIZE, it must have been said, Go and WASH Men, in the Name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Ghost. So that the outward Baptism, with Water, is as much here commanded, as if it had been expressed in English words, or as we can now express it. &lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;But because the word Baptize was grown a Technical Term, in other Languages, whereby to express the Holy Sacrament of Baptism, long before our English Translation, therefore our Translators did rightly retain the word Baptize in this Text, Matth. xxviii. 19.  and in other Texts which speak of that Holy Sacrament. &lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;But in other places they translate the word Baptize, as Mark vii. 4. When they come from the Market ??? ?? ??&amp;pi;????????,  except they are Baptized, which we literally translate except they Wash. And in the  same Verse, ??&amp;pi;??????? &amp;pi;???????,  &amp;c. The Baptisms of Cups and Pots, &amp;c. which we translate the Washing of Cups and Pots. And Heb. ix. 10.  speaking of these Legal Institutions, which stood only in Meats and Drinks, and divers Washings, and carnal Ordinances, &amp;c. the word which we here translate Washings, is, in the Original,  ??&amp;pi;???????, Baptisms: In Meats and Drinks, and divers Baptisms. And in the Vulgar Latin, the Greek word is retained in both &lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;these Texts, Mark vii. 4. Nisi Baptizentur, non Comedunt. Except they are Baptized, i.e. Wash their Hands, they eat not. And Baptismata Calicum, &amp;c. The Baptisms of Cups, &amp;c. And Heb. ix. 10. In Cibis &amp; Pontibus, &amp; variis Baptismatibus, i.e. In Meats and Drinks, and divers Baptisms. So that it is plain that the word Baptism, and the word Washing, tho' not the same word, have yet the self-same meaning. &lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;2. It is true, that the word Baptism is often taken in a Figurative and Allegorical Sense, to mean the INWARD BAPTISM, the Washing, or Cleansing of the Heart :But so is the word Washing also, as often, as Jer. iv. 14.  &amp;c. And there is scarce a Word in the World but is capable of many Figurative and Allegorical Meanings. Thus Circumcision is very often used for the Inward Circumcision or Purity of the Heart .And Fire is taken to express Love, and likewise Anger, and many other things. &lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;But it is a received Rule for the Interpretation of Scripture, and indeed of all other Writings and Words, that the plain Literal Meaning is always to be taken, where there is no manifest Contradiction or Absurdity in it; as when a Man is said to have a Fire burning in his Breast, it cannot be meant of the Literal Fire: So when we are commanded to Wash or Circumcise our Hearts, and the like. But on the other hand, if any Man will take upon him to understand Words in a Figurative Sense, at his own will and pleasure, without an apparent Necessity from the Scope and Coherence, he sets up to Banter, and leaves no Certainty in any Words or Expressions in the World. Therefore I will conclude this Point of the natural Signification and Etymology of the word Baptize: And, unless the Quakers can shew an apparent Contradiction or Absurdity to take it in the Literal Signification, in this Text, Matth. xxviii. 19.  then it must be meant of the OUTWARD WASHING or BAPTISM, because that is the only True, and Proper, and Literal Signification of the Word. &lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;And it will be further Demonstrated in the next Section, that there can be no Contradiction or Absurdity to take it in a Literal Sense, because the Apostles, and Others thereunto Commissionated by them, did Practise it, in the Literal Sense. &lt;BR&gt;(p. 23-6)&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;</Text>
        <Category></Category>
        <SubCategory></SubCategory>
        <Context>In the first section Leslie hope to show that Matthew 28:19 &quot;was meant of water-baptism&quot;</Context>
        <Provenance>Ad Fontes: Digital Library of Classic Protestant Texts</Provenance>
        <DoE>2003-08-25</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory></SSCategory>
        <Type></Type>
        <Theme></Theme>
        <Comments>&amp;bull;Great bits on literal and figurative&lt;BR&gt;&amp;bull;The &quot;?&quot;s are Greek letters that didn't cut and paste properly.</Comments>
        <Dictionary></Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>15306</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>5747</WorkID>
        <Metaphor></Metaphor>
        <Text>These modern Sapphos are conceited creatures,&lt;BR&gt;They sport their thoughts as others do their features;&lt;BR&gt;These but coquette it with a different part,&lt;BR&gt;And seize the head, while others charm the heart.&lt;BR&gt;(ll. 15-8, p. 452)</Text>
        <Category>Body</Category>
        <SubCategory>Face</SubCategory>
        <Context></Context>
        <Provenance>Reading</Provenance>
        <DoE>2003-07-29</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory>Features</SSCategory>
        <Type>Simile</Type>
        <Theme></Theme>
        <Comments></Comments>
        <Dictionary></Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>9265</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>3579</WorkID>
        <Metaphor></Metaphor>
        <Text>To every individual in nature is given an individual property by nature not to be invaded or usurped by any ... For every one, as he is himself, so he has a self-propriety, else he could not &lt;i&gt;be&lt;/i&gt; himself ...&lt;BR&gt;(p. 55)</Text>
        <Category></Category>
        <SubCategory></SubCategory>
        <Context></Context>
        <Provenance>Reading Saree Makdisi's &lt;i&gt;William Blake and the Impossible History of the 1790s&lt;/i&gt; (287)</Provenance>
        <DoE>2005-05-02</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory></SSCategory>
        <Type></Type>
        <Theme></Theme>
        <Comments>&amp;bull;REVISIT and fill out citation</Comments>
        <Dictionary></Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>10280</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>3953</WorkID>
        <Metaphor></Metaphor>
        <Text>We acknowledge a Great and Sublime Mystery in the Holy Trinity of GOD: That is a Mystery to us, which exceeds our Understanding. And many such Mysteries there are, to us, in the Nature of God which we all acknowledge; A First Cause without a Beginning! A Being which neither made it self, nor was made by any other! Infinite without Extension! In every place, yet circumscribed in no place! Eternal and Perpetually Existing, without any Succession! aPresent, without Past, or Future! and many other such un-explainable, un-intelligible, Incomprehensible Mysteries; which yet hinder not our Belief of a God. And therefore not being able fully and clearly to explain the Trinity, which is the most hidden and secret Attribute of the Nature of God, can be no Reason for us to reject such Revelation which God has given us of Himself. Yet do we not want several Shadows and Resemblances of one Nature communicating it self to many Individuals, without either a Multiplication or Division of the Nature. We say that the Soul is all in all, and all in every part of the Body: yet that the Soul is neither Multiplied nor Divided among the several Members of the Body. It is impossible for us either to Explain this, or to Deny it; for we feel it to be so, though it is wholly unconceivable to us how it can be. Now if the Soul ,which is but an Image of God, at an Infinite distance, can communicate it self to several Members, without breach of its Unity; why should it be Impossible for the Eternal and Infinite Mind to communicate it self to several Persons, without breach of its Unity; I will be bold to say, you will not find so near a Parallel in Nature whereby to conceive of God's Eternity, or his Infinity, as this, and a great many more, whereby we may conceive of His Trinity and Unity, by what we feel in our selves, and see in a thousand things that are before us. We see Extension not Divided but Distinguished into its three Dimensions; and Communicating its whole Nature to each of the Three, for Each is Extension; and yet there is but one Extension in all the Three. &lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;The Soul is not Divided betwixt its several Faculties; they remain perfectly distinguished though not divided from one another: To understand what is present, is a quite different thing from Remembring what is Past; and to Love or Hate, is different from both of these; yet these Three Faculties, the Understanding, the Memory, and the Will, partake all equally of the same Soul .&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;Light and Heat are so different, that some are capable of the One, who are not of the Other; and yet they are not Divided in the Sun; but flow equally and naturally from it without any Division of its Nature. &lt;BR&gt;(p.322-4)&lt;BR&gt;</Text>
        <Category></Category>
        <SubCategory></SubCategory>
        <Context>On the trinity: the Socinians are guilty of contradiction</Context>
        <Provenance>Ad Fontes: Digital Library of Classic Protestant Texts</Provenance>
        <DoE>2003-08-25</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory></SSCategory>
        <Type></Type>
        <Theme></Theme>
        <Comments>&amp;bull;Leslie calls these &quot;parallels&quot;: &quot;I say not that any of these Parallels do come up to the full explanation of the Communication of the Divine Nature to several Persons, without any Division or Multiplication of the Nature: But I am sure they take away the Contradiction alledged to be in it, while we see the same Difficulty in our own and other Natures, which we can as little Explain.&quot; (p.324).&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;</Comments>
        <Dictionary></Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>10279</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>3953</WorkID>
        <Metaphor></Metaphor>
        <Text>We come now to Examine, what they set up against any Signs or Figures under the Gospel, from another Topic; and that is, That the Gospel is all Substance, and therefore that there must be no Sign or Figure at all in it. &lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;Answ. By Substance here they mean that which is Inward, or Spiritual, that every thing in the Gospel is Spiritual. &lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;But this will overthrow all Outward, or Bodily Worship. For that is distinguished from Spiritual, or Inward Worship. &lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;And, in one sense, all Bodily Worship is a Sign or Figure of the Inward, or Spiritual; which is the Principal and Substantial Worship. Thus Bowing the Knee, or Uncovering the Head at Prayer, are Signs or Figures of the Inward Reverence and Devotion of the Heart .&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;And this the Quakers practise; therefore, by their own Argument, they have Signs and Figures as well as others; only they throw off those of Christ's Institution, and make new ones of their own. &lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;It is impossible to be without Signs and Figures. For this whole World is a Figure of that which is to come. We our selves are Figures of God, being Images of him: And what is an Image but the Figure or Sign of a Thing? Christ is a Figure of God, being the Express Image of his Person, Heb. i. 3.  And we now have the Knowledge of God in the Face of Jesus Christ. God is a Light inaccessible to Angels, as well as unto Men, without some Medium: His Essence cannot be seen or known Immediately, by any but Himself. All Creatures partake of him in Signs and Figures of him; each in their several Degrees; there are Higher and more Noble Figures; but all are Figures. And God has, in all Ages, through the World, Dispensed himself to Mankind in Signs and Figures; we could not otherwise apprehend Him. Christ is the most Noble and Lively Figure of God: Therefore his Dispensation is far beyond all others that went before him. Yet even now, We see through a Glass darkly, 1 Cor. xiii. 12.  or, in a Riddle; as our Margent reads it,  ?? ?????????,  in a Figure. &lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;What is the Bible that we read, what are Words but the Signatures, the Signs or Figures of Things? We can see the Essence of no one thing in the World, more than of God. And what are all those Accidents of Colour, Quantity and Quality, by which we distinguish Things, but so many Figures or Signs of them? &lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;So very wild is that Notion, that there must be no Signs or Figures under the Gospel! &lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;It would be much Truer, if they had said, That there are nothing else but Signs and Figures: There is nothing else without a Figure but God! For all Creatures are Figures of Him, Christ, the Highest. &lt;BR&gt;(p. 95-6)</Text>
        <Category></Category>
        <SubCategory></SubCategory>
        <Context>On Quakers and figuration. Leslie continues and shows that the Quakers do indeed have &quot;figures&quot;</Context>
        <Provenance>Ad Fontes: Digital Library of Classic Protestant Texts</Provenance>
        <DoE>2003-08-25</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory></SSCategory>
        <Type></Type>
        <Theme></Theme>
        <Comments>&amp;bull;Great bits on literal and figurative</Comments>
        <Dictionary></Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>13379</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>4969</WorkID>
        <Metaphor></Metaphor>
        <Text>When she rates things, and moves from ground to ground,&lt;BR&gt;The name of &lt;i&gt;reason&lt;/i&gt; she obtains by this;&lt;BR&gt;But when reason she the truth has found,&lt;BR&gt;And standeth fixed, she understanding is.</Text>
        <Category>Uncategorized</Category>
        <SubCategory></SubCategory>
        <Context>Given in 6th entry for Reason. </Context>
        <Provenance>Reading Johnson's and Bailey's dictionaries</Provenance>
        <DoE>2004-06-24</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory></SSCategory>
        <Type></Type>
        <Theme></Theme>
        <Comments>&amp;bull;REVISIT. Who is this she?</Comments>
        <Dictionary></Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>9329</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>3599</WorkID>
        <Metaphor></Metaphor>
        <Text>When we have pious thoughts, and think of Heaven,&lt;BR&gt;Yet go about, nor ask to be forgiven,&lt;BR&gt;Perchance they're preaching, or a chapter saying,&lt;BR&gt;Or on their knees they are devoutly praying;&lt;BR&gt;When we are sad, and know no reason why,&lt;BR&gt;Perchance it is, because some there do die;&lt;BR&gt;And some place may in th' head be hung with black,&lt;BR&gt;Which makes us dull, yet know not what we lack.&lt;BR&gt;Our fancies which in verse or prose we put,&lt;BR&gt;May pictures be, which they do draw or cut;&lt;BR&gt;And when these fancies and thin do show,&lt;BR&gt;They may be graven in seal, for ought we know;&lt;BR&gt;When we have cross opinions in the mind,&lt;BR&gt;Then we may them in Schools disputing find;&lt;BR&gt;When we of childish toys do think, a fair&lt;BR&gt;May be in th' brain, where crowds of fairies are,&lt;BR&gt;And in each stall may all such knacks be sold,&lt;BR&gt;As rattles, bells, or bracelets made of gold;&lt;BR&gt;Pins, whistles, and the like may be brought there,&lt;BR&gt;And thus within the head may be a fair:&lt;BR&gt;And when our brain with amorous thoughts is stayed,&lt;BR&gt;Perhaps there is a bride and bridegroom made;&lt;BR&gt;And when our thoughts all merry be and gay,&lt;BR&gt;There may be dancing on their wedding day.</Text>
        <Category>Population</Category>
        <SubCategory></SubCategory>
        <Context>I've included the entire poem</Context>
        <Provenance>Reading</Provenance>
        <DoE>2006-12-15</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory></SSCategory>
        <Type>Metaphor</Type>
        <Theme></Theme>
        <Comments></Comments>
        <Dictionary></Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>13384</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>4972</WorkID>
        <Metaphor></Metaphor>
        <Text>Whether it be a divine revelation or no, reason must &lt;i&gt;judge&lt;/i&gt;, which can never permit the mind to reject a greater evidence to embrace what is less evident.</Text>
        <Category>Government</Category>
        <SubCategory>Judge</SubCategory>
        <Context></Context>
        <Provenance>Johnson's Dictionary</Provenance>
        <DoE>2004-12-02</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory></SSCategory>
        <Type>Personification</Type>
        <Theme></Theme>
        <Comments>&amp;bull;This is cited by Johnson in his definition of &quot;To JUDGE. v.n.&quot;</Comments>
        <Dictionary>Court</Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>14096</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>5237</WorkID>
        <Metaphor></Metaphor>
        <Text>You saw what heart-religion meant [...] true religion is not a negative or an external thing; but the life of God in the soul of man; the image of God stamped upon the heart.</Text>
        <Category>Uncategorized</Category>
        <SubCategory>Stamping</SubCategory>
        <Context></Context>
        <Provenance>Reading J. P. van Noppen's &lt;i&gt;Transforming Words&lt;/i&gt; (123). </Provenance>
        <DoE>2005-06-27</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory>Image</SSCategory>
        <Type>Metaphor</Type>
        <Theme></Theme>
        <Comments></Comments>
        <Dictionary>Impression</Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>12096</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>4593</WorkID>
        <Metaphor> &quot;'Cou'd your Eyes penetrate my naked Breast, / 'There you might read these Characters engrav'd, / '&lt;i&gt;That, by your Virtues I am bound! inslav'd!&lt;/i&gt;&quot;</Metaphor>
        <Text>Then &lt;i&gt;warmly&lt;/i&gt; swear, or &lt;i&gt;solemnly&lt;/i&gt; protest,&lt;BR&gt;&lt;b&gt; &quot;Cou'd your Eyes penetrate my naked Breast,&lt;BR&gt; &quot;There you might read these Characters engrav'd,&lt;BR&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;i&gt;&quot;That, by your Virtues I am bound! inslav'd!&lt;/i&gt;&lt;b&gt; &lt;/b&gt;&lt;BR&gt; &quot;I know the &lt;i&gt;double&lt;/i&gt; Windings of the Laws,&lt;BR&gt; &quot;No Man alive can better &lt;i&gt;serve&lt;/i&gt; your Cause;&lt;BR&gt; &quot;Leave it, &lt;i&gt;Dear Sir&lt;/i&gt;, but leave it to my &lt;i&gt;Care&lt;/i&gt;,&lt;BR&gt; &quot;I'd lose both Eyes, e're you should lose a Hair;&lt;BR&gt; &quot;E're you shou'd prove at last the publick &lt;i&gt;Sport&lt;/i&gt;,&lt;BR&gt; &quot;Or stand the &lt;i&gt;Loss&lt;/i&gt; of being cast in Court.&lt;BR&gt; &quot;No Sir! Enjoy your &lt;i&gt;Pleasure&lt;/i&gt;, and your &lt;i&gt;Wealth&lt;/i&gt;,&lt;BR&gt; &quot;Go &lt;i&gt;Home&lt;/i&gt;, and take your &lt;i&gt;Ease&lt;/i&gt;; and mind your &lt;i&gt;Health&lt;/i&gt;!&quot;&lt;BR&gt;</Text>
        <Category>Writing</Category>
        <SubCategory>Engraving</SubCategory>
        <Context></Context>
        <Provenance>Searching &quot;breast&quot; and &quot;engrav&quot; in HDIS (Poetry)</Provenance>
        <DoE>2005-03-09</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory></SSCategory>
        <Type>Metaphor</Type>
        <Theme></Theme>
        <Comments></Comments>
        <Dictionary></Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>15174</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>5690</WorkID>
        <Metaphor> &quot;But O! how rare benignant Virtue springs / In the blank bosom of despotic kings!&quot;</Metaphor>
        <Text>O blest Biography! thy charms of yore&lt;BR&gt; Historic Truth to strong Affection bore;&lt;BR&gt; And fost'ring Virtue gave thee, as thy dower,&lt;BR&gt; Of both thy Parents the attractive power&lt;BR&gt; To win the heart, the wavering thought to fix,&lt;BR&gt; And fond delight with wise instruction mix.&lt;BR&gt; First of thy votaries, peerless, and alone,&lt;BR&gt; Thy Plutarch shines, by moral beauty known:&lt;BR&gt; Enchanting Sage! whose living lessons teach,&lt;BR&gt; What heights of Virtue human efforts reach.&lt;BR&gt; Tho' oft thy Pen, eccentrically wild,&lt;BR&gt; Ramble, in Learning's various maze beguil'd;&lt;BR&gt; Tho' in thy Style no brilliant graces shine,&lt;BR&gt; Nor the clear conduct of correct Design,&lt;BR&gt; Thy every page is uniformly bright&lt;BR&gt; With mild Philanthropy's diviner light.&lt;BR&gt; Of gentlest manners, as of mind elate,&lt;BR&gt; Thy happy Genius had the glorious fate&lt;BR&gt; To regulate, with Wisdom's soft controul,&lt;BR&gt; The strong ambition of a Trajan's soul.&lt;BR&gt;&lt;b&gt; But O! how rare benignant Virtue springs&lt;BR&gt; In the blank bosom of despotic kings!&lt;/b&gt;</Text>
        <Category>Uncategorized</Category>
        <SubCategory>Blank</SubCategory>
        <Context></Context>
        <Provenance>Searching &quot;blank&quot; and &quot;bosom&quot; in HDIS (Poetry)</Provenance>
        <DoE>2005-03-07</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory></SSCategory>
        <Type>Metaphor</Type>
        <Theme></Theme>
        <Comments>&amp;bull;Doesn't really make sense? Blank bosom?&lt;BR&gt;</Comments>
        <Dictionary></Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>16041</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>6052</WorkID>
        <Metaphor> &quot;Go forth, ye glorious conquerors of the mind&quot;</Metaphor>
        <Text>'Enough--the pow'r I now bestow enjoy,&lt;BR&gt; 'In Virtue's cause the forceful harp employ:&lt;BR&gt;&lt;b&gt; 'Go forth, ye glorious conquerors of the mind,&lt;/b&gt;&lt;BR&gt; 'Atchieve the hallow'd task to you assign'd:&lt;BR&gt; 'Applaud the valiant, and the base controul,&lt;BR&gt; 'Disturb, exalt, enchant the human soul.'&lt;BR&gt;</Text>
        <Category>War</Category>
        <SubCategory>Conquest</SubCategory>
        <Context></Context>
        <Provenance>Searching &quot;mind&quot; and &quot;conque&quot; in HDIS (Poetry)</Provenance>
        <DoE>2005-02-06</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory>Conquer Mind</SSCategory>
        <Type>Metaphor</Type>
        <Theme></Theme>
        <Comments></Comments>
        <Dictionary></Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>14523</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>5419</WorkID>
        <Metaphor> &quot;Not all their cruelty (the fair rejoin'd) / Shall ever boast a conquest o'er my mind&quot;</Metaphor>
        <Text>'For this are daughters born, (Faldoni cried)&lt;BR&gt; 'To fall the victims of parental pride!&lt;BR&gt; 'When nature, youth, and sympathy unite,&lt;BR&gt; 'Say, shall a father's voice forbid the rite?&lt;BR&gt; 'Shall he, with cruel and relentless hands,&lt;BR&gt; 'O'erthrow the altar? tear the nuptial bands?&lt;BR&gt; 'But thou with love and virtue shall combine,&lt;BR&gt; 'To break the law that bids thee not be mine:&lt;BR&gt; 'Still shall the lov'd Teresa be my bride:&lt;BR&gt; 'Not Fortune's gifts to which thou art allied,&lt;BR&gt; 'In my attachment claim'd their venal part,&lt;BR&gt; 'I sought what love requires, a tender heart:&lt;BR&gt; 'Tho' wreck'd, despoil'd, of Fortune's golden store,&lt;BR&gt; 'Rich only in thy heart, I prize thee more.&lt;BR&gt; 'With me ascend yon Alpinean height,&lt;BR&gt; 'Let Italy's bright sun illume our flight,&lt;BR&gt; 'There, haply there, at our disastrous tale,&lt;BR&gt; 'In some kind breast compassion may prevail!&lt;BR&gt; 'In vain--for busy apprehension still&lt;BR&gt; 'Alarms my love, and traverses my will:&lt;BR&gt; 'Worn with the labours of the length'ning way,&lt;BR&gt; 'Should'st thou sink down to weariness a prey:&lt;BR&gt; 'If in that moment, by thy father led,&lt;BR&gt; 'Of Ruffians thou should'st hear the thund'ring tread,&lt;BR&gt; 'What wou'd my rage, by love impell'd, avail,&lt;BR&gt; 'If, as the coward numbers shou'd prevail,&lt;BR&gt; '(Thou most ador'd, thou blest with every charm)&lt;BR&gt; 'They still shou'd tear thee from this vanquish'd arm,&lt;BR&gt;&lt;b&gt; 'Not all their cruelty (the fair rejoin'd)&lt;BR&gt; 'Shall ever boast a conquest o'er my mind&lt;/b&gt;,&lt;BR&gt; 'Ne'er shall they wrest this heart, still uncontrol'd,&lt;BR&gt; 'From Constancy's embrace, and Passion's hold:&lt;BR&gt; 'If to the law that bids me not be thine,&lt;BR&gt; 'One more severe, a father, shou'd adjoin,&lt;BR&gt; 'To rescue still my soul from that distress,&lt;BR&gt; 'A thought, enbosom'd in this heart's recess,&lt;BR&gt; 'Shou'd, rising into act--Ah spare the rest!--&lt;BR&gt; 'Say can't thy fancy my resolve suggest?--&lt;BR&gt; 'This poniard--</Text>
        <Category>War</Category>
        <SubCategory>Conquest</SubCategory>
        <Context></Context>
        <Provenance>Searching &quot;mind&quot; and &quot;conque&quot; in HDIS (Poetry)</Provenance>
        <DoE>2005-02-06</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory>Conquer Mind</SSCategory>
        <Type>Metaphor</Type>
        <Theme></Theme>
        <Comments></Comments>
        <Dictionary></Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>10760</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>4168</WorkID>
        <Metaphor> &quot;[W]ise Men on sound Reason ground Belief: / How that they find what for the Soul is good, / As by their Smell and Taste they judge their Food; / For who but each Man's Reason ought to try / 'Tis Faith, who must be sav'd or damn'd thereby&quot;</Metaphor>
        <Text>All Learning to themselves the Church ingross'd,&lt;BR&gt; The Layman's Right of Literature was lost:&lt;BR&gt; God's Word they made peculiar to their Schools,&lt;BR&gt; Learn'd were their &lt;i&gt;Shepherds&lt;/i&gt;, but their &lt;i&gt;Flocks&lt;/i&gt; were Fool&lt;BR&gt; Who pray'd and paid, and without further thought,&lt;BR&gt; Believ'd in gross whate'er the Pulpit taught.&lt;BR&gt; All humane Sense to holy Craft gave place,&lt;BR&gt; And Reason was a Slave to doubtful Grace.&lt;BR&gt; So blind was Zeal, the People so unwise,&lt;BR&gt; That in their transubstantiate Sacrifice,&lt;BR&gt; They'd trust their erring Guides before their faithful Eyes,&lt;BR&gt; Believe the Euch'rist to be Flesh indeed,&lt;BR&gt; Which their own Senses prov'd to be but Bread.&lt;BR&gt; Sure that Relig'on ne'er could be of Heav'n,&lt;BR&gt; That robs us of that Knowledge God has giv'n.&lt;BR&gt; If Reason must not judge of Faith's true light,&lt;BR&gt; How came our Guides to know the wrong from right,&lt;BR&gt; Or, how their rev'rend Heads distinguish plain,&lt;BR&gt; Betwixt the &lt;i&gt;Bible&lt;/i&gt; and the &lt;i&gt;Alchoran&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;BR&gt; I doubt, were they of Reason dispossest,&lt;BR&gt; 'Twould puzzle 'em to determine which was best.&lt;BR&gt; Reason's the heav'nly Ray that lights the Soul,&lt;BR&gt; And the Faith dark that does its Power controul.&lt;BR&gt; Fools without Thought are in Opinion stiff,&lt;BR&gt;&lt;b&gt; But wise Men on sound Reason ground Belief:&lt;BR&gt; How that they find what for the Soul is good,&lt;BR&gt; As by their Smell and Taste they judge their Food;&lt;BR&gt; For who but each Man's Reason ought to try&lt;BR&gt; 'Tis Faith, who must be sav'd or damn'd thereby.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;BR&gt; But useful Reason was, alas! deny'd,&lt;BR&gt; And Souls depended on their outward Guide.&lt;BR&gt; Th'eternal Word implicitly they took,&lt;BR&gt; And did not dare to soil the sacred Book;&lt;BR&gt; But, hoping well, took all things on content,&lt;BR&gt; And, to enrich their Priests, kept always &lt;i&gt;Lent&lt;/i&gt;;&lt;BR&gt; Gave Sums of value, each to his degree,&lt;BR&gt; For worthless Baubles of Idolatry;&lt;BR&gt; Increas'd their own great Miseries and Wants,&lt;BR&gt; T'adorn with gay Attire their wooden Saints.&lt;BR&gt; When the Church Puppits were t'appear in State,&lt;BR&gt; No Robes could be too rich, no Cost too great;&lt;BR&gt; Each Bigot club'd, that the unharnas'd Shrine,&lt;BR&gt; For sainted Log, might be profusely fine.&lt;BR&gt; The People largely gave, but Heaven knows,&lt;BR&gt; The Priest play'd booty when he bought the Cloaths,&lt;BR&gt; And could not for his Soul be so upright,&lt;BR&gt; To do his Saints that Justice which he might.&lt;BR&gt; New Tissue Mantles for the Waxwork Child,&lt;BR&gt; New Clouts and Cradle, for the Old were soil'd.&lt;BR&gt; For good St. &lt;i&gt;Peter&lt;/i&gt; a Pontifick Dress,&lt;BR&gt; And costly Net his Function to express,&lt;BR&gt; Of Gold and Silver made, which shew too plain,&lt;BR&gt; Those were the only Nets to fish for Men:&lt;BR&gt; Yet tho' their Saints were all so nobly clad,&lt;BR&gt; The saving Clergy this wise Conduct had,&lt;BR&gt; To keep their wooden Gods thus fine and gay,&lt;BR&gt; Like foundling Bastards, at the Parish Pay.&lt;BR&gt; Ten thousand Fopp'ries more did they contrive,&lt;BR&gt; To gull the Laity that the Church might thrive.&lt;BR&gt; Indulgences for any Sins they sold,&lt;BR&gt; None fear'd Damnation, lest they wanted Gold:&lt;BR&gt; But rigid Penance was enjoin'd the Poor,&lt;BR&gt; And all such Misers as conceal'd their Store:&lt;BR&gt; For very strait and rugged was the way&lt;BR&gt; To Heav'n, for him that could and would not pay:&lt;BR&gt; This Text was greatly by the Priests admir'd,&lt;BR&gt;&lt;i&gt;Where much is given, much shall be requir'd&lt;/i&gt;;&lt;BR&gt; Whose genuine sence they basely did confound,&lt;BR&gt; And, to their Gain, the sacred Words expound.&lt;BR&gt; Thus their poor Hearers craftily were won,&lt;BR&gt; First to be Bigots, next to be undone.&lt;BR&gt; The Catalogue of mouldy Saints, 'tis true,&lt;BR&gt; And number of their Beads, the People knew;&lt;BR&gt; Were also taught in a strange Tongue to pray,&lt;BR&gt; And could their &lt;i&gt;Ave&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;Pater&lt;/i&gt; say:&lt;BR&gt; But the blind Suppliants understood no more,&lt;BR&gt; The sacred Jargon that they mumbled o'er,&lt;BR&gt; Than &lt;i&gt;Sappho&lt;/i&gt;'s Parrots, taught to cry aloud,&lt;BR&gt; That &lt;i&gt;Sappho&lt;/i&gt; was a great and mighty God.</Text>
        <Category>Body</Category>
        <SubCategory>Eating and Drinking</SubCategory>
        <Context></Context>
        <Provenance>HDIS</Provenance>
        <DoE>2004-08-31</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory>Food</SSCategory>
        <Type>Comparison</Type>
        <Theme></Theme>
        <Comments></Comments>
        <Dictionary></Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>11425</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>4352</WorkID>
        <Metaphor> 'Tis &lt;i&gt;Lust&lt;/i&gt;, (not Love) and Reason, that are Foes</Metaphor>
        <Text>Right you conclude, reply'd the smiling Boy&lt;BR&gt; Love ruins none, 'tis Men themselves destroy;&lt;BR&gt; And those vile Wretches, which you lately saw,&lt;BR&gt; Transgress'd his Rules, as well as Reason's Law.&lt;BR&gt; They're not Love's Subjects, but the Slaves of &lt;i&gt;Lust&lt;/i&gt;,&lt;BR&gt; Nor is their Punishment so great, as just.&lt;BR&gt; For Love and &lt;i&gt;Lust&lt;/i&gt; essentially divide,&lt;BR&gt; Like Day and Night, Humility and Pride;&lt;BR&gt; One Darkness hides, t'other does always shine,&lt;BR&gt; This of infernal Make, and that divine.&lt;BR&gt; Reason no gen'rous Passion does oppose;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;b&gt; 'Tis &lt;/b&gt;&lt;i&gt;Lust&lt;/i&gt;&lt;b&gt;, (not Love) and Reason, that are Foes.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;BR&gt; She bids you scorn a base inglorious Flame,&lt;BR&gt; Black as the gloomy Shade, from whence it came,&lt;BR&gt; In this, her Precepts should Obedience find,&lt;BR&gt; But yours is not of that ignoble kind.&lt;BR&gt; You Err, in thinking she would disapprove&lt;BR&gt; The brave Pursuit of honourable Love,&lt;BR&gt; And therefore judge what's harmless, an Offence,&lt;BR&gt; Invert her Meaning, and mistake her Sense.&lt;BR&gt; She could not such insipid Counsel give,&lt;BR&gt; As not to love at all, 'tis not to live,&lt;BR&gt; But where bright Virtue, and true Beauty lies,&lt;BR&gt; And that in Delia, charming Delia's Eyes.&lt;BR&gt; Could you, contented, see th' Angelic Maid&lt;BR&gt; In old Alexis' dull Embraces laid?&lt;BR&gt; Or Rough-hewn Tityrus possess those Charms,&lt;BR&gt; Which are in Heaven, the Heaven of Delia's Arms?&lt;BR&gt; Consider, Youth, what Transports you forego,&lt;BR&gt; The most intire Felicity below;&lt;BR&gt; Which is by Fate alone reserv'd for you;&lt;BR&gt; Monarchs have been deny'd, for Monarchs sue.&lt;BR&gt; I own 'tis difficult to gain the Prize,&lt;BR&gt; Or 'twould be cheap, and low in noble Eyes;&lt;BR&gt; But there is one soft Minute, when the Mind&lt;BR&gt; Is left unguarded, waiting to be kind,&lt;BR&gt; Which the wise Lover understanding right,&lt;BR&gt; Steals in like Day upon the Wings of Light.&lt;BR&gt; You urge your Vow, but can those Vows prevail&lt;BR&gt; Whose first Foundation, and whose Reason fail?&lt;BR&gt; You vow'd to leave fair Delia, but you thought&lt;BR&gt; Your Passion was a Crime, your Flame a Fault;&lt;BR&gt; But since your Judgment err'd, it has no Force&lt;BR&gt; To bind at all, but is dissolv'd of Course.&lt;BR&gt; And therefore hesitate no longer here,&lt;BR&gt; But banish all the dull Remains of Fear.&lt;BR&gt; Dare you be happy Youth, but dare, and be;&lt;BR&gt; I'll be your Convoy to the charming she.&lt;BR&gt; What still irresolute? Debating still?&lt;BR&gt; View her, and then forsake her if you will.&lt;BR&gt;</Text>
        <Category>War</Category>
        <SubCategory>Enemies</SubCategory>
        <Context></Context>
        <Provenance></Provenance>
        <DoE>2004-06-22</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory></SSCategory>
        <Type>Metaphor</Type>
        <Theme></Theme>
        <Comments>&lt;BR&gt;</Comments>
        <Dictionary></Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>14524</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>5419</WorkID>
        <Metaphor> A thought may be &quot;enbosom'd in this heart's recess&quot;</Metaphor>
        <Text>'For this are daughters born, (Faldoni cried)&lt;BR&gt; 'To fall the victims of parental pride!&lt;BR&gt; 'When nature, youth, and sympathy unite,&lt;BR&gt; 'Say, shall a father's voice forbid the rite?&lt;BR&gt; 'Shall he, with cruel and relentless hands,&lt;BR&gt; 'O'erthrow the altar? tear the nuptial bands?&lt;BR&gt; 'But thou with love and virtue shall combine,&lt;BR&gt; 'To break the law that bids thee not be mine:&lt;BR&gt; 'Still shall the lov'd Teresa be my bride:&lt;BR&gt; 'Not Fortune's gifts to which thou art allied,&lt;BR&gt; 'In my attachment claim'd their venal part,&lt;BR&gt; 'I sought what love requires, a tender heart:&lt;BR&gt; 'Tho' wreck'd, despoil'd, of Fortune's golden store,&lt;BR&gt; 'Rich only in thy heart, I prize thee more.&lt;BR&gt; 'With me ascend yon Alpinean height,&lt;BR&gt; 'Let Italy's bright sun illume our flight,&lt;BR&gt; 'There, haply there, at our disastrous tale,&lt;BR&gt; 'In some kind breast compassion may prevail!&lt;BR&gt; 'In vain--for busy apprehension still&lt;BR&gt; 'Alarms my love, and traverses my will:&lt;BR&gt; 'Worn with the labours of the length'ning way,&lt;BR&gt; 'Should'st thou sink down to weariness a prey:&lt;BR&gt; 'If in that moment, by thy father led,&lt;BR&gt; 'Of Ruffians thou should'st hear the thund'ring tread,&lt;BR&gt; 'What wou'd my rage, by love impell'd, avail,&lt;BR&gt; 'If, as the coward numbers shou'd prevail,&lt;BR&gt; '(Thou most ador'd, thou blest with every charm)&lt;BR&gt; 'They still shou'd tear thee from this vanquish'd arm,&lt;BR&gt; 'Not all their cruelty (the fair rejoin'd)&lt;BR&gt; 'Shall ever boast a conquest o'er my mind,&lt;BR&gt; 'Ne'er shall they wrest this heart, still uncontrol'd,&lt;BR&gt; 'From Constancy's embrace, and Passion's hold:&lt;BR&gt; 'If to the law that bids me not be thine,&lt;BR&gt; 'One more severe, a father, shou'd adjoin,&lt;BR&gt; 'To rescue still my soul from that distress,&lt;BR&gt;&lt;b&gt; 'A thought, enbosom'd in this heart's recess&lt;/b&gt;,&lt;BR&gt; 'Shou'd, rising into act--Ah spare the rest!--&lt;BR&gt; 'Say can't thy fancy my resolve suggest?--&lt;BR&gt; 'This poniard--</Text>
        <Category>Uncategorized</Category>
        <SubCategory>Recess</SubCategory>
        <Context></Context>
        <Provenance>Searching  in HDIS (Poetry)</Provenance>
        <DoE>2005-02-06</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory></SSCategory>
        <Type>Metaphor</Type>
        <Theme></Theme>
        <Comments></Comments>
        <Dictionary></Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>9591</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>3701</WorkID>
        <Metaphor> All objects are ready form'd and plac'd / To our hands; and these the Senses to the Mind convey, / And as those represent them, this must judge: / How can the Will be free, when the Understanding, / On which the Will depends, cannot be so&quot;</Metaphor>
        <Text>D. JOH.&lt;i&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;/i&gt;I find thou retir'st here, and never readst or thinkst.&lt;BR&gt; Can that blind faculty the Will be free,&lt;BR&gt; When it depends upon the Understanding?&lt;BR&gt; Which argues first before the Will can chuse;&lt;BR&gt; And the last Dictate of the Judgment sways&lt;BR&gt; The Will, as in a Balance, the last Weight&lt;BR&gt; Put in the Scale, lifts up the other end,&lt;BR&gt; And with the same Necessity.&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;HERM.&lt;i&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;/i&gt;But foolish men and sinners act against&lt;BR&gt; Their Understandings, which inform 'em better.&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;D. ANT.&lt;i&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;/i&gt;None willingly do any thing against the last&lt;BR&gt; Dictates of their Judgments, whatsoe'r men do,&lt;BR&gt; Their present opinions lead 'em to.&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;D. LOP.&lt;i&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;/i&gt;As fools that are afraid of sin, are by the thought&lt;BR&gt; Of present pleasure, or some other reason,&lt;BR&gt; Necessarily byass'd to pursue&lt;BR&gt; The opinion they are of at that moment.&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;HERM.&lt;i&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;/i&gt;The Understanding yet is free, and might perswade 'em better.&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;D. JOH.&lt;i&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;/i&gt;The Understanding never can be free;&lt;BR&gt; For what we understand, spite of our selves we do:&lt;BR&gt;&lt;b&gt; All objects are ready form'd and plac'd&lt;BR&gt; To our hands; and these the Senses to the Mind convey,&lt;BR&gt; And as those represent them, this must judge:&lt;BR&gt; How can the Will be free, when the Understanding,&lt;BR&gt; On which the Will depends, cannot be so.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;HERM.&lt;BR&gt;Lay by your devillish Philosophy, and change the dangerous and destructive course of your leud lives.&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;D. ANT.&lt;i&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;/i&gt;Change our natures? Go bid a Blackamore be white, we follow our Constitutions, which we did not give our selves.</Text>
        <Category>Government</Category>
        <SubCategory>Judge</SubCategory>
        <Context>Act III</Context>
        <Provenance>Searching &quot;judge&quot; and kws HDIS (Drama)</Provenance>
        <DoE>2004-10-14</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory></SSCategory>
        <Type>Simile</Type>
        <Theme></Theme>
        <Comments>&amp;bull;Title says tragedy, C-H says comedy. Huh? REVISIT.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;bull;INTEREST. A poweful philosophical argument tucked away in a play.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;bull;The senses represent and the mind judges. </Comments>
        <Dictionary>Court</Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>12584</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>4754</WorkID>
        <Metaphor> One should &quot;Drink early ... at Reason's Bowl, / And fill with wholesome Draughts thy youthful Soul&quot;</Metaphor>
        <Text>Wealth to acquire is most Men's sov'reign Care,&lt;BR&gt; And then a Wife to bring that Wealth an Heir.&lt;BR&gt; In Tracts of Waste th'improving Plowshare's seen,&lt;BR&gt; And barren Heaths in fruitful Tilth are green.&lt;BR&gt; Who's satisfy'd, however small his Store,&lt;BR&gt; Should scorn to throw away a Wish for more.&lt;BR&gt; No stately Equipage, no splendid Plate,&lt;BR&gt; No sumptuous House, no Rent-roll of Estate,&lt;BR&gt; E'er gave the fever'd Blood a Moment's Rest,&lt;BR&gt; Or pluck'd one Thorn from out its Master's Breast.&lt;BR&gt; Who thinks to know the use of Joy and Wealth,&lt;BR&gt; Must first be well in Mind, and strong in Health.&lt;BR&gt; Who lives in Fear, or longs with much for more,&lt;BR&gt; Has just such Pleasure from his useless Store,&lt;BR&gt; As Age-dim Eyes from Painting can receive,&lt;BR&gt; Or Musick's Strains to Ears impostum'd give.&lt;BR&gt; The tainted Cask sours all it does contain;&lt;BR&gt; Shun Pleasures, ever bought too dear with Pain.&lt;BR&gt; The Wretch that covets, always lives in Want,&lt;BR&gt; Stint your Desire, Heav'n has no more to grant.&lt;BR&gt; The envious fall to others Joy a Prey,&lt;BR&gt; And as their Neighbours thrive, they pine away;&lt;BR&gt; The Breasts that's Envy's Slave with Pains is prick'd&lt;BR&gt; Beyond what fell Inquisitors inflict.&lt;BR&gt; He who his rising Anger can't controul,&lt;BR&gt; Shall rue the Sallies of his heated Soul,&lt;BR&gt; Shall wish, in Agony of Heart, undone&lt;BR&gt; What Passion will'd in absent Reason's Throne.&lt;BR&gt; Anger's a short-liv'd Madness, and with Sway,&lt;BR&gt; Rules Sovereign if not tutor'd to obey.&lt;BR&gt; Keep strongly in the hot rebellious Mind,&lt;BR&gt; Be it with Bits restrain'd, and Curbs confin'd.&lt;b&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;/b&gt; The docile Horse in prime of Years is broke&lt;BR&gt; To bear the Rein, or stretch beneath the Yoke.&lt;BR&gt; The Whelp that hunts the Deer Skin round the Court,&lt;BR&gt; Staunch loves the Field, nor ever quits the Sport.&lt;BR&gt;&lt;b&gt; Drink early then, my Friend, at Reason's Bowl,&lt;BR&gt; And fill with wholesome Draughts thy youthful Soul.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;BR&gt; If Wine or Gall the Recent Vessel stains,&lt;BR&gt; Each Scent alike the faithful Cask retains.</Text>
        <Category>Body</Category>
        <SubCategory>Eating and Drinking</SubCategory>
        <Context></Context>
        <Provenance>HDIS</Provenance>
        <DoE>2004-08-09</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory></SSCategory>
        <Type>Metaphor</Type>
        <Theme></Theme>
        <Comments></Comments>
        <Dictionary></Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>15761</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>5931</WorkID>
        <Metaphor> The Sophist boasts in vain that he can &quot;Disprove [Nature's] general empire o'er the heart&quot;</Metaphor>
        <Text>O ye, who listen to the plaintive strain,&lt;BR&gt; With strange enjoyment, and with rapturous pain,&lt;BR&gt; Who erst have felt the &lt;i&gt;Stranger's&lt;/i&gt; lone despair,&lt;BR&gt; And &lt;i&gt;Haller's&lt;/i&gt; settled, sad, remorseful care,&lt;BR&gt; Does &lt;i&gt;Rolla's&lt;/i&gt; pure affection less excite&lt;BR&gt; The inexpressive anguish of delight?&lt;BR&gt; Do &lt;i&gt;Cora's&lt;/i&gt; fears, which beat without control,&lt;BR&gt; With less solicitude engross the soul?&lt;BR&gt; Ah, no! your minds with kindred zeal approve&lt;BR&gt; Maternal feeling, and heroic love.&lt;BR&gt; You must approve; where Man exists below,&lt;BR&gt; In temperate climes, or 'midst drear wastes of snow,&lt;BR&gt; Or where the solar fires incessant flame,&lt;BR&gt; Thy laws, all-powerful Nature, are the same:&lt;BR&gt; Vainly the Sophist boasts, he can explain&lt;BR&gt; The causes of thy universal reign--&lt;BR&gt; More vainly would his cold presumptuous art&lt;BR&gt;&lt;b&gt; Disprove thy general empire o'er the heart:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;BR&gt; A voice proclaims thee, that we must believe,&lt;BR&gt; A voice, that surely speaks not to deceive;&lt;BR&gt; That voice poor &lt;i&gt;Cora&lt;/i&gt; heard, and closely prest&lt;BR&gt; Her darling infant to her fearful breast;&lt;BR&gt; Distracted dar'd the bloody field to tread,&lt;BR&gt; And sought &lt;i&gt;Alonzo&lt;/i&gt; through the heaps of dead,&lt;BR&gt; Eager to catch the music of his breath,&lt;BR&gt; Though faltering in the agonies of death,&lt;BR&gt; To touch his lips, though pale and cold, once more,&lt;BR&gt; And clasp his bosom, though it stream'd with gore;&lt;BR&gt; That voice too &lt;i&gt;Rolla&lt;/i&gt; heard, and, greatly brave,&lt;BR&gt; His &lt;i&gt;Cora's&lt;/i&gt; dearest treasure died to save,&lt;BR&gt; Gave to the hopeless Parent's arms her child,&lt;BR&gt; Beheld her transports, and expiring smil'd.&lt;BR&gt; That voice ye hear--Oh! be its will obey'd!&lt;BR&gt; 'Tis Valour's impulse and 'tis Virtue's aid--&lt;BR&gt; It prompts to all Benevolence admires,&lt;BR&gt; To all that heav'nly Piety inspires,&lt;BR&gt; To all that Praise repeats through lengthen'd years,&lt;BR&gt; That Honour sanctifies, and Time reveres.</Text>
        <Category>Government</Category>
        <SubCategory>Empire</SubCategory>
        <Context>Back Matter</Context>
        <Provenance>Searching &quot;heart&quot; and &quot;empire&quot; in HDIS (Drama)</Provenance>
        <DoE>2004-08-16</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory></SSCategory>
        <Type>Metaphor</Type>
        <Theme></Theme>
        <Comments>&amp;bull;Originally by August Friedrich Ferdinand von Kotzebue(1761-1819) </Comments>
        <Dictionary></Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>8515</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>3258</WorkID>
        <Metaphor> To Reason's yoke the mind quickly will incline ... &quot;But if neglected, will as easily stray, / And master Reason, which she should obey&quot;</Metaphor>
        <Text>Whate'er you write of pleasant or sublime,&lt;BR&gt; Always let sense accompany your rhyme.&lt;BR&gt; Falsely they seem each other to oppose;&lt;BR&gt; Rhyme must be made with Reason's laws to close;&lt;BR&gt; And when to conquer her you bend your force,&lt;BR&gt; The mind will triumph in the noble course.&lt;BR&gt;&lt;b&gt; To Reason's yoke she quickly will incline,&lt;BR&gt; Which, far from hurting, renders her divine;&lt;BR&gt; But if neglected, will as easily stray,&lt;BR&gt; And master Reason, which she should obey.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;BR&gt; Love Reason, then; and let whate'er you write&lt;BR&gt; Borrow from her its beauty, force, and light.&lt;BR&gt; Most writers mounted on a resty muse,&lt;BR&gt; Extravagant and senseless objects chuse;&lt;BR&gt; They think they err, if in their verse they fall&lt;BR&gt; On any thought that's plain or natural.&lt;BR&gt; Fly this excess; and let Italians be&lt;BR&gt; Vain authors of false glittering poetry.&lt;BR&gt; All ought to aim at sense; but most in vain&lt;BR&gt; Strive the hard pass and slippery path to gain;&lt;BR&gt; You drown, if to the right or left you stray;&lt;BR&gt; Reason to go has often but one way.&lt;BR&gt; Sometimes an author, fond of his own thought,&lt;BR&gt; Pursues its object till it's overwrought:&lt;BR&gt; If he describes a house, he shows the face,&lt;BR&gt; And after walks you round from place to place;&lt;BR&gt; Here is a vista, there the doors unfold,&lt;BR&gt; Balconies here are ballustred with gold;&lt;BR&gt; Then counts the rounds and ovals in the halls,&lt;BR&gt; &quot;The festoons, friezes, and the astragals:&quot;&lt;BR&gt; Tired with his tedious pomp, away I run,&lt;BR&gt; And skip o'er twenty pages, to be gone.&lt;BR&gt; Of such descriptions the vain folly see,&lt;BR&gt; And shun their barren superfluity.&lt;BR&gt; All that is needless carefully avoid;&lt;BR&gt; The mind once satisfied is quickly cloyed:&lt;BR&gt; He cannot write, who knows not to give o'er;&lt;BR&gt; To mend one fault, he makes a hundred more:&lt;BR&gt; A verse was weak, you turn it much too strong,&lt;BR&gt; And grow obscure for fear you should be long.&lt;BR&gt; Some are not gaudy, but are flat and dry;&lt;BR&gt; Not to be low, another soars too high.&lt;BR&gt; Would you of every one deserve the praise?&lt;BR&gt; In writing vary your discourse and phrase;&lt;BR&gt; A frozen style, that neither ebbs nor flows,&lt;BR&gt; Instead of pleasing, makes us gape and dose.&lt;BR&gt; Those tedious authors are esteemed by none&lt;BR&gt; Who tire us, humming the same heavy tone.&lt;BR&gt; Happy who in his verse can gently steer,&lt;BR&gt; From grave to light; from pleasant to severe:&lt;BR&gt; His works will be admired wherever found,&lt;BR&gt; And oft with buyers will be compassed round.&lt;BR&gt; In all you write, be neither low nor vile;&lt;BR&gt; The meanest theme may have a proper style.&lt;BR&gt;</Text>
        <Category>Animals</Category>
        <SubCategory>Yoke</SubCategory>
        <Context></Context>
        <Provenance>Searching in HDIS (Poetry)</Provenance>
        <DoE>2005-02-06</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory></SSCategory>
        <Type>Metaphor</Type>
        <Theme></Theme>
        <Comments></Comments>
        <Dictionary></Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>8516</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>3258</WorkID>
        <Metaphor> To Reason's yoke the mind quickly will incline ... &quot;But if neglected, will as easily stray, / And master Reason, which she should obey&quot;</Metaphor>
        <Text>Whate'er you write of pleasant or sublime,&lt;BR&gt; Always let sense accompany your rhyme.&lt;BR&gt; Falsely they seem each other to oppose;&lt;BR&gt; Rhyme must be made with Reason's laws to close;&lt;BR&gt; And when to conquer her you bend your force,&lt;BR&gt; The mind will triumph in the noble course.&lt;BR&gt;&lt;b&gt; To Reason's yoke she quickly will incline,&lt;BR&gt; Which, far from hurting, renders her divine;&lt;BR&gt; But if neglected, will as easily stray,&lt;BR&gt; And master Reason, which she should obey.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;BR&gt; Love Reason, then; and let whate'er you write&lt;BR&gt; Borrow from her its beauty, force, and light.&lt;BR&gt; Most writers mounted on a resty muse,&lt;BR&gt; Extravagant and senseless objects chuse;&lt;BR&gt; They think they err, if in their verse they fall&lt;BR&gt; On any thought that's plain or natural.&lt;BR&gt; Fly this excess; and let Italians be&lt;BR&gt; Vain authors of false glittering poetry.&lt;BR&gt; All ought to aim at sense; but most in vain&lt;BR&gt; Strive the hard pass and slippery path to gain;&lt;BR&gt; You drown, if to the right or left you stray;&lt;BR&gt; Reason to go has often but one way.&lt;BR&gt; Sometimes an author, fond of his own thought,&lt;BR&gt; Pursues its object till it's overwrought:&lt;BR&gt; If he describes a house, he shows the face,&lt;BR&gt; And after walks you round from place to place;&lt;BR&gt; Here is a vista, there the doors unfold,&lt;BR&gt; Balconies here are ballustred with gold;&lt;BR&gt; Then counts the rounds and ovals in the halls,&lt;BR&gt; &quot;The festoons, friezes, and the astragals:&quot;&lt;BR&gt; Tired with his tedious pomp, away I run,&lt;BR&gt; And skip o'er twenty pages, to be gone.&lt;BR&gt; Of such descriptions the vain folly see,&lt;BR&gt; And shun their barren superfluity.&lt;BR&gt; All that is needless carefully avoid;&lt;BR&gt; The mind once satisfied is quickly cloyed:&lt;BR&gt; He cannot write, who knows not to give o'er;&lt;BR&gt; To mend one fault, he makes a hundred more:&lt;BR&gt; A verse was weak, you turn it much too strong,&lt;BR&gt; And grow obscure for fear you should be long.&lt;BR&gt; Some are not gaudy, but are flat and dry;&lt;BR&gt; Not to be low, another soars too high.&lt;BR&gt; Would you of every one deserve the praise?&lt;BR&gt; In writing vary your discourse and phrase;&lt;BR&gt; A frozen style, that neither ebbs nor flows,&lt;BR&gt; Instead of pleasing, makes us gape and dose.&lt;BR&gt; Those tedious authors are esteemed by none&lt;BR&gt; Who tire us, humming the same heavy tone.&lt;BR&gt; Happy who in his verse can gently steer,&lt;BR&gt; From grave to light; from pleasant to severe:&lt;BR&gt; His works will be admired wherever found,&lt;BR&gt; And oft with buyers will be compassed round.&lt;BR&gt; In all you write, be neither low nor vile;&lt;BR&gt; The meanest theme may have a proper style.</Text>
        <Category>Government</Category>
        <SubCategory>Rule and Subjection</SubCategory>
        <Context></Context>
        <Provenance>Searching in HDIS (Poetry)</Provenance>
        <DoE>2005-02-06</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory>Subjection of Reason</SSCategory>
        <Type>Metaphor</Type>
        <Theme></Theme>
        <Comments></Comments>
        <Dictionary></Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>12043</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>4578</WorkID>
        <Metaphor> Truth has &quot;a window in her naked breast&quot;</Metaphor>
        <Text>Nor did there on the other side, I ween,&lt;BR&gt;Forms though more soft, less heav'nly appear;&lt;BR&gt;Conjugal Love and Concord still were seen,&lt;BR&gt;Becoming Meekness and Submission near;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;b&gt;Next Truth, a window in her naked breast&lt;/b&gt;,&lt;BR&gt;Modesty and Prudence ever judging right,&lt;BR&gt;Piety, adding lustre to the rest,&lt;BR&gt;And heav'n-born Charity appear'd in sight;&lt;BR&gt;Blest is the Maid whose paths these virtues guide,&lt;BR&gt;Happy! thrice happy He possess'd of such a Bride!</Text>
        <Category>Architecture</Category>
        <SubCategory>Window</SubCategory>
        <Context></Context>
        <Provenance>Searching &quot;breast&quot; and &quot;window&quot; in HDIS (Poetry)</Provenance>
        <DoE>2006-01-25</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory></SSCategory>
        <Type>Metaphor?</Type>
        <Theme>Momus Glass</Theme>
        <Comments>&amp;bull;Is this a metaphor? A personification?</Comments>
        <Dictionary></Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>15127</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>5663</WorkID>
        <Metaphor> Wisdom unseals charm'd Reason's drowsy eyes,</Metaphor>
        <Text>Rome's legal Code at length on Naples' coast&lt;BR&gt; By chance recover'd, as by ravage lost,&lt;BR&gt; Soon wiser laws, the work of many an age,&lt;BR&gt; Plann'd by the Prince, the Statesman, and the Sage,&lt;BR&gt; Mix with the edicts fram'd in Error's school,&lt;BR&gt; And smooth the rigid form of Gothic rule;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;b&gt; Wisdom unseals charm'd Reason's drowsy eyes,&lt;/b&gt;&lt;BR&gt; And once again Astr&amp;aelig;a leaves the skies.&lt;BR&gt; Themis abash'd, her folly taught to feel,&lt;BR&gt; Less frequent makes to heaven the rash appeal,&lt;BR&gt; And blushes to decide the doubtful right&lt;BR&gt; By burning Ordeal, or the listed fight.&lt;BR&gt; The haughty noble quits the civil sword,&lt;BR&gt; And the gown'd Judge succeeds the feudal Lord,&lt;BR&gt; Impartial Justice curbs the oppressive deed,&lt;BR&gt; And Science smiles from savage licence free</Text>
        <Category>Body</Category>
        <SubCategory>Eye</SubCategory>
        <Context></Context>
        <Provenance></Provenance>
        <DoE>2004-06-22</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory>Reason's Eyes</SSCategory>
        <Type>Personification</Type>
        <Theme>Mind's Eyes</Theme>
        <Comments> </Comments>
        <Dictionary>Eye</Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>14953</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>5591</WorkID>
        <Metaphor>&quot;  And when thou yields to night thy wide domain, / Let rays of truth enlight his sleeping brain.&quot;</Metaphor>
        <Text>Golden Apollo, that thro' heaven wide&lt;BR&gt;  Scatter'st the rays of light, and truth's beams!&lt;BR&gt;In lucent words my darkling verses dight,&lt;BR&gt;  And wash my earthy mind in thy clear streams,&lt;BR&gt;  That wisdom may descend in fairy dreams:&lt;BR&gt;All while the jocund hours in thy train&lt;BR&gt;Scatter their fancies at thy poet's feet;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;b&gt;  And when thou yields to night thy wide domain,&lt;BR&gt;Let rays of truth enlight his sleeping brain.&lt;/b&gt;</Text>
        <Category>Light</Category>
        <SubCategory>Ray</SubCategory>
        <Context></Context>
        <Provenance>Searching in HDIS (Poetry)</Provenance>
        <DoE>2006-04-25</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory>Rays of Truth</SSCategory>
        <Type>Metaphor</Type>
        <Theme></Theme>
        <Comments></Comments>
        <Dictionary></Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>15906</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>5976</WorkID>
        <Metaphor>&quot;  And, while around their spells accurs'd they shed, / For deeds of foul import his breast they steel'd&quot;</Metaphor>
        <Text>  For now the Fiends, whom Moloch left in trust&lt;BR&gt;  O'er England's plains rebellion's flame to spread,&lt;BR&gt;  Had gain'd dominion o'er his soul unjust.&lt;BR&gt;  With subtle skill his daring hopes they fed,&lt;BR&gt;&lt;b&gt;  And, while around their spells accurs'd they shed,&lt;BR&gt;  For deeds of foul import his breast they steel'd:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;BR&gt;  With crowns ideal they adorn'd his head,&lt;BR&gt;  And tempting baits of fancied power reveal'd,&lt;BR&gt;While the barb'd hook within they artfully conceal'd.</Text>
        <Category>Mineral</Category>
        <SubCategory>Steel</SubCategory>
        <Context></Context>
        <Provenance>Searching &quot;breast&quot; and &quot;steel&quot; in HDIS (Poetry)</Provenance>
        <DoE>2005-06-13</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory></SSCategory>
        <Type>Metaphor</Type>
        <Theme></Theme>
        <Comments></Comments>
        <Dictionary>Metal</Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>11743</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>4459</WorkID>
        <Metaphor>&quot;  Britannia's state what bounds confine? / (Of rising thought O golden mine!)&quot;</Metaphor>
        <Text>&lt;b&gt;  Britannia's state what bounds confine?&lt;BR&gt;  (Of rising thought O golden mine!)&lt;/b&gt;&lt;BR&gt;Mountains, Alps, streams, gulfs, oceans, set no bound:&lt;BR&gt;  She sallies till she strikes the star;&lt;BR&gt;  Expanding wide, and launching far&lt;BR&gt;As wind can fly, or rolling wave resound.</Text>
        <Category>Mineral</Category>
        <SubCategory>Golden Mine</SubCategory>
        <Context></Context>
        <Provenance>Searching &quot;thought&quot; and &quot;gold&quot; in HDIS (Poetry)</Provenance>
        <DoE>2005-05-27</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory></SSCategory>
        <Type>Metaphor</Type>
        <Theme></Theme>
        <Comments>&amp;bull;INFO: In &lt;i&gt;Lives of the Poets&lt;/i&gt;, Johnson writes, &quot;In 1730 he relapsed to poetry, and sent into the world Imperium Pelagi; a Naval Lyrick, written in Imitation of Pindar's Spirit, occasioned by His Majesty's Return from Hanover, September 1729, and the succeeding Peace. It is inscribed to the Duke of Chandos. In the Preface we are told that &quot;the ode is the most spirited kind of Poetry, and that the Pindarick is the most spirited kind of ode.&quot; &quot;This I speak,&quot; he adds with sufficient candour, &quot;at my own very great peril. But truth has an eternal title to our confession, though we are sure to suffer by it.&quot; Behold again &quot;the fairest of poets.&quot; Young's Imperium Pelagi as well as his tragedies was ridiculed in Fielding's Tom Thumb; but let us not forget that it was one of his pieces which the author of the Night Thoughts deliberately refused to own.&quot;</Comments>
        <Dictionary>Metal</Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>9608</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>3713</WorkID>
        <Metaphor>&quot;  Come, thou heart-reviving Gleam, / Thou, of Comforters the best, / Thou, the Souls delightful Guest, / A refreshing sweet relief;&quot;</Metaphor>
        <Text>See with what splendor &lt;i&gt;Dives&lt;/i&gt; sits at mear,&lt;BR&gt;With choice of Dainties, courting him to eat.&lt;BR&gt;His Habit Purple, and his Linnen fine,&lt;BR&gt;As if drest up on purpose here to dine.&lt;BR&gt;How the Spectators look, and seem to say,&lt;BR&gt;There's too much store provided for one day:&lt;BR&gt;How many wretched Souls do beg for Bread,&lt;BR&gt;Whilst this same Glutton hath his Table spreadaCome into us, Holy Ghost,&lt;BR&gt;  From thy bright Coelestial coast,&lt;BR&gt;Send us a resplendant Beam:&lt;BR&gt;  Come, thou Father of the Poor,&lt;BR&gt;Come, thou willing Gift-bestow'r,&lt;BR&gt;&lt;b&gt;  Come, thou heart-reviving Gleam,&lt;BR&gt;Thou, of Comforters the best,&lt;BR&gt;  Thou, the Souls delightful Guest,&lt;BR&gt;A refreshing sweet relief;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;BR&gt;  Thou in toyl a resting seat,&lt;BR&gt;Temper in excessive heat,&lt;BR&gt;  Solace to a Soul in grief.&lt;BR&gt;O thou blessedest of Lights!&lt;BR&gt;  Those that love t'observe thy Rites,&lt;BR&gt;With thy self their bosoms fill.&lt;BR&gt;  While thou'rt absent, nothing can&lt;BR&gt;Be regardable in man;&lt;BR&gt;  Nothing can he act but ill.&lt;BR&gt;What is sordid, mundifie;&lt;BR&gt;  Water, what is over-dry:&lt;BR&gt;What is wounded, render sound;&lt;BR&gt;  Pliant make what's hard to yield;&lt;BR&gt;Cherish what with Cold is chil'd;&lt;BR&gt;  Govern what is vagabond.&lt;BR&gt;In the faithful that confide&lt;BR&gt;  In thy mercies, cause reside&lt;BR&gt;All the train of Sev'n-fold Grace,&lt;BR&gt;  Give what Vertue's merit is,&lt;BR&gt;Give th'accomplishment of Bliss,&lt;BR&gt;  Joys of an eternal Race. &lt;i&gt;Amen&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;BR&gt;With all varieties? And thus they show&lt;BR&gt;Their envy: But alas, did they but know,&lt;BR&gt;And well consider what his wants are, then&lt;BR&gt;They'd pity him, as if the worst of men.&lt;BR&gt;His Talent's rich: on earth there's none above it;&lt;BR&gt;But he wants Grace and Wisdom to improve it.&lt;BR&gt;All his Estate is but a mighty spoil;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;b&gt;He hath a Lamp, but that Lamp hath no Oyl.&lt;BR&gt;He hath a Soul, but what doth that embrace?&lt;/b&gt;&lt;BR&gt;Vain worldly Lusts; the opposites to Grace.&lt;BR&gt;His House shines gloriously; but when all's done,&lt;BR&gt;He hath the Star-light, but he wants the Sun.&lt;BR&gt;A Friend to Vice, and Vertue's mortal hater;&lt;BR&gt;Having the Creature, but not the Creator.&lt;BR&gt;This world's a Torrent of false Joys; the boat&lt;BR&gt;Is his vain life, doth on it dayly float.&lt;BR&gt;His Silver Anchor is as weak as Sand;&lt;BR&gt;Nor can his Gold conduct him safe to Land,&lt;BR&gt;But rather sink him to the Misers Cell,&lt;BR&gt;There to inhabit where damn'd Spirits dwell.&lt;BR&gt;Can he be worth your envy then? forbear,&lt;BR&gt;Rather in pity shed a Christian tear.&lt;BR&gt;If he be happy, May it be thy will,&lt;BR&gt;O Lord, that I be miserable still.&lt;BR&gt;  Give me thy Grace, although I'm clad in Rags;&lt;BR&gt;  Let Vice attend the Miser and his Bags.</Text>
        <Category>Population</Category>
        <SubCategory>Guest</SubCategory>
        <Context>I've included the entire poem</Context>
        <Provenance>Searching &quot;soul&quot; and &quot;guest&quot; in HDIS (Poetry)</Provenance>
        <DoE>2006-03-13</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory></SSCategory>
        <Type>Personification</Type>
        <Theme></Theme>
        <Comments></Comments>
        <Dictionary>Inhabitants</Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>13898</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>5170</WorkID>
        <Metaphor>&quot;  Far from the crowd / Of passions loud, / Thyself to me discover&quot;</Metaphor>
        <Text>  Far from the crowd&lt;BR&gt;  Of passions loud,&lt;BR&gt;Thyself to me discover:&lt;BR&gt;  Then I dwell alone with God,&lt;BR&gt;And clasp my heavenly Lover;</Text>
        <Category>Population</Category>
        <SubCategory>Crowd</SubCategory>
        <Context>Psalms</Context>
        <Provenance>Searching &quot;passion&quot; and &quot;crowd&quot; in HDIS (Poetry)</Provenance>
        <DoE>2006-03-08</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory></SSCategory>
        <Type>Personification</Type>
        <Theme></Theme>
        <Comments></Comments>
        <Dictionary>Inhabitants</Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>11112</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>4264</WorkID>
        <Metaphor>&quot;  His Heart is made Thy Altar, whence / To Heav'n arise pure Flames of holy Fire&quot;</Metaphor>
        <Text>  Inmate Divine! Celestial Guest!&lt;BR&gt;Who dost inhabit every pious Breast,&lt;BR&gt;Vile Man becomes, when purify'd by Grace,&lt;BR&gt;Thy Living Temple, and abiding Place.&lt;BR&gt;&lt;b&gt;  His Heart is made Thy Altar, whence&lt;BR&gt;To Heav'n arise pure Flames of holy Fire&lt;/b&gt;,&lt;BR&gt;It moves by Thy impulsive Influence,&lt;BR&gt;And feels the God within, fresh Heat and Life inspire.&lt;BR&gt;Minds, destitute of Native Purity,&lt;BR&gt;Quicken'd, ennobled and refin'd by Thee,&lt;BR&gt;  To the blest Seats above aspire,&lt;BR&gt;Wing'd with Celestial Love, and strong Desire.&lt;BR&gt;  They by their striving upward prove&lt;BR&gt;  Th' attractive Center is above,&lt;BR&gt;  Thither their Motions they direct,&lt;BR&gt;All which the Sun of Righteousness respect:&lt;BR&gt;  Govern'd by Him they take their Course,&lt;BR&gt;Drawn by his Glorious Orb's Magnetic Force.</Text>
        <Category>Architecture</Category>
        <SubCategory>Altar</SubCategory>
        <Context>Stanza X</Context>
        <Provenance>Searching in HDIS (Poetry)</Provenance>
        <DoE>2006-03-15</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory></SSCategory>
        <Type>Metaphor</Type>
        <Theme></Theme>
        <Comments></Comments>
        <Dictionary></Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>10532</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>4088</WorkID>
        <Metaphor>&quot;  Joy must beat high in ev'ry vein, / Pleasure thro' all thy bosom reign;&quot;</Metaphor>
        <Text>  With pleasing rev'rence I behold&lt;BR&gt;  The pearly portals wide unfold:&lt;BR&gt;Enter, my soul, and view th'amazing scenes;&lt;BR&gt;  Sit fast upon the flying muse,&lt;BR&gt;  And let thy roving wonder loose&lt;BR&gt;  O'er all th'empyreal plains.&lt;BR&gt;Noon stands eternal here: here may thy sight&lt;BR&gt;Drink in the rays of primogenial light;&lt;BR&gt;    Here breathe immortal air:&lt;BR&gt;&lt;b&gt;  Joy must beat high in ev'ry vein,&lt;BR&gt;  Pleasure thro' all thy bosom reign;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;BR&gt;  The laws forbid the stranger, pain,&lt;BR&gt;    And banish every care.</Text>
        <Category>Government</Category>
        <SubCategory>Rule and Subjection</SubCategory>
        <Context>Stanza III. From Book II. Sacred to Virtue, Honour, and Friendship</Context>
        <Provenance>Searching in HDIS (Poetry)</Provenance>
        <DoE>2006-03-06</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory>Rule of Pleasure</SSCategory>
        <Type>Personification</Type>
        <Theme></Theme>
        <Comments></Comments>
        <Dictionary></Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>15901</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>5976</WorkID>
        <Metaphor>&quot;  Th' impression sad pervaded every breast,&quot;</Metaphor>
        <Text>  As hung the list'ning warriors on his song&lt;BR&gt;  He saw the varying passions as they rose,&lt;BR&gt;  And mark'd in every face th' emotion strong.&lt;BR&gt;  Sudden a melancholy theme he chose;&lt;BR&gt;  And, as he sung the fallen hero's woes,&lt;BR&gt;  The sympathetic chords he softly press'd.&lt;BR&gt;  Still, at each mournful modulation's close,&lt;BR&gt;&lt;b&gt;  Th' impression sad pervaded every breast,&lt;/b&gt;&lt;BR&gt;Each moisten'd eye the power of melody confess'd.</Text>
        <Category>Uncategorized</Category>
        <SubCategory>Impression</SubCategory>
        <Context></Context>
        <Provenance>Searching &quot;breast&quot; and &quot;impression&quot; in HDIS (Poetry)</Provenance>
        <DoE>2005-05-20</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory></SSCategory>
        <Type>Metaphor</Type>
        <Theme></Theme>
        <Comments></Comments>
        <Dictionary>Impression</Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>12126</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>4605</WorkID>
        <Metaphor>&quot;  The Grecian Prince the Love of Virtue taught: / With Fortitude and Patience steel'd his Breast&quot;</Metaphor>
        <Text>Young William's princely Form she pleas'd surveys&lt;BR&gt;  With manly Air and Grace peculiar shine;&lt;BR&gt;If early Worth insures a lasting Praise,&lt;BR&gt;  Fame's noblest Wreaths shall one great Day be thine.&lt;BR&gt;As Pallas once in Mentor's Shape confess'd,&lt;BR&gt;&lt;b&gt;  The Grecian Prince the Love of Virtue taught:&lt;BR&gt;With Fortitude and Patience steel'd his Breast,&lt;/b&gt;&lt;BR&gt;  And by Degrees the finish'd Hero wrought:&lt;BR&gt;So, in thy Cares, the Picture, Poyntz, we see,&lt;BR&gt;And Britain safe confides her &lt;i&gt;second Hopes&lt;/i&gt; to Thee!</Text>
        <Category>Visual Arts</Category>
        <SubCategory>Steel</SubCategory>
        <Context></Context>
        <Provenance>Searching &quot;breast&quot; and &quot;steel&quot; in HDIS (Poetry)</Provenance>
        <DoE>2005-06-13</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory></SSCategory>
        <Type>Metaphor</Type>
        <Theme></Theme>
        <Comments></Comments>
        <Dictionary></Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>15990</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>6013</WorkID>
        <Metaphor>&quot;  The stranger, Reason, cross'd her way.&quot;</Metaphor>
        <Text>As flowers that fade in burning day,&lt;BR&gt;  At evening find the dew-drop dear,&lt;BR&gt;But fiercer feel the noon-tide ray,&lt;BR&gt;  When soften'd by the nightly tear;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;Returning in the flowing tear,&lt;BR&gt;  This lovely flower, more sweet than they,&lt;BR&gt;Found her fair&lt;b&gt; &lt;/b&gt;soul , and wandering near,&lt;BR&gt;&lt;b&gt;  The stranger, Reason, cross'd her way.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;Found her fair soul--Ah! so to find&lt;BR&gt;  Was but more dreadful grief to know!&lt;BR&gt;Ah! sure, the privilege of mind&lt;BR&gt;  Can not be worth the wish of woe.</Text>
        <Category>Population</Category>
        <SubCategory>Stranger</SubCategory>
        <Context>XIII</Context>
        <Provenance>Searching in HDIS (Poetry)</Provenance>
        <DoE>2006-02-22</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory></SSCategory>
        <Type>Personification</Type>
        <Theme></Theme>
        <Comments></Comments>
        <Dictionary></Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>16059</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>6061</WorkID>
        <Metaphor>&quot; 'Tho' from my mind each flatt'ring thought retir'd, / 'And in my bosom Hope and Peace expir'd;&quot;</Metaphor>
        <Text>'Known to Misfortune from my tender years,&lt;BR&gt; 'My parents' ashes drank my early tears:&lt;BR&gt; 'A barb'rous uncle, to each vice allied,&lt;BR&gt; 'The office of a parent ill supplied:&lt;BR&gt; 'Of my entire inheritance possess'd,&lt;BR&gt; 'By lucre prompted, and by fortune blest,&lt;BR&gt; 'He pass'd the ocean never to return,&lt;BR&gt; 'And left me weeping o'er my parents' urn:&lt;BR&gt; 'Then Arabert, the gen'rous stranger, came,&lt;BR&gt; 'To soothe my sorrows, and relieve my shame:&lt;BR&gt; 'Beneath his tender care my woes decreas'd,&lt;BR&gt; 'More than Religion's, he was Pity's priest:&lt;BR&gt; 'To reach his bounty my affection strove,&lt;BR&gt; 'Till gratitude was heighten'd into love:&lt;BR&gt; 'Nor he at length refus'd the lover's part,&lt;BR&gt; 'The pity that adorn'd, betray'd his heart.&lt;BR&gt; 'How ardently he wish'd the nuptial rite&lt;BR&gt; 'In holy wedlock might our hands unite!&lt;BR&gt; 'But stern Religion at our vows exclaim'd,&lt;BR&gt; 'And tore the bands that Love and Nature fram'd:&lt;BR&gt; 'For then devoted to her hallow'd shrine,&lt;BR&gt; 'His country's laws forbade him to be mine.&lt;BR&gt;&lt;b&gt; 'Tho' from my mind each flatt'ring thought retir'd,&lt;BR&gt; 'And in my bosom Hope and Peace expir'd;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;BR&gt; 'Yet on their ruins Love triumphant rose:&lt;BR&gt; 'Enough--shame o'er the rest a mantle throws:&lt;BR&gt; 'At length Remorse effac'd the guilty scene,&lt;BR&gt; 'And to his breast apply'd her dagger keen;&lt;BR&gt; 'Restrain'd in full career the erring youth,&lt;BR&gt; 'And led him back to Innocence and Truth:&lt;BR&gt; ''Twas then he fled (divorc'd from Pleasure's chain)&lt;BR&gt; 'To woo Religion in this gloomy fane:&lt;BR&gt; 'Yet ere he fled, my bliss he fondly plann'd,&lt;BR&gt; 'And scatter'd riches with a lavish hand:&lt;BR&gt; 'Ah, what to me avail'd the golden store?&lt;BR&gt; 'The giver gone, the gift could charm no more.</Text>
        <Category>Population</Category>
        <SubCategory>Retire</SubCategory>
        <Context></Context>
        <Provenance>Searching in HDIS (Poetry);</Provenance>
        <DoE>2005-04-20</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory></SSCategory>
        <Type>Personification</Type>
        <Theme></Theme>
        <Comments></Comments>
        <Dictionary>Inhabitants</Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>15258</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>5724</WorkID>
        <Metaphor>&quot; 'Tis thine to renovate the fancy's springs&quot;</Metaphor>
        <Text>Is there no eminent revenge above,&lt;BR&gt; For violated oaths and perjur'd love?&lt;BR&gt; Shall ruthless man our miseries begin,&lt;BR&gt; Yet wanton irresponsive to the sin?&lt;BR&gt; The brilliant reptile marshall'd every art,&lt;BR&gt; To brave the prejudice and seize my heart.&lt;BR&gt; False as Amphissian waves his accents flow'd,&lt;BR&gt; Which hide Destruction 'neath the liquid road:&lt;BR&gt; With cruel skill he bent the servile knee,&lt;BR&gt; And stood, like Ruin, 'twixt my good and me.&lt;BR&gt; His toils, like furies in th' &amp;AElig;olian wind,&lt;BR&gt; Bestorm'd the placid current of my mind;&lt;BR&gt; And made th' ideal billows, raging, rise,&lt;BR&gt; Till their rude vehemence had brav'd the skies:&lt;BR&gt; So quick th' Enormities ingulph'd me in,&lt;BR&gt; I look'd a Demon ere I knew the sin.&lt;BR&gt; Once Hope, in garish raiments, cheer'd my eye,&lt;BR&gt; Renerv'd my wish, and check'd the unborn sigh:&lt;BR&gt; Ah, sweet Seducer! whither art thou flown?&lt;BR&gt; While social Demons seize thy silver throne;&lt;BR&gt; 'Tis thine to sprinkle manna o'er the mind,&lt;BR&gt; 'Tis thine to temper the ferocious wind,&lt;BR&gt;&lt;b&gt; 'Tis thine to renovate the fancy's springs,&lt;BR&gt;&lt;/b&gt; Raise the worn maid, and glad despairing kings.&lt;BR&gt;</Text>
        <Category>Uncategorized</Category>
        <SubCategory>Springs</SubCategory>
        <Context></Context>
        <Provenance>Found again searching HDIS (Poetry)</Provenance>
        <DoE>2004-07-12</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory></SSCategory>
        <Type>Metaphor</Type>
        <Theme></Theme>
        <Comments>&lt;BR&gt;</Comments>
        <Dictionary></Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>15257</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>5724</WorkID>
        <Metaphor>&quot; 'Tis thine to sprinkle manna o'er the mind&quot;</Metaphor>
        <Text>Is there no eminent revenge above,&lt;BR&gt; For violated oaths and perjur'd love?&lt;BR&gt; Shall ruthless man our miseries begin,&lt;BR&gt; Yet wanton irresponsive to the sin?&lt;BR&gt; The brilliant reptile marshall'd every art,&lt;BR&gt; To brave the prejudice and seize my heart.&lt;BR&gt; False as Amphissian waves his accents flow'd,&lt;BR&gt; Which hide Destruction 'neath the liquid road:&lt;BR&gt; With cruel skill he bent the servile knee,&lt;BR&gt; And stood, like Ruin, 'twixt my good and me.&lt;BR&gt; His toils, like furies in th' &amp;AElig;olian wind,&lt;BR&gt; Bestorm'd the placid current of my mind;&lt;BR&gt; And made th' ideal billows, raging, rise,&lt;BR&gt; Till their rude vehemence had brav'd the skies:&lt;BR&gt; So quick th' Enormities ingulph'd me in,&lt;BR&gt; I look'd a Demon ere I knew the sin.&lt;BR&gt; Once Hope, in garish raiments, cheer'd my eye,&lt;BR&gt; Renerv'd my wish, and check'd the unborn sigh:&lt;BR&gt; Ah, sweet Seducer! whither art thou flown?&lt;BR&gt; While social Demons seize thy silver throne;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;b&gt; 'Tis thine to sprinkle manna o'er the mind&lt;/b&gt;,&lt;BR&gt; 'Tis thine to temper the ferocious wind,&lt;BR&gt; 'Tis thine to renovate the fancy's springs,&lt;BR&gt; Raise the worn maid, and glad despairing kings.&lt;BR&gt;</Text>
        <Category>Uncategorized</Category>
        <SubCategory>Manna</SubCategory>
        <Context></Context>
        <Provenance></Provenance>
        <DoE>2004-07-12</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory></SSCategory>
        <Type>Metaphor</Type>
        <Theme></Theme>
        <Comments>&lt;BR&gt;</Comments>
        <Dictionary></Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>11681</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>4434</WorkID>
        <Metaphor>&quot; 'Tis true indeed, that there are few Tempers to be found, wherein these Sensations of the several Passions are in such a &lt;i&gt;Ballance&lt;/i&gt;, as in all cases to leave the Mind in a proper State, for considering the Importance of every Action or Event.&quot;</Metaphor>
        <Text>&lt;b&gt; 'Tis true indeed, that there are few Tempers to be found, wherein these Sensations of the several Passions are in such a &lt;/b&gt;&lt;i&gt;Ballance&lt;/i&gt;&lt;b&gt;, as in all cases to leave the Mind in a proper State, for considering the Importance of every Action or Event.&lt;/b&gt; The Sensations of &lt;i&gt;Anger&lt;/i&gt; in some Tempers are violent above their proportion; those of &lt;i&gt;Ambition&lt;/i&gt;, &lt;i&gt;Avarice&lt;/i&gt;, &lt;i&gt;desire of sensual Pleasure&lt;/i&gt;, and even of &lt;i&gt;natural Affection&lt;/i&gt;, in several Dispositions, possess the Mind too much, and make it incapable of attending to any thing else. Scarce any one Temper is always constant and uniform in its Passions. The best State of human Nature possible might require a Diversity of Passions and Inclinations, for the different Occupations necessary for the whole: But the Disorder seems to be much greater than is [56] requisite for this End. &lt;i&gt;Custom&lt;/i&gt;, &lt;i&gt;Education&lt;/i&gt;, &lt;i&gt;Habits&lt;/i&gt;, and &lt;i&gt;Company&lt;/i&gt;, may [57] often contribute much to this Disorder, however its Original may be ascribed to some more universal Cause. But it is not so great, but that human Life is still a desireable State, having a superiority of Goodness and Happiness. Nor, if we apply our selves to it, does it hinder us from discerning that just &lt;i&gt;Ballance&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;Oeconomy&lt;/i&gt;, which would constitute the most happy State of each Person, and promote the greatest Good in the whole. &lt;BR&gt;(p. 47)</Text>
        <Category>Uncategorized</Category>
        <SubCategory>Balance</SubCategory>
        <Context>Treatise I</Context>
        <Provenance>Searchign &quot;mind&quot; in Liberty Fund's OLL</Provenance>
        <DoE>2005-08-18</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory></SSCategory>
        <Type>Metaphor</Type>
        <Theme></Theme>
        <Comments></Comments>
        <Dictionary></Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>15029</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>5616</WorkID>
        <Metaphor>&quot; 'Twixt shame and passion floats the struggling mind, / To Virtue now, and now to vice inclin'd, / This frowns refusal, that persuades to yield, / Till Reason falls, and Passion takes the field&quot;</Metaphor>
        <Text>As varying Pleasure darts her smiles around,&lt;BR&gt; And strews her ruddiest rose-buds on the ground,&lt;BR&gt; As shines Love's nectar in Youth's flattering glass,&lt;BR&gt; And Nature gilds the minutes as they pass.&lt;BR&gt; Swift glides the heart from Virtue's fair intent,&lt;BR&gt; And faint Denial half implies consent.&lt;BR&gt;&lt;b&gt; 'Twixt shame and passion floats the struggling mind,&lt;BR&gt; To Virtue now, and now to vice inclin'd,&lt;BR&gt; This frowns refusal, that persuades to yield,&lt;BR&gt; Till Reason falls, and Passion takes the field,&lt;/b&gt;&lt;BR&gt; Then guard, oh! noble youth, the sliding heart,&lt;BR&gt; Sov'reigns are subjects to the master part;&lt;BR&gt; The ruling passion still maintains its post,&lt;BR&gt; Monarch o'er monarchs, and the mortal's lost.&lt;BR&gt;</Text>
        <Category>War</Category>
        <SubCategory>Struggle</SubCategory>
        <Context></Context>
        <Provenance>Searching HDIS for &quot;ruling passion&quot;</Provenance>
        <DoE>2004-05-25</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory></SSCategory>
        <Type>Metaphor; Personification</Type>
        <Theme></Theme>
        <Comments>&amp;bull;I've included twice: Struggle and Field</Comments>
        <Dictionary></Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>15088</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>5616</WorkID>
        <Metaphor>&quot; 'Twixt shame and passion floats the struggling mind, / To Virtue now, and now to vice inclin'd, / This frowns refusal, that persuades to yield, / Till Reason falls, and Passion takes the field&quot;</Metaphor>
        <Text>As varying Pleasure darts her smiles around,&lt;BR&gt; And strews her ruddiest rose-buds on the ground,&lt;BR&gt; As shines Love's nectar in Youth's flattering glass,&lt;BR&gt; And Nature gilds the minutes as they pass.&lt;BR&gt; Swift glides the heart from Virtue's fair intent,&lt;BR&gt; And faint Denial half implies consent.&lt;BR&gt;&lt;b&gt; 'Twixt shame and passion floats the struggling mind,&lt;BR&gt; To Virtue now, and now to vice inclin'd,&lt;BR&gt; This frowns refusal, that persuades to yield,&lt;BR&gt; Till Reason falls, and Passion takes the field,&lt;/b&gt;&lt;BR&gt; Then guard, oh! noble youth, the sliding heart,&lt;BR&gt; Sov'reigns are subjects to the master part;&lt;BR&gt; The ruling passion still maintains its post,&lt;BR&gt; Monarch o'er monarchs, and the mortal's lost.&lt;BR&gt;</Text>
        <Category>War</Category>
        <SubCategory>Field of Battle</SubCategory>
        <Context></Context>
        <Provenance>Searching HDIS for &quot;ruling passion&quot;</Provenance>
        <DoE>2004-05-25</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory></SSCategory>
        <Type>Metaphor; Personification</Type>
        <Theme></Theme>
        <Comments>&amp;bull;I've included twice: Struggle and Field</Comments>
        <Dictionary></Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>12094</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>4591</WorkID>
        <Metaphor>&quot; 'Why wouldst thou follow with delusive Art, / 'So poor a Conquest as a female heart?&quot;</Metaphor>
        <Text>'&lt;i&gt;Shalum&lt;/i&gt;, I know Thee more than mortal wise,&lt;BR&gt; 'Vers'd in the Earth, the Ocean, and the Skies:&lt;BR&gt; 'Thou know'st the various Virtues of the Soil,&lt;BR&gt; 'And which would mock, and which deserves the toil&lt;BR&gt; ''Tis thine to view the rolling Orbs on high,&lt;BR&gt; 'And trace the wandring Planets thro' the sky.&lt;BR&gt; 'Thy Thoughts are fix'd sublime, and far above&lt;BR&gt; 'The weak engagements of a Woman's Love.&lt;BR&gt; 'Oh! cease, and leave me to my self alone,&lt;BR&gt; 'Already happy in my Little Own.&lt;BR&gt;&lt;b&gt; 'Why wouldst thou follow with delusive Art,&lt;BR&gt; 'So poor a Conquest as a female heart?&lt;/b&gt;&lt;BR&gt; 'Still may thy labours with Success be paid;&lt;BR&gt; 'May Wood to Wood be joyn'd, and Shade to Shade.&lt;BR&gt; 'Great be thy Comfort in thy lov'd recess,&lt;BR&gt; 'But tempt not me to share, and make the Blessing less.</Text>
        <Category>War</Category>
        <SubCategory>Conquest</SubCategory>
        <Context></Context>
        <Provenance>Searching &quot;conque&quot; and &quot;heart&quot; in HDIS (Poetry)</Provenance>
        <DoE>2005-02-14</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory>Conquer Heart</SSCategory>
        <Type>Metaphor</Type>
        <Theme></Theme>
        <Comments>&amp;bull;C-H draws from the Second Edition. Find original edition REVISIT.</Comments>
        <Dictionary></Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>9472</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>3649</WorkID>
        <Metaphor>&quot; (Your Mind b'ing more transcendent than your State, / For while but Knees to this, Hearts bow to that,)&quot;</Metaphor>
        <Text>To you whose Dignity strikes us with aw,&lt;BR&gt; And whose far greater Judgment gives us law,&lt;BR&gt;&lt;b&gt; (Your Mind b'ing more transcendent than your State,&lt;BR&gt; For while but Knees to this, Hearts bow to that,)&lt;/b&gt;&lt;BR&gt; These humble Papers never durst come near,&lt;BR&gt; Had not your pow'rful Word bid them appear;&lt;BR&gt; In which such majesty, such sweetness dwells,&lt;BR&gt; As in one act obliges, and compels.&lt;BR&gt; None can dispute commands vouchsaf'd by you.&lt;BR&gt; What shall my fears then and confusion do?&lt;BR&gt; They must resign, and by their just pretence&lt;BR&gt; Some value set on my obedience.&lt;BR&gt; For in religious Duties, 'tis confest,&lt;BR&gt; The most Implicite are accepted best.&lt;BR&gt; If on that score your Highness will excuse&lt;BR&gt; This blushing tribute of an artless Muse,&lt;BR&gt; She may (encourag'd by your least regard,&lt;BR&gt; Which first can worth create, and then reward)&lt;BR&gt; At modest distance with improved strains&lt;BR&gt; That Mercy celebrate which now she gains.&lt;BR&gt; But should you that severer justice use,&lt;BR&gt; Which these too prompt Approches may produce,&lt;BR&gt; As the swift Hinde which hath escaped long,&lt;BR&gt; Believes a Vulgar shot would be a wrong;&lt;BR&gt; But wounded by a Prince falls without shame,&lt;BR&gt; And what in life she loses, gains in fame:&lt;BR&gt; So if a Ray from you chance to be sent,&lt;BR&gt; Which to consume, and not to warm, is meant;&lt;BR&gt; My trembling Muse at least more nobly dies,&lt;BR&gt; And falls by that a truer sacrifice.</Text>
        <Category>Government</Category>
        <SubCategory>State</SubCategory>
        <Context>I've included the entire poem</Context>
        <Provenance>Searching in HDIS (Poetry)</Provenance>
        <DoE>2005-04-20</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory></SSCategory>
        <Type>Metaphor</Type>
        <Theme></Theme>
        <Comments></Comments>
        <Dictionary></Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>9712</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>3761</WorkID>
        <Metaphor>&quot; A Crowd of Vertues fill your Princely Breast&quot;</Metaphor>
        <Text>&lt;i&gt;Hushai&lt;/i&gt; in Silence heard the Prince, and weigh'd&lt;BR&gt; Each word he spake, then to him thus reply'd;&lt;BR&gt; Great Prince, th' Almighty has to you been kind,&lt;BR&gt; Stamp'd Graces on your Body and your mind,&lt;BR&gt; As if he for your Head a Crown design'd.&lt;BR&gt; We shall not search into Fates Secret Womb,&lt;BR&gt; God alone knows the things that are to come;&lt;BR&gt; But should you never sit on &lt;i&gt;David&lt;/i&gt;'s Throne,&lt;BR&gt; 'Tis better to deserve than wear a Crown.&lt;BR&gt; Of Royal Blood, and of great Birth you are,&lt;BR&gt; Born under some benign auspicious Star,&lt;BR&gt; Lov'd by the best, and prais'd by every Tongue,&lt;BR&gt; The glorious Subject of each worthy Song:&lt;BR&gt; The young man's Wish, Joy of each Warlike Wight,&lt;BR&gt; The People's Darling, and the World's Delight.&lt;BR&gt;&lt;b&gt; A Crowd of Vertues fill your Princely Breast,&lt;/b&gt;&lt;BR&gt; And what appears more glorious than the rest,&lt;BR&gt; You are of Truth and Loyalty possest.&lt;BR&gt; That I would cherish in you, that would raise&lt;BR&gt; To an admired height, that I would chiefly praise.&lt;BR&gt; Let Fools and subtil Politicians scorn&lt;BR&gt; Fair Vertue, which doth best a Prince adorn:&lt;BR&gt; Whilst you her bright and shining Robes put on,&lt;BR&gt; You will appear more great than &lt;i&gt;Solomon&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;BR&gt; Let not Great Prince, the Fumes of Vulgar Praise,&lt;BR&gt; Your bolder Spirits to Ambition raise.&lt;BR&gt; We cannot see into the Mist of Fate,&lt;BR&gt; Till time brings forth, you must expecting wait;&lt;BR&gt; But Fortune, rather Providence, not Chance,&lt;BR&gt; The constant, stout, and wise doth still advance.&lt;BR&gt; Let your quick Eye be to her Motions ty'd;&lt;BR&gt; But still let Noble Vertue be your Guide:&lt;BR&gt; For when that God and Vertue points the way,&lt;BR&gt; There can be then no danger to obey.&lt;BR&gt; But here in Wisdom's School we ought to learn,&lt;BR&gt; How we 'twixt Good and Evil may discern,&lt;BR&gt; For noble Prince, you must true difference make,&lt;BR&gt; Lest for the one the other you mistake.&lt;BR&gt; You must not think you may your self advance,&lt;BR&gt; By laying hold on every proffer'd chance.&lt;BR&gt; Tho Fortune seems to smile, and egg you on,&lt;BR&gt; Let Vertue be your Rule and Guide alone.&lt;BR&gt; Thus &lt;i&gt;David&lt;/i&gt; for his Guide his Vertue took;&lt;BR&gt; Nor was by Fortune's proffer'd Kindness shook.&lt;BR&gt; His Vertue and his Loyalty did save&lt;BR&gt; King &lt;i&gt;Saul&lt;/i&gt;, when Fortune brought him to his Cave.&lt;BR&gt; And if that I may to you Counsel give,&lt;BR&gt; You should without a Crown for ever live,&lt;BR&gt; Rather than get it by the Peoples Lust,&lt;BR&gt; Or purchase it by ways that are unjust.&lt;BR&gt;&lt;i&gt;David&lt;/i&gt; your Ancestor, from whom you spring,&lt;BR&gt; Would never by Rebellion be made King;&lt;BR&gt; But long in &lt;i&gt;Gath&lt;/i&gt; a Warring Exile stay'd,&lt;BR&gt; Till for him God a lawful way had made.&lt;BR&gt; In &lt;i&gt;Hebron&lt;/i&gt;, full of Glory and Renown,&lt;BR&gt; He gain'd, at last, and not usurpt the Crown.&lt;BR&gt; By full Consent he did the same obtain,&lt;BR&gt; And Heav'n's anointing Oyl was not in vain.&lt;BR&gt; I once did seem to &lt;i&gt;Amazia&lt;/i&gt; dear,&lt;BR&gt; Who me above m'ambitious hopes did rear;&lt;BR&gt; I serv'd him then according to my skill,&lt;BR&gt; And bow'd my Mind unto my Soveraign's Will.&lt;BR&gt; Too neer the Soveraign Image then I stood,&lt;BR&gt; To think that every Line and Stroke was good.&lt;BR&gt; Some Daubers I endeavour'd to remove,&lt;BR&gt; And to amend their artless Errours strove.&lt;BR&gt; My Skill in secret these with slander wound;&lt;BR&gt; With every Line I drew still faults were found;&lt;BR&gt; Till wearied, I at last my Work gave o're.&lt;BR&gt; And &lt;i&gt;Amazia&lt;/i&gt; (I shall say no more)&lt;BR&gt; Did me to my lov'd Privacy restore.&lt;BR&gt; For this they think I must my Vertue change,&lt;BR&gt; For Envy, Malice, and for sweet Revenge.&lt;BR&gt; Me by themselves they judge, who would do so,&lt;BR&gt; And cause the King suspect me for his Foe.&lt;BR&gt; But by th'advice I give, you best will find&lt;BR&gt; Th'Integrity and Plainness of my Mind;&lt;BR&gt; And that I harbour not that vile intent&lt;BR&gt; Their Poets and their Malice do invent.&lt;BR&gt; Far be't from me, to be like Cursed &lt;i&gt;Cham&lt;/i&gt;;&lt;BR&gt; A good Son strives to hide his Father's shame.&lt;BR&gt; A King, the Father of his Country is;&lt;BR&gt; His shame is every Act he doth amiss.&lt;BR&gt; Good and just Kings God's Image bear; but when&lt;BR&gt; Their Frailties let us see they are but Men,&lt;BR&gt; We cannot every Action so applaud,&lt;BR&gt; As if it came from an unerring God.&lt;BR&gt; Kings have their Passions, and deceiv'd may be,&lt;BR&gt; When b'others Ears and Eyes they hear and see:&lt;BR&gt; For Sycophants, of Courts the Bane and Curse,&lt;BR&gt; Make all things better than they are, or worse.&lt;BR&gt; To Evil prone, to Mischief ever bent,&lt;BR&gt; Th'all Objects with false colours represent;&lt;BR&gt; The Guilty clear, condemn the Innocent.&lt;BR&gt; Thus, noble Prince, they you and me accuse&lt;BR&gt; With all the Venome Malice can infuse.&lt;BR&gt;&lt;i&gt;Baal&lt;/i&gt;'s Priests, Hell, and our Foes, new Arts have got,&lt;BR&gt; The filthy Reliques of their former Plot;&lt;BR&gt; Whereby they would our Lives in danger bring,&lt;BR&gt; And make us cursed Traytors to the King.&lt;BR&gt; What mayn't these cunning men hope to atchieve,&lt;BR&gt; When by their Arts few men their Plot believe?&lt;BR&gt; When b'horrid ways, not known to &lt;i&gt;Jews&lt;/i&gt; before,&lt;BR&gt; Their Plot's transform'd, and laid now at our door?&lt;BR&gt; But fear not, Sir, we have a sure Defence,&lt;BR&gt; The Peoples Love, God, Law, and Innocence.&lt;BR&gt; Keep fast your Vertue, and you shall be blest,&lt;BR&gt; And let alone to God and Time the rest.</Text>
        <Category>Population</Category>
        <SubCategory>Crowd</SubCategory>
        <Context></Context>
        <Provenance>Searching &quot;breast&quot; and &quot;crowd&quot; in HDIS (Poetry)</Provenance>
        <DoE>2006-03-08</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory></SSCategory>
        <Type>Personification</Type>
        <Theme></Theme>
        <Comments></Comments>
        <Dictionary>Inhabitants</Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>14632</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>5474</WorkID>
        <Metaphor>&quot; A father, husband, brother sorrowing weep, / Whose hearts engraven thy fair virtues keep.&quot;</Metaphor>
        <Text>Far in thy life below that high sphere plac'd&lt;BR&gt; Where grandeur dwells with wealth and titles grac'd,&lt;BR&gt; Fulfilling in the rank bestow'd by fate&lt;BR&gt; The silent virtues of thy humbler state;&lt;BR&gt; Like the fair rose that blooms and falls to earth&lt;BR&gt; In the same vale which first beheld its birth,&lt;BR&gt; Unseen, unknown beyond that narrow space&lt;BR&gt; Where heaven to thee indulgent fixt thy place;&lt;BR&gt; Thou art not now bewailed in thy death&lt;BR&gt; By pride's vain pomp or flattery's idle breath:&lt;BR&gt; Thy memory more grateful praise obtains,&lt;BR&gt; When o'er the grave which hides thy cold remains&lt;BR&gt;&lt;b&gt; A father, husband, brother sorrowing weep,&lt;BR&gt; Whose hearts engraven thy fair virtues keep.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;BR&gt;</Text>
        <Category>Writing</Category>
        <SubCategory>Engraving</SubCategory>
        <Context></Context>
        <Provenance>Searching in &quot;heart&quot; and &quot;engrav&quot; in HDIS (Poetry)</Provenance>
        <DoE>2005-03-08</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory></SSCategory>
        <Type>Metaphor</Type>
        <Theme></Theme>
        <Comments>&amp;bull;Here the engraving suggests the memorialization of the grave stone.</Comments>
        <Dictionary></Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>10653</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>4141</WorkID>
        <Metaphor>&quot; All Hearts and Eyes she conquers with her Charms&quot;</Metaphor>
        <Text>Remote from &lt;i&gt;France&lt;/i&gt; (the &lt;i&gt;Channel&lt;/i&gt; flows between)&lt;BR&gt; White Cliffs, tall Tow'rs, and glitt'ring Spires are seen:&lt;BR&gt; A lovely Isle adorns the Subject Seas,&lt;BR&gt; Rich in the Product of a Godlike Race,&lt;BR&gt; All brave and stout as &lt;i&gt;Mars&lt;/i&gt; as &lt;i&gt;Venus&lt;/i&gt; fair,&lt;BR&gt; Gentle in Peace, and terrible in War:&lt;BR&gt; Great amidst Changes, fix'd in high Renown,&lt;BR&gt; No other Victors but themselves they own;&lt;BR&gt; What Nation can such Troops of Victors boast,&lt;BR&gt; Reviving all that &lt;i&gt;Greece&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;Rome&lt;/i&gt; have lost?&lt;BR&gt; All court their Love, or to their Valour bow:&lt;BR&gt; No Bounds their Arms, no end their Triumphs know,&lt;BR&gt; Fond of their Laws, and willing to obey,&lt;BR&gt; They temper Freedom with Imperial Sway:&lt;BR&gt; Brave as in Fight, in Arts and Counsels great,&lt;BR&gt; They add new Strength and Beauty to the State;&lt;BR&gt; Religion, free from Pomp, yet still Divine,&lt;BR&gt; Does in the purest, brightest Colours shine;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;b&gt; All Hearts and Eyes she conquers with her Charms&lt;/b&gt;,&lt;BR&gt; And with her Love the willing People warms,&lt;BR&gt; Plenty and Riches crown the smiling Plains;&lt;BR&gt; Till'd by a Race of strong industrious Swains.&lt;BR&gt; Proud &lt;i&gt;Neptune&lt;/i&gt; bends beneath their awful Sway,&lt;BR&gt; And all the Winds and Waves their Sails obey,&lt;BR&gt; Beneath whose lofty Tow'rs the Billows foam,&lt;BR&gt; Conveying endless Wealth and Plenty home,&lt;BR&gt; Or carrying dread and hostile Arms afar,&lt;BR&gt; That speak in Thunder and in Flames make War:&lt;BR&gt;&lt;i&gt;Tethys&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;Jason&lt;/i&gt;, and the &lt;i&gt;Grecian&lt;/i&gt; Band&lt;BR&gt; Of &lt;i&gt;Argonauts&lt;/i&gt;, for Naval Valour fam'd,&lt;BR&gt; Must yield to these, whilst on their fruitful Shores&lt;BR&gt; They empty, from both Worlds, the noblest Stores.&lt;BR&gt;</Text>
        <Category>War</Category>
        <SubCategory>Conquest</SubCategory>
        <Context></Context>
        <Provenance>Searching &quot;conque&quot; and &quot;heart&quot; in HDIS (Poetry)</Provenance>
        <DoE>2005-02-10</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory>Conquer Heart</SSCategory>
        <Type>Metaphor</Type>
        <Theme></Theme>
        <Comments></Comments>
        <Dictionary></Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>14237</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>5304</WorkID>
        <Metaphor>&quot; All my heart is open wide, / Every bar is thrown aside&quot;</Metaphor>
        <Text>A RANT&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;Wine, I feel thy rapt'ring power!&lt;BR&gt; Thine is all the present hour.&lt;BR&gt; Strong Delight tumultuous reigns,&lt;BR&gt; And throbs throughout my bursting veins.&lt;BR&gt;&lt;b&gt; All my heart is open wide,&lt;BR&gt; Every bar is thrown aside.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;BR&gt; Prudence hence; it loaths to trace&lt;BR&gt; The features of thy simpering face,&lt;BR&gt; Thy sober-measur'd gait to spy,&lt;BR&gt; And leaden joy-forbidding eye.&lt;BR&gt; Prudence hence; thy laws I scorn,&lt;BR&gt; Thou of mean Deceit art born,&lt;BR&gt; By sly Hypocrisy begot;&lt;BR&gt; Noble Frankness heeds thee not.&lt;BR&gt; Yet though all my sallying soul&lt;BR&gt; Expatiates wide, and hates controul;&lt;BR&gt; Though my thoughts unbridled dare&lt;BR&gt; Forward fly in wild career;&lt;BR&gt; In their most impetuous course,&lt;BR&gt; Let me, Reason, own thy force:&lt;BR&gt; Though thou totter'st on thy &lt;b&gt;throne&lt;/b&gt;,&lt;BR&gt; Let me call thee still my own;&lt;BR&gt; For so mad I would not be,&lt;BR&gt; As quite to lose the sight of thee.&lt;BR&gt;</Text>
        <Category>Architecture</Category>
        <SubCategory>Door</SubCategory>
        <Context>I've included the entire poem</Context>
        <Provenance>HDIS</Provenance>
        <DoE>2004-07-19</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory>Bar</SSCategory>
        <Type>Metaphor</Type>
        <Theme></Theme>
        <Comments></Comments>
        <Dictionary></Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>15254</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>5723</WorkID>
        <Metaphor>&quot; And each unwelcome mental guest, / Lay dormant in the human breast&quot;</Metaphor>
        <Text>In such an age, a guileless twain,&lt;BR&gt; Roger and Sue, illum'd the plain;&lt;BR&gt; Unbred in academic schools,&lt;BR&gt; They follow'd Reason and her rules;&lt;BR&gt; In all the paths of prudence trod,&lt;BR&gt; And lov'd their friend, and fear'd their God.&lt;BR&gt; Then Freedom rov'd the mountain's side,&lt;BR&gt; And Innocence was all their pride;&lt;BR&gt; No sadd'ning love-lorn maiden then,&lt;BR&gt; Bemoan'd the perfidy of men;&lt;BR&gt; For Virtue bless'd the rural throng,&lt;BR&gt; Inform'd their hearts, and fed their song.&lt;BR&gt; No vicious tenets broke their rest,&lt;BR&gt; (Like missives from the peevish east,&lt;BR&gt; Blighting the wholesome rip'ning ear)&lt;BR&gt; Or laid the basis of a tear.&lt;BR&gt; The dirty passions of the mind,&lt;BR&gt; Were then subdu'd, controul'd, confin'd;&lt;BR&gt; Pale Fear, and all her haggard train,&lt;BR&gt; That generate and nurture pain,&lt;BR&gt;&lt;b&gt; And each unwelcome mental guest,&lt;BR&gt; Lay dormant in the human breast;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;BR&gt; No Cypress then deform'd the brow,&lt;BR&gt; Or mourning willow noted woe;&lt;BR&gt; Or broken oaths made maids forlorn,&lt;BR&gt; For Woe and Vice were then unborn;&lt;BR&gt; Their lives unchoak'd with baneful weeds,&lt;BR&gt; Pass'd in a change of worthy deeds;&lt;BR&gt; The sacred commerce fixt and known,&lt;BR&gt; Supreme delight was all their own.&lt;BR&gt;</Text>
        <Category>Population</Category>
        <SubCategory>Guest</SubCategory>
        <Context></Context>
        <Provenance></Provenance>
        <DoE>2004-06-22</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory></SSCategory>
        <Type>Personification</Type>
        <Theme></Theme>
        <Comments></Comments>
        <Dictionary>Inhabitants</Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>14052</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>5223</WorkID>
        <Metaphor>&quot; And my heart, within me burning, / Is become like melting wax.&quot;</Metaphor>
        <Text>Loose, as to a fluid turning,&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; Are my bones, my joints relax,&lt;BR&gt;&lt;b&gt; And my heart, within me burning,&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; Is become like melting wax.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;BR&gt;</Text>
        <Category>Uncategorized</Category>
        <SubCategory>Wax</SubCategory>
        <Context></Context>
        <Provenance>Searching &quot;wax&quot; and &quot;heart&quot; in HDIS (Poetry)</Provenance>
        <DoE>2005-03-27</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory>Melting</SSCategory>
        <Type>Simile</Type>
        <Theme>Psalm 22</Theme>
        <Comments>&amp;bull;Another heart like melting wax!&lt;BR&gt;&amp;bull;Cross-reference: Blackmore, Chamberlayne, Darby, Frere, Merrick, Parnell, Smart, Wesleys.</Comments>
        <Dictionary></Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>15571</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>5842</WorkID>
        <Metaphor>&quot; And now these D&amp;aelig;mons of the captive mind / Him to the drery Cave of Discontent resignd&quot;</Metaphor>
        <Text>  On Dissipation still this Treachor waits,&lt;BR&gt;    Obsequiously behind at distance due;&lt;BR&gt;  And still to Discontents accurse gates,&lt;BR&gt;    The House of Sorrow, these ungodlie Two,&lt;BR&gt;    Conduct their fainty thralls--Great things to do&lt;BR&gt;  The Knight resolvd, but never yet could find&lt;BR&gt;    The proper time, while still his miseries grew:&lt;BR&gt;&lt;b&gt;  And now these D&amp;aelig;mons of the captive mind&lt;BR&gt;Him to the drery Cave of Discontent resignd&lt;/b&gt;,&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;  Deep in the wyldes of Faerie Lond it lay;&lt;BR&gt;    Wide was the mouth, the roofe all rudely rent;&lt;BR&gt;  Some parts receive, and some exclude the Day,&lt;BR&gt;    For deepe beneath the hill its caverns went:&lt;BR&gt;    The ragged walls with lightning seemd ybrent,&lt;BR&gt;  And loathlie vermin ever crept the flore:&lt;BR&gt;    Yet all in sight, with towres and castles gent,&lt;BR&gt;  A beauteous lawnskepe rose afore the dore,&lt;BR&gt;The which to view so fayre the Captives grieved sore.</Text>
        <Category>Uncategorized</Category>
        <SubCategory>Captive</SubCategory>
        <Context></Context>
        <Provenance>Searching in HDIS (Poetry)</Provenance>
        <DoE>2006-01-18</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory></SSCategory>
        <Type>Metaphor</Type>
        <Theme></Theme>
        <Comments></Comments>
        <Dictionary>Metal</Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>12908</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>4831</WorkID>
        <Metaphor>&quot; And powerfully the message seal / On the believing heart&quot;</Metaphor>
        <Text>&amp;nbsp; Thou only didst reveal,&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; How good in Christ Thou art,&lt;BR&gt;&lt;b&gt; And powerfully the message seal&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; On the believing heart&lt;/b&gt;:&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; Thine is the work of grace,&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; Lord, I the whole disclaim,&lt;BR&gt; All glory, love, and thanks, and praise&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; Be paid to Jesu's name.&lt;BR&gt;</Text>
        <Category>Uncategorized</Category>
        <SubCategory>Stamping and Sealing</SubCategory>
        <Context>Part II. After Preaching</Context>
        <Provenance>Searching &quot;seal&quot; and &quot;heart&quot; in HDIS (Poetry)</Provenance>
        <DoE>2005-04-19</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory></SSCategory>
        <Type>Metaphor</Type>
        <Theme></Theme>
        <Comments></Comments>
        <Dictionary></Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>11249</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>4314</WorkID>
        <Metaphor>&quot; And see how Nature, bountiful and kind, / Stamps the Paternal Image on his Mind&quot;</Metaphor>
        <Text>And Thou, his pious Consort, here below,&lt;BR&gt; Lavish of Grief, and prodigal of Woe:&lt;BR&gt; Oh! choak thy Griefs, thy rising Sighs suppress,&lt;BR&gt; Nor let thy Sorrows violate his Peace.&lt;BR&gt; This Rage of Anguish, that disdains Relief,&lt;BR&gt; Dims his bright Joys, with some Allay of Grief.&lt;BR&gt; Look on his dearest Pledge, he left behind,&lt;BR&gt;&lt;b&gt; And see how Nature, bountiful and kind,&lt;BR&gt; Stamps the Paternal Image on his Mind.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;BR&gt; Oh! may the hereditary Virtues run&lt;BR&gt; In fair Succession, to adorn the Son;&lt;BR&gt; The last best Hopes of &lt;i&gt;Albion&lt;/i&gt;'s Realms to grace,&lt;BR&gt; And form the Hero worthy of his Race:&lt;BR&gt; Some Means at last by &lt;i&gt;Britain&lt;/i&gt; may be found,&lt;BR&gt; To dry her Tears, and close her bleeding Wound.&lt;BR&gt; And if the Muse thro' future Times can see,&lt;BR&gt; Fair Youth, thy Father shall revive in thee:&lt;BR&gt; Thou shalt the wond'ring Nation's Hopes engage,&lt;BR&gt; To rise the &lt;i&gt;Stanhope&lt;/i&gt; of the future Age.</Text>
        <Category>Uncategorized</Category>
        <SubCategory>Stamping</SubCategory>
        <Context></Context>
        <Provenance>Searching &quot;stamp&quot; and &quot;mind&quot; in HDIS (Poetry)</Provenance>
        <DoE>2005-04-07</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory>Image</SSCategory>
        <Type>Metaphor</Type>
        <Theme></Theme>
        <Comments></Comments>
        <Dictionary></Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>14197</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>5279</WorkID>
        <Metaphor>&quot; And sure forgiveness sealest / On all our waiting hearts,&quot;</Metaphor>
        <Text>Father, till Thou revealest&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; Truth in our inward parts,&lt;BR&gt;&lt;b&gt; And sure forgiveness sealest&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; On all our waiting hearts,&lt;/b&gt;&lt;BR&gt; Us by Thy fear o'erawing&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; From evil far remove,&lt;BR&gt; And let us feel Thee drawing&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; Our hearts with cords of love.&lt;BR&gt;</Text>
        <Category>Uncategorized</Category>
        <SubCategory>Seal</SubCategory>
        <Context>For the Evening</Context>
        <Provenance>Searching &quot;seal&quot; and &quot;heart&quot; in HDIS (Poetry)</Provenance>
        <DoE>2005-04-19</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory></SSCategory>
        <Type>Metaphor</Type>
        <Theme></Theme>
        <Comments>&amp;bull;Bibliography from http://www.bautz.de/bbkl/w/wesley_c.shtml</Comments>
        <Dictionary></Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>16049</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>6055</WorkID>
        <Metaphor>&quot; As a record of Love let it ever remain; / My bosom thy tablet--thy pencil a dart.&quot;</Metaphor>
        <Text>When the shadows of twilight steal over the plain,&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; And the Nightingale pours its lorn plaint in the grove;&lt;BR&gt; Ah! will not the fondness that thrills thro' the strain,&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; Then recall to my mind his dear accents of Love!&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;Then spare, thou sweet Urchin, thou soother of pain,&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; Oh! spare the soft picture engrav'd on my heart;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;b&gt; As a record of Love let it ever remain;&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; My bosom thy tablet--thy pencil a dart.&lt;/b&gt;</Text>
        <Category>Visual Arts</Category>
        <SubCategory>Tablet</SubCategory>
        <Context>Final Stanzas. &lt;BR&gt;The &quot;sweet Urchin&quot; is Love.</Context>
        <Provenance>Searching in HDIS (Poetry)</Provenance>
        <DoE>2005-03-08</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory></SSCategory>
        <Type>Metaphor</Type>
        <Theme></Theme>
        <Comments></Comments>
        <Dictionary></Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>12095</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>4592</WorkID>
        <Metaphor>&quot; At Eyes alone our Beaus direct their art, / Nor know the nobler Conquest of the Heart.&quot;</Metaphor>
        <Text>Our Youth of old were wont the Fair to move,&lt;BR&gt; By manly Vigour, and athletic Love:&lt;BR&gt; With healthful Nerves they prest the glowing Dame,&lt;BR&gt; Not squeal'd in sing-song Lays a sickly Flame.&lt;BR&gt;&lt;b&gt; At Eyes alone our Beaus direct their art,&lt;BR&gt; Nor know the nobler Conquest of the Heart.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;BR&gt; With her own Arms a Mistress they pursue,&lt;BR&gt; Snuff, Powder, Patches, Paste, and Billets doux.&lt;BR&gt; Man's hardy mould is in his Habit lost,&lt;BR&gt; And Beaus assume the Softness of their Toast.&lt;BR&gt;</Text>
        <Category>War</Category>
        <SubCategory>Conquest</SubCategory>
        <Context></Context>
        <Provenance>Searching &quot;conque&quot; and &quot;heart&quot; in HDIS (Poetry)</Provenance>
        <DoE>2005-02-14</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory>Conquer Heart</SSCategory>
        <Type>Metaphor</Type>
        <Theme></Theme>
        <Comments>&amp;bull;C-H draws from the Second Edition. Find original edition REVISIT.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;bull;INTEREST describes the fall away from athletic conquest to a softer, but not nobler, sort.</Comments>
        <Dictionary></Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>10281</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>3954</WorkID>
        <Metaphor>&quot; August and Open, as the Hero's Mind, / Be her capacious Courts design'd&quot;</Metaphor>
        <Text>XXVII.&lt;b&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;/b&gt;Where the white Towers and ancient Roofs did stand,&lt;BR&gt; Remains of Wolsey's or great Henry's Hand,&lt;BR&gt; To Age now yielding, or devour'd by Flame;&lt;BR&gt; Let a young Phenix raise her tow'ring Head:&lt;BR&gt; Her Wings with lengthen'd Honour let Her spread;&lt;BR&gt; And by her Greatness show her Builder's Fame.&lt;b&gt;&lt;BR&gt; August and Open, as the Hero's Mind,&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; Be her capacious Courts design'd:&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; &lt;/b&gt;Let ev'ry Sacred Pillar bear&lt;BR&gt; Trophies of Arms, and Monuments of War.&lt;BR&gt; The King shall there in Parian Marble breath,&lt;BR&gt; His Shoulder bleeding fresh: and at His Feet&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; Disarm'd shall lye the threat'ning Death:&lt;BR&gt; (For so was saving Jove's Decree compleat.)&lt;BR&gt; Behind, That Angel shall be plac'd, whose Shield&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; Sav'd Europe, in the Blow repell'd:&lt;BR&gt; On the firm Basis, from his Oozy Bed&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; Boyn shall raise his Laurell'd Head;&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; And his Immortal Stream be known,&lt;BR&gt; Artfully waving thro' the wounded Stone.&lt;BR&gt;(p. 174, ll. 360-9)</Text>
        <Category>Architecture</Category>
        <SubCategory>Courtyards</SubCategory>
        <Context></Context>
        <Provenance>Searching HDIS (Poetry)</Provenance>
        <DoE>2004-02-25</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory></SSCategory>
        <Type>Simile</Type>
        <Theme></Theme>
        <Comments>&amp;bull;Editors: &quot;P takes from Horace's &lt;i&gt;Carmen Secularae&lt;/i&gt; little more than the title and general theme&quot; (p. 876).&lt;BR&gt;&amp;bull;Variant gives &quot;Open, yet Solid, as the Builder's Mind&quot; for l. 366. </Comments>
        <Dictionary></Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>12214</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>4638</WorkID>
        <Metaphor>&quot; Be mindful of Thy gracious word, / And stamp me with Thy Spirit's seal.&quot;</Metaphor>
        <Text>Holy, and true, and righteous Lord,&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; I wait to prove Thy perfect will;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;b&gt; Be mindful of Thy gracious word,&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; And stamp me with Thy Spirit's seal.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;BR&gt;</Text>
        <Category>Uncategorized</Category>
        <SubCategory>Stamping</SubCategory>
        <Context>Part II</Context>
        <Provenance>Searching &quot;stamp&quot; and &quot;mind&quot; in HDIS (Poetry); found again &quot;seal&quot;</Provenance>
        <DoE>2005-04-07</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory>Seal</SSCategory>
        <Type>Metaphor</Type>
        <Theme></Theme>
        <Comments></Comments>
        <Dictionary></Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>14192</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>5274</WorkID>
        <Metaphor>&quot; Be mindful of Thy gracious word, / And stamp me with Thy Spirit's seal.&quot;</Metaphor>
        <Text>Holy, and true, and righteous Lord,&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; I wait to prove Thy perfect will;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;b&gt; Be mindful of Thy gracious word,&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; And stamp me with Thy Spirit's seal.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;BR&gt;</Text>
        <Category>Uncategorized</Category>
        <SubCategory>Stamping</SubCategory>
        <Context>The Plurality and Trinity of Persons.</Context>
        <Provenance>Searching &quot;stamp&quot; and &quot;mind&quot; in HDIS (Poetry)</Provenance>
        <DoE>2005-04-07</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory>Seal</SSCategory>
        <Type>Metaphor</Type>
        <Theme></Theme>
        <Comments>&amp;bull;INTEREST: Plurality of person? (Locke and Identity issues...)</Comments>
        <Dictionary></Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>14709</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>5488</WorkID>
        <Metaphor>&quot; Before my wondering sense new phantoms dance, / And stamp their horrid shapes upon my brain&lt;b&gt;&quot;&lt;/b&gt;</Metaphor>
        <Text>&lt;b&gt; Before my wondering sense new phantoms dance,&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; And stamp their horrid shapes upon my brain&lt;/b&gt;--&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; A wretch with jealous brow, and eyes askance,&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; Feeds all in secret on his bosom pain.&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;Fond love, fierce hate assail;&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;Alternate they prevail:&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; While conscious pride and shame with rage conspire,&lt;BR&gt; And urge the latent spark to flames of torturing fire.&lt;BR&gt;</Text>
        <Category>Uncategorized</Category>
        <SubCategory>Dancing Phantoms</SubCategory>
        <Context></Context>
        <Provenance>Searching &quot;stamp&quot; and &quot;brain&quot; in HDIS (Poetry)</Provenance>
        <DoE>2005-04-11</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory></SSCategory>
        <Type>Personification</Type>
        <Theme></Theme>
        <Comments></Comments>
        <Dictionary></Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>14710</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>5488</WorkID>
        <Metaphor>&quot; Before my wondering sense new phantoms dance, / And stamp their horrid shapes upon my brain&lt;b&gt;&quot;&lt;/b&gt;</Metaphor>
        <Text>&lt;b&gt; Before my wondering sense new phantoms dance,&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; And stamp their horrid shapes upon my brain&lt;/b&gt;--&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; A wretch with jealous brow, and eyes askance,&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; Feeds all in secret on his bosom pain.&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;Fond love, fierce hate assail;&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;Alternate they prevail:&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; While conscious pride and shame with rage conspire,&lt;BR&gt; And urge the latent spark to flames of torturing fire.&lt;BR&gt;</Text>
        <Category>Uncategorized</Category>
        <SubCategory>Stamping</SubCategory>
        <Context></Context>
        <Provenance>Searching &quot;stamp&quot; and &quot;brain&quot; in HDIS (Poetry)</Provenance>
        <DoE>2005-04-11</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory>Shapes</SSCategory>
        <Type>Metaphor</Type>
        <Theme></Theme>
        <Comments></Comments>
        <Dictionary></Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>15939</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>6000</WorkID>
        <Metaphor>&quot; Bless'd be that Eye which dropp'd the friendly tear, / That sign'd each truth, and stamp'd the Soul sincere!&quot;</Metaphor>
        <Text>Bless'd be that Heart which felt a Father's care,&lt;BR&gt; While warning Youth to shun Sin's fatal snare!&lt;BR&gt;&lt;b&gt; Bless'd be that Eye which dropp'd the friendly tear,&lt;BR&gt; That sign'd each truth, and stamp'd the Soul sincere!&lt;/b&gt;&lt;BR&gt; Bless'd be that Tongue whose broken pathos prov'd&lt;BR&gt; How much was felt, and fear'd, and hop'd, and lov'd!&lt;BR&gt; Thrice happy Youth! would they those truths attend,&lt;BR&gt; That mark'd Thee Pastor--Parent--Guardian--Friend!&lt;BR&gt; 'Twas god-like Love that urg'd thy pious plan,&lt;BR&gt; Those Angel-sentiments, and tears of Man!&lt;BR&gt; Like Heav'n's wing'd fires thy warm affections flew,&lt;BR&gt; And forc'd each eye to drop celestial dew,&lt;BR&gt; While spreading kerchiefs caught the silent show'r,&lt;BR&gt; And, like bright banners, prov'd thy conqu'ring pow'r--&lt;BR&gt; All drooping heads, and streaming eyes, confess'd&lt;BR&gt; The inward workings of each labouring breast;&lt;BR&gt; Except a few fantastic Apes alone,&lt;BR&gt; Whose heads were feather, and whose hearts were stone.</Text>
        <Category>Uncategorized</Category>
        <SubCategory>Stamping</SubCategory>
        <Context></Context>
        <Provenance>Searching &quot;stamp&quot; and &quot;soul&quot; in HDIS (Poetry)</Provenance>
        <DoE>2005-04-08</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory></SSCategory>
        <Type>Metaphor</Type>
        <Theme></Theme>
        <Comments></Comments>
        <Dictionary></Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>15180</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>5694</WorkID>
        <Metaphor>&quot; Blest be that pencil, every art be blest, / That stamps his image deeper on our breast!&quot;</Metaphor>
        <Text>Thou friend! yet left me of the choicer few,&lt;BR&gt; Whom grief's fond eyes with growing love review;&lt;BR&gt; O thou! whom mutal sorrow will incline&lt;BR&gt; To mix thy sympathetic sighs with mine;&lt;BR&gt; Still be it ours to pay, with just regret,&lt;BR&gt; At Friendship's facred shrine our common debt!&lt;BR&gt; Tho' doom'd (so Heaven ordains) to see no more&lt;BR&gt; The gentle Being, whom we both deplore;&lt;BR&gt; Painting shall still, sweet soothing art! supply&lt;BR&gt; A form so precious in Affection's eye.&lt;BR&gt; Ah! little thought we, in that happier hour,&lt;BR&gt; When our gay Muse rehears'd the Pencil's power;&lt;BR&gt; To mourn that form in cold obstruction laid,&lt;BR&gt; And see him only by the pencil's aid!&lt;BR&gt;&lt;b&gt; Blest be that pencil, every art be blest,&lt;BR&gt; That stamps his image deeper on our breast!&lt;/b&gt;</Text>
        <Category>Uncategorized</Category>
        <SubCategory>Stamping</SubCategory>
        <Context></Context>
        <Provenance>Searching &quot;stamp&quot; and &quot;breast&quot; in HDIS (Poetry)</Provenance>
        <DoE>2005-04-11</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory>Image</SSCategory>
        <Type>Metaphor</Type>
        <Theme></Theme>
        <Comments></Comments>
        <Dictionary></Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>11241</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>4308</WorkID>
        <Metaphor>&quot; But &lt;i&gt;Adam's&lt;/i&gt; Soul being put in his Body, his Brain was a &lt;i&gt;Tabula rasa, &lt;/i&gt;as White Paper, had no Impressions in it, but such as either God put in it, or such as came to him by his Senses.&quot;</Metaphor>
        <Text>The surest way to find out what this &lt;i&gt;Image &lt;/i&gt;was at first, is to consider, what the New Testament says of it, when we come to be restored to it. &lt;i&gt;We must put on the new Man&lt;/i&gt;, &lt;i&gt;after the image of him that created him&lt;/i&gt;; or as elsewhere, the &lt;i&gt;new man in righteousness and true holiness&lt;/i&gt;. This then was the &lt;i&gt;Image of God&lt;/i&gt;, in which Man was at first made. Nor ought the Image of God to be considered only as an Expression that imports only our representing him here on Earth, and having Dominion over the Creatures: For in &lt;i&gt;Genesis&lt;/i&gt; the Creation of Man in the image of God, is expressed as a thing different from his Dominion over the Creatures, which seems to be given to him as a consequent of it. The image of God seems to be this, That the Soul of man was a Being of another Sort and Order than all those material Beings till then made, which were neither capable of Thought nor Liberty, in which respect the Soul was made after the &lt;i&gt;Image of God&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;b&gt; But &lt;/b&gt;&lt;i&gt;Adam's&lt;/i&gt;&lt;b&gt; Soul being put in his Body, his Brain was a &lt;/b&gt;&lt;i&gt;Tabula rasa, &lt;/i&gt;&lt;b&gt;as White Paper, had no Impressions in it, but such as either God put in it, or such as came to him by his Senses&lt;/b&gt;. A Man born deaf and blind, newly come to hear and see, is not a more Ignorant and Amazed-like Creature than &lt;i&gt;Adam&lt;/i&gt; must have been, if God had not conveyed some great Impressions into him; [end page 110] such as first the acknowledging and obeying him as his Maker, and then the managing his Body so as to make it an instrument, by which he could make use of and observe Creation. There is no reason to think that his Body was at first inclined to Appetite, and that his Mind was apt to serve his Body, but that both were restrained by supernatural Assistances: It is much more natural and more agreeable to the Words of the &lt;i&gt;Wiseman&lt;/i&gt;, to think that &lt;i&gt;God made man upright&lt;/i&gt;, that his Body craved modestly, and that his Mind was both Judge and Master of those Cravings; and if a natural Hypothesis may be offered, but only as an Hypothesis, it may be supposed, That a Man's Blood was naturally low and cool, but that it was capable of a vast Inflammation and Elevation, by which a Man's Powers might be exalted to much higher Degrees of Knowledge and Capacity: The Animal Spirits receiving their Quality from that of the Blood, a new and a strong Fermentation in the Blood might raise them, and by consequence exalt a man to a much greater sublimity of Thought: But with that it might dispose him to be easily inflamed by Appetites and Passions, it might put him under the power of his Body, and make his Body much more apt to be fired at outward objects, which might sink all Spiritual and pure Ideas in him, and raise gross ones with much Fury and Rapidity. Hereby his whole Frame might be corrupted, and that might go so deep in him, that all those who descended from him, might be defiled by it, as we see Madness and some Chronical Diseases pass from Parents to Children.&lt;BR&gt;(pp. 110-1)k</Text>
        <Category>Writing</Category>
        <SubCategory>Tabula Rasa</SubCategory>
        <Context>Commentary on Article 9</Context>
        <Provenance>Searching &quot;tabula rasa&quot; in ECCO</Provenance>
        <DoE>2006-10-09</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory></SSCategory>
        <Type>Metaphor</Type>
        <Theme>Blank Slate</Theme>
        <Comments>&amp;bull;Marginal citation of Gen 1:27-8&lt;BR&gt;&amp;bull;INTEREST. USE in entry. Another case of an innatist blank slate. The following mixture of natural philosophy and biblical exegesis is worth rereading.</Comments>
        <Dictionary>Writing</Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>10770</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>4166</WorkID>
        <Metaphor>&quot; But as the Passions of the Human Mind&lt;b&gt; / &lt;/b&gt;Must strictly be to Nature's Laws confin'd,&quot;</Metaphor>
        <Text>Well therefore may our Author own his Fears&lt;BR&gt; To tread, where Avon's Swan so oft appears;&lt;BR&gt; To Night he aims to draw Domestick Life,&lt;BR&gt; A Vicious Husband, and a Virtuous Wife;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;b&gt; But as the Passions of the Human Mind&lt;BR&gt; Must strictly be to Nature's Laws confin'd,&lt;/b&gt;&lt;BR&gt; He labours that his Wit shou'd timely flow,&lt;BR&gt; And not the Business of the Scene forego.&lt;BR&gt; A seasonable Jest may be allow'd,&lt;BR&gt; But nothing that's Impertinent, is Good;&lt;BR&gt; And yet he writes to please, and frankly owns,&lt;BR&gt; Good Plays have very seldom met your Frowns;&lt;BR&gt; Yet bad ones oft Succeed, and Harlequin&lt;BR&gt; Has trick'd your Judgment, when he cur'd your Spleen</Text>
        <Category>Government</Category>
        <SubCategory>Law</SubCategory>
        <Context>Front Matter</Context>
        <Provenance>Searching &quot;mind&quot; and &quot;law&quot; in HDIS (Drama)</Provenance>
        <DoE>2005-04-25</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory></SSCategory>
        <Type>Metaphor</Type>
        <Theme></Theme>
        <Comments></Comments>
        <Dictionary>Court</Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>9628</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>3725</WorkID>
        <Metaphor>&quot; But he who stamp'd [the soul] there at first, can make / It once again a new Impression take&quot;</Metaphor>
        <Text>Thirdly.&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;Nay, once again, it's Nature to declare,&lt;BR&gt; 'Twill sweet Impressions take, God's Image bear.&lt;BR&gt; It bore it once, O then, how did it shine!&lt;BR&gt; A glorious shadow of him, who's Divine:&lt;BR&gt; But now 'tis blurr'd, and soil'd by filthy dust;&lt;BR&gt; O 'tis defac'd and spoil'd by means of Lust.&lt;BR&gt;&lt;b&gt; But he who stamp'd it there at first, can make&lt;BR&gt; It once again a new Impression take&lt;/b&gt;:&lt;BR&gt; He can wash off the soil, refine the Ore,&lt;BR&gt; And make it shine fairer than heretofore.&lt;BR&gt; O what a glorious thing! how rare 'twill be,&lt;BR&gt; When God renews his Image once in thee?&lt;BR&gt; Lose not the Soul, (the wax) for nought can bear&lt;BR&gt; This Image then, nor can that loss repair.&lt;BR&gt;</Text>
        <Category>Uncategorized</Category>
        <SubCategory>Stamping</SubCategory>
        <Context></Context>
        <Provenance>Searching in HDIS (Poetry)</Provenance>
        <DoE>2005-03-27</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory>Impression</SSCategory>
        <Type>Metaphor</Type>
        <Theme></Theme>
        <Comments></Comments>
        <Dictionary>Impression</Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>15642</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>5891</WorkID>
        <Metaphor>&quot; But hope is the string that rides a sailor's heart--So, heave a-head, my lads&quot;</Metaphor>
        <Text>CHEERLY.&lt;BR&gt;Come, come along, my lads! heave ahead. Three cheers under my mistress's window, and then away.&lt;BR&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;BR&gt;(Sailors appear dissatisfied with Cheerly.&lt;/i&gt;)&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;What! slack in stays! Why, do you think Cheerly prefers his mistress to his duty? No, no, my lads! My country's servic. --you rewarded, --and then my love. Ah! cou'd but my dear little girl and I be lash'd alongside each other before we part I shou'd be content. Vain has engaged that I shall have her; but as he will not tell me his scheme, his conceit makes him unfit to be relied on.&lt;b&gt; But hope is the string that rides a sailor's heart--So, heave a-head, my lads&lt;/b&gt;--One farewell at the window, and if the wind comes about a point to-morrow, we'll weigh, and then for Arethusa's glory.</Text>
        <Category>Uncategorized</Category>
        <SubCategory>String</SubCategory>
        <Context>Act II, scene 2iii</Context>
        <Provenance>Searching  in HDIS (Drama)</Provenance>
        <DoE>2006-01-25</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory></SSCategory>
        <Type>Metaphor</Type>
        <Theme></Theme>
        <Comments></Comments>
        <Dictionary></Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>16622</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>6281</WorkID>
        <Metaphor>&quot; But hope rose gently in the mother's breast; / For well she knew that neither grief nor joy / Pain'd without hope, or pleased without alloy&quot;</Metaphor>
        <Text>Awed by the elfin's threats, and fill'd with dread&lt;BR&gt; The parents wept, and sought their infant's bed:&lt;BR&gt; Despair alone the father's soul possess'd;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;b&gt; But hope rose gently in the mother's breast;&lt;BR&gt; For well she knew that neither grief nor joy&lt;BR&gt; Pain'd without hope, or pleased without alloy&lt;/b&gt;;&lt;BR&gt; And while these hopes and fears her heart divide,&lt;BR&gt; A cheerful vision bade the fears subside.&lt;BR&gt;</Text>
        <Category>Mineral</Category>
        <SubCategory>Alloy</SubCategory>
        <Context></Context>
        <Provenance>Searching &quot;mind&quot; and &quot;alloy&quot; in HDIS (Poetry)</Provenance>
        <DoE>2005-04-14</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory></SSCategory>
        <Type>Metaphor</Type>
        <Theme></Theme>
        <Comments>&amp;bull;C-H pulls from Poetical Works (1838)</Comments>
        <Dictionary>Metal</Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>10491</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>4051</WorkID>
        <Metaphor>&quot; But let thine image ever dwell / Stampt as a seal upon my heart.&quot;</Metaphor>
        <Text>I hold no more commerce with hell,&lt;BR&gt; My dearest lusts shall all depart;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;b&gt; But let thine image ever dwell&lt;BR&gt; Stampt as a seal upon my heart.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;BR&gt;</Text>
        <Category>Uncategorized</Category>
        <SubCategory>Stamping and Sealing</SubCategory>
        <Context>Book I. Sacred to Devotion and Piety</Context>
        <Provenance>Searching &quot;stamp&quot; and &quot;heart&quot; in HDIS (Poetry); found again &quot;seal&quot;</Provenance>
        <DoE>2005-04-07</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory></SSCategory>
        <Type>Simile</Type>
        <Theme></Theme>
        <Comments></Comments>
        <Dictionary></Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>9632</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>3729</WorkID>
        <Metaphor>&quot; But make me' a Seal upon Thy Heart! / A Badg Thou on Thy Arm mayst wear,&quot;</Metaphor>
        <Text>SPONSA.&lt;i&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;Pone me ut signaculum super Cor.&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;Sponsa.&lt;BR&gt;&lt;/i&gt;Blest, ever blessed be that Day.&lt;BR&gt; When thus Thou cam'est, and thus I lay!&lt;BR&gt; O let us never, never part,&lt;BR&gt;&lt;b&gt; But make me' a Seal upon Thy Heart!&lt;BR&gt; A Badg Thou on Thy Arm mayst wear,&lt;/b&gt;&lt;BR&gt; That where Thou art, I may be there,&lt;BR&gt; And never, never from Thee part,&lt;BR&gt; But always on, or next Thy Heart!&lt;BR&gt; &quot;For love, (And who loves more than I?)&lt;BR&gt; &quot;Stronger than Death, does Death defie.&lt;BR&gt; &quot;His Conquests like the Graves, extend,&lt;BR&gt; &quot;And further, up to Heav'n his flames ascend.&lt;BR&gt; &quot;But never was there such a Flame,&lt;BR&gt; &quot;As that, in which to me he came;&lt;BR&gt; &quot;So dreadful, scorching, and so bright,&lt;BR&gt; &quot;I blest, but trembled at the sight.&lt;BR&gt; &quot;A Fire; Love was himself that Fire,&lt;BR&gt; &quot;Which in no Waters will expire:&lt;BR&gt; &quot;But, eve'n in Floods, securely lives,&lt;BR&gt; &quot;And all their watry threats survives.&lt;BR&gt; &quot;Nor quench, nor drown it can the Flood,&lt;BR&gt; &quot;Nor buy it, all the seeming good&lt;BR&gt; &quot;This World, that mighty Chapman, boasts&lt;BR&gt; &quot;In his vast Traffique through all Coasts.&lt;BR&gt; &quot;For so invaluable is its price,&lt;BR&gt; &quot;And its exchange so monstrous high does rise,&lt;BR&gt; &quot;The Universe too little is for 'its Merchandise.</Text>
        <Category>Writing</Category>
        <SubCategory>Seal</SubCategory>
        <Context>I've included the entire poem</Context>
        <Provenance>Searching &quot;heart&quot; and &quot;seal&quot; in HDIS (Poetry)</Provenance>
        <DoE>2005-04-17</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory></SSCategory>
        <Type>Metaphor</Type>
        <Theme></Theme>
        <Comments></Comments>
        <Dictionary></Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>9910</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>3858</WorkID>
        <Metaphor>&quot; But on his Heart the stamp of Death he wore&quot;</Metaphor>
        <Text>The fury of this Storm &lt;i&gt;Duke Brunswick&lt;/i&gt; bore,&lt;BR&gt; Whom nor in Arms, nor Courage could defend:&lt;BR&gt;&lt;b&gt; But on his Heart the stamp of Death he wore&lt;/b&gt;,&lt;BR&gt; No longer could Life's batter'd Fort contend,&lt;BR&gt; He dying fell, embalm'd in his own gore,&lt;BR&gt; To crown his actions with a glorious end,&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; On whom no barb'rous Enemy could confer,&lt;BR&gt; &amp;nbsp; Less than a high, immortal Character</Text>
        <Category>Uncategorized</Category>
        <SubCategory>Stamp</SubCategory>
        <Context></Context>
        <Provenance>Searching &quot;heart&quot; and &quot;stamp&quot; in HDIS (Poetry)</Provenance>
        <DoE>2005-04-07</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory></SSCategory>
        <Type>Metaphor</Type>
        <Theme></Theme>
        <Comments></Comments>
        <Dictionary></Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>16270</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>6163</WorkID>
        <Metaphor>&quot; But plant ideas like a printing-press; / Or, graven copper-plate, again to roll / The pristine stamp of proud Employer's Soul.&quot;</Metaphor>
        <Text>Will you your heavenly Sire's best blessing slight?&lt;BR&gt; Be Dupes by day? and Negroes through the night?&lt;BR&gt; For trifles be betray'd? for bubbles bought?&lt;BR&gt; For toys yield up all Liberty but thought?&lt;BR&gt; Corporeal faculties be moved, or stand,&lt;BR&gt; Like wheels and levers in Mechanic's hand?&lt;BR&gt; Exert your intellectual strength, and skill,&lt;BR&gt; The mere Automatons of others' Will!&lt;BR&gt; Your eyes be blind; or, more than seen, perceive?&lt;BR&gt; Your ears be deaf; breasts more than's meant believe?&lt;BR&gt; Thought, introduc'd, and lodg'd within the head,&lt;BR&gt; Lie dormant, there; or, number'd with the dead.&lt;BR&gt; The brain resembling only large hotel,&lt;BR&gt; Where none but foreign families may dwell;&lt;BR&gt; Like sham ambassadorial shadow, sent&lt;BR&gt; To signify frail Sovereign's false intent.&lt;BR&gt; Perfidious Pimp--or Spy--or abject Scout,&lt;BR&gt; On some base expedition posted out,&lt;BR&gt; To act pert Duns, or Bully's bolder part,&lt;BR&gt; Nor feel one kind emotion move the heart!&lt;BR&gt; Amanuensis, never to digress,&lt;BR&gt;&lt;b&gt; But plant ideas like a printing-press;&lt;BR&gt; Or, graven copper-plate, again to roll&lt;BR&gt; The pristine stamp of proud Employer's Soul.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;BR&gt; Still trudging every road, like common hack,&lt;BR&gt; To take Fools' trifles--bring Fops' baggage back.&lt;BR&gt; All native Cogitations' private store,&lt;BR&gt; To celibacy sworn, must breed no more;&lt;BR&gt; But, unproductive, all, in secret cell,&lt;BR&gt; Like insulated Nuns--Monks--Hermits--dwell--&lt;BR&gt; No propagated offspring brought to birth&lt;BR&gt; To speak their wisdom, or their parents' worth.</Text>
        <Category>Uncategorized</Category>
        <SubCategory>Stamp</SubCategory>
        <Context></Context>
        <Provenance>Searching &quot;soul&quot; and &quot;stamp&quot; in HDIS (Poetry)</Provenance>
        <DoE>2005-04-08</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory></SSCategory>
        <Type>Metaphor</Type>
        <Theme></Theme>
        <Comments>&amp;bull;INTEREST. Printing press. I've included thrice: Printing Press, Engraving, Stamping</Comments>
        <Dictionary></Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>16271</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>6163</WorkID>
        <Metaphor>&quot; But plant ideas like a printing-press; / Or, graven copper-plate, again to roll / The pristine stamp of proud Employer's Soul.&quot;</Metaphor>
        <Text>Will you your heavenly Sire's best blessing slight?&lt;BR&gt; Be Dupes by day? and Negroes through the night?&lt;BR&gt; For trifles be betray'd? for bubbles bought?&lt;BR&gt; For toys yield up all Liberty but thought?&lt;BR&gt; Corporeal faculties be moved, or stand,&lt;BR&gt; Like wheels and levers in Mechanic's hand?&lt;BR&gt; Exert your intellectual strength, and skill,&lt;BR&gt; The mere Automatons of others' Will!&lt;BR&gt; Your eyes be blind; or, more than seen, perceive?&lt;BR&gt; Your ears be deaf; breasts more than's meant believe?&lt;BR&gt; Thought, introduc'd, and lodg'd within the head,&lt;BR&gt; Lie dormant, there; or, number'd with the dead.&lt;BR&gt; The brain resembling only large hotel,&lt;BR&gt; Where none but foreign families may dwell;&lt;BR&gt; Like sham ambassadorial shadow, sent&lt;BR&gt; To signify frail Sovereign's false intent.&lt;BR&gt; Perfidious Pimp--or Spy--or abject Scout,&lt;BR&gt; On some base expedition posted out,&lt;BR&gt; To act pert Duns, or Bully's bolder part,&lt;BR&gt; Nor feel one kind emotion move the heart!&lt;BR&gt; Amanuensis, never to digress,&lt;BR&gt;&lt;b&gt; But plant ideas like a printing-press;&lt;BR&gt; Or, graven copper-plate, again to roll&lt;BR&gt; The pristine stamp of proud Employer's Soul.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;BR&gt; Still trudging every road, like common hack,&lt;BR&gt; To take Fools' trifles--bring Fops' baggage back.&lt;BR&gt; All native Cogitations' private store,&lt;BR&gt; To celibacy sworn, must breed no more;&lt;BR&gt; But, unproductive, all, in secret cell,&lt;BR&gt; Like insulated Nuns--Monks--Hermits--dwell--&lt;BR&gt; No propagated offspring brought to birth&lt;BR&gt; To speak their wisdom, or their parents' worth.</Text>
        <Category>Writing</Category>
        <SubCategory>Printing Press</SubCategory>
        <Context></Context>
        <Provenance>Searching in HDIS (Poetry)</Provenance>
        <DoE>2005-04-08</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory></SSCategory>
        <Type>Metaphor</Type>
        <Theme></Theme>
        <Comments>&amp;bull;INTEREST. Printing press. I've included thrice: Printing Press, Engraving, Stamping</Comments>
        <Dictionary></Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>16272</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>6163</WorkID>
        <Metaphor>&quot; But plant ideas like a printing-press; / Or, graven copper-plate, again to roll / The pristine stamp of proud Employer's Soul.&quot;</Metaphor>
        <Text>Will you your heavenly Sire's best blessing slight?&lt;BR&gt; Be Dupes by day? and Negroes through the night?&lt;BR&gt; For trifles be betray'd? for bubbles bought?&lt;BR&gt; For toys yield up all Liberty but thought?&lt;BR&gt; Corporeal faculties be moved, or stand,&lt;BR&gt; Like wheels and levers in Mechanic's hand?&lt;BR&gt; Exert your intellectual strength, and skill,&lt;BR&gt; The mere Automatons of others' Will!&lt;BR&gt; Your eyes be blind; or, more than seen, perceive?&lt;BR&gt; Your ears be deaf; breasts more than's meant believe?&lt;BR&gt; Thought, introduc'd, and lodg'd within the head,&lt;BR&gt; Lie dormant, there; or, number'd with the dead.&lt;BR&gt; The brain resembling only large hotel,&lt;BR&gt; Where none but foreign families may dwell;&lt;BR&gt; Like sham ambassadorial shadow, sent&lt;BR&gt; To signify frail Sovereign's false intent.&lt;BR&gt; Perfidious Pimp--or Spy--or abject Scout,&lt;BR&gt; On some base expedition posted out,&lt;BR&gt; To act pert Duns, or Bully's bolder part,&lt;BR&gt; Nor feel one kind emotion move the heart!&lt;BR&gt; Amanuensis, never to digress,&lt;BR&gt;&lt;b&gt; But plant ideas like a printing-press;&lt;BR&gt; Or, graven copper-plate, again to roll&lt;BR&gt; The pristine stamp of proud Employer's Soul.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;BR&gt; Still trudging every road, like common hack,&lt;BR&gt; To take Fools' trifles--bring Fops' baggage back.&lt;BR&gt; All native Cogitations' private store,&lt;BR&gt; To celibacy sworn, must breed no more;&lt;BR&gt; But, unproductive, all, in secret cell,&lt;BR&gt; Like insulated Nuns--Monks--Hermits--dwell--&lt;BR&gt; No propagated offspring brought to birth&lt;BR&gt; To speak their wisdom, or their parents' worth.</Text>
        <Category>Writing</Category>
        <SubCategory>Copper-plate Engraving</SubCategory>
        <Context></Context>
        <Provenance>Searching in HDIS (Poetry); Found again &quot;copper&quot; and &quot;soul&quot;</Provenance>
        <DoE>2005-04-08</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory></SSCategory>
        <Type>Metaphor</Type>
        <Theme></Theme>
        <Comments>&amp;bull;INTEREST. Printing press. I've included thrice: Printing Press, Engraving, Stamping</Comments>
        <Dictionary></Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>9494</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>3640</WorkID>
        <Metaphor>&quot; But under God this Jewel [the Conscience], O esteem / For its great worth, as rarest next to Christ&quot;</Metaphor>
        <Text>The Conscience was ever, and is still&lt;BR&gt; The fountain of all actions, good or ill;&lt;BR&gt; And all the actings, whether foul or fair,&lt;BR&gt; Of men, are as their Consciences are.&lt;BR&gt; Conscience goes with us where e're we go,&lt;BR&gt; To bear record of whatsoe're we do.&lt;BR&gt;&lt;b&gt; &lt;/b&gt;Conscience is Gods Vice-Roy in the Soul,&lt;BR&gt; And all are liable to its controul.&lt;BR&gt; Conscience is Christs Vicar in mans heart,&lt;BR&gt; It keeps Court there, and acts the Judges part.&lt;BR&gt; Its verdict can be by no pow'r repeal'd,&lt;BR&gt; Its stroaks are wounds that never can be heal'd:&lt;BR&gt; It's the Souls Anchor, boldness it maintains&lt;BR&gt; In judgment, and is of unwearied pains.&lt;BR&gt; Conscience is most like God, it is supreme,&lt;BR&gt;&lt;b&gt; But under God this Jewel, O esteem&lt;BR&gt; For its great worth, as rarest next to Christ&lt;/b&gt;;&lt;BR&gt; It is our Patron, our Apologist;&lt;BR&gt; It is impartial, active, and sincere,&lt;BR&gt; Gods Register in us; his Harbinger&lt;BR&gt; For to prepare his way; this is beside&lt;BR&gt; Mans faithful Surety, Treasurer and Guide.&lt;BR&gt; The evidence of a good Conscience will&lt;BR&gt; Find with the judge of hearts acceptance still;&lt;BR&gt; Good Conscience is the only Ark that can&lt;BR&gt; Ding down the &lt;i&gt;Dagons&lt;/i&gt; of all deeds prophane.&lt;BR&gt; A Conscience unstain'd with blushing crimes,&lt;BR&gt; Holds out in all changes of States and Times.&lt;BR&gt; Mount &lt;i&gt;Sion&lt;/i&gt; and good Conscience abide&lt;BR&gt; For ever, and tentations can deride.&lt;BR&gt; A Conscience that is kept free from blame,&lt;BR&gt; Laughs at the false reports of long-tongu'd fame.&lt;BR&gt; Good Conscience will speak within, when all breath,&lt;BR&gt; The doors are shut to ev'ry vocal call.&lt;BR&gt; When riches, husband, wife, parents, friends, breath,&lt;BR&gt; Life, patience, firm hope, assured faith&lt;BR&gt; Have left us; a good Conscience is so fast&lt;BR&gt; A friend, that it sticks to us till the last.&lt;BR&gt; A right good Conscience term this we may,&lt;BR&gt; To live therein until our dying day.&lt;BR&gt; Good Conscience still keeps Holy-day, is bent&lt;BR&gt; To feasting ev'ry day; there is no Lent,&lt;BR&gt; No Fasting-days that interrupt this Feast,&lt;BR&gt; But still the chear is more and more encreas'd.&lt;BR&gt; Who keeps his Conscience from offences clear,&lt;BR&gt; That man keeps &lt;i&gt;Hil'ry&lt;/i&gt; Term throughout the year&lt;BR&gt; But he that shipwracks a good Conscience shall&lt;BR&gt; Let in great riches, but the Devil withal.&lt;BR&gt; Good Conscience, as &lt;i&gt;Davids&lt;/i&gt; Instrument,&lt;BR&gt; Drives away th'evil Spirit of discontent.&lt;BR&gt; Good Conscience can suck content divine,&lt;BR&gt; From bitt'rest drugs, turn &lt;i&gt;Marah&lt;/i&gt; into Wine.&lt;BR&gt; Can sweetly smile, ev'n in afflictions sharp,&lt;BR&gt; This made &lt;i&gt;Pauls&lt;/i&gt; Prisons-songs, tun'd &lt;i&gt;Davids&lt;/i&gt; harp.&lt;BR&gt; It is a Paradise with pleasures fraught,&lt;BR&gt; All our best duties are without it naught.&lt;BR&gt; It's to the Castle of the Heart a Wall&lt;BR&gt; Of Brass: it is a Christians coat of Mail,&lt;BR&gt; How many do for want of it miscarry!&lt;BR&gt; It is a cordial Electuary:&lt;BR&gt; And very many good ingredients go&lt;BR&gt; Therein, Meat, Drink, Sleep, Ease, Refreshment too.&lt;BR&gt; Good Conscience on God it self can roul;&lt;BR&gt; 'Tis &lt;i&gt;Aquavit&amp;aelig;&lt;/i&gt; to the swouning soul.&lt;BR&gt; A Conscience that from wickedness is pure,&lt;BR&gt; Can in the Cannons mouth repose secure.&lt;BR&gt; No such provision 'gainst an evil day,&lt;BR&gt; As a good Conscience; this is they say&lt;BR&gt; A constant Feast; who hath a Conscience good,&lt;BR&gt; Fares well although he have no other Food.&lt;BR&gt; A sincere heart will not do any thing&lt;BR&gt; 'Gainst Conscience, is bold in suffering;&lt;BR&gt; But ah! fearful of sin, such as upright&lt;BR&gt; would walk, must have God always in their sight.&lt;BR&gt;</Text>
        <Category>Mineral</Category>
        <SubCategory>Jewel</SubCategory>
        <Context></Context>
        <Provenance>Searching in HDIS (Poetry)</Provenance>
        <DoE>2005-06-07</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory></SSCategory>
        <Type>Metaphor</Type>
        <Theme>Conscience</Theme>
        <Comments>&amp;bull;Rich stanza.</Comments>
        <Dictionary></Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>10212</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>3937</WorkID>
        <Metaphor>&quot; But when they read the Volumes of his Mind, / (Vast Tomes!) and Search'd the Closets of his Brain, / What endless Sums of Wisdom did they find?&quot;</Metaphor>
        <Text>    His Own was wonderful and great,&lt;BR&gt;  At &lt;i&gt;Mons&lt;/i&gt; he ran upon the mouth of Fate,&lt;BR&gt;  And from War's Deluge sav'd a sinking State.&lt;BR&gt;  In Him, as in the Heav'n commanded Ark,&lt;BR&gt;  The Families of &lt;i&gt;Holland&lt;/i&gt; did imbark.&lt;BR&gt;  How did They meet Him with exalted praise?&lt;BR&gt;What Elogies they sung? What Statues did they raise?&lt;BR&gt;  But yet they could not think Him fit&lt;BR&gt;    At the grave Council-board to sit,&lt;BR&gt;  Imputing Courage to a Youthful heat.&lt;BR&gt; &lt;b&gt; But when they read the Volumes of his Mind,&lt;BR&gt;  (Vast Tomes!) and Search'd the Closets of his Brain,&lt;BR&gt;  What endless Sums of Wisdom did they find?&lt;/b&gt;&lt;BR&gt;What untouch'd Heaps of Prudence did his Head contain?&lt;BR&gt;    The bearded Seniors wondred to behold&lt;BR&gt;       A Prince, who had few Summers told,&lt;BR&gt;  Young without rashness, without dotage Old.</Text>
        <Category>Architecture</Category>
        <SubCategory>Closet</SubCategory>
        <Context>Stanza XIII.</Context>
        <Provenance>Searching &quot;mind&quot; and &quot;closet&quot; in HDIS (Poetry); found again &quot;brain&quot;</Provenance>
        <DoE>2005-09-06</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory></SSCategory>
        <Type>Metaphor</Type>
        <Theme></Theme>
        <Comments>&amp;bull;I've included twice: Books and Closet</Comments>
        <Dictionary>Rooms</Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>10213</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>3937</WorkID>
        <Metaphor>&quot; But when they read the Volumes of his Mind, / (Vast Tomes!) and Search'd the Closets of his Brain, / What endless Sums of Wisdom did they find?&quot;</Metaphor>
        <Text>    His Own was wonderful and great,&lt;BR&gt;  At &lt;i&gt;Mons&lt;/i&gt; he ran upon the mouth of Fate,&lt;BR&gt;  And from War's Deluge sav'd a sinking State.&lt;BR&gt;  In Him, as in the Heav'n commanded Ark,&lt;BR&gt;  The Families of &lt;i&gt;Holland&lt;/i&gt; did imbark.&lt;BR&gt;  How did They meet Him with exalted praise?&lt;BR&gt;What Elogies they sung? What Statues did they raise?&lt;BR&gt;  But yet they could not think Him fit&lt;BR&gt;    At the grave Council-board to sit,&lt;BR&gt;  Imputing Courage to a Youthful heat.&lt;BR&gt; &lt;b&gt; But when they read the Volumes of his Mind,&lt;BR&gt;  (Vast Tomes!) and Search'd the Closets of his Brain,&lt;BR&gt;  What endless Sums of Wisdom did they find?&lt;/b&gt;&lt;BR&gt;What untouch'd Heaps of Prudence did his Head contain?&lt;BR&gt;    The bearded Seniors wondred to behold&lt;BR&gt;       A Prince, who had few Summers told,&lt;BR&gt;  Young without rashness, without dotage Old.</Text>
        <Category>Writing</Category>
        <SubCategory>Books</SubCategory>
        <Context>Stanza XIII.</Context>
        <Provenance>Searching in HDIS (Poetry)</Provenance>
        <DoE>2005-09-06</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory>Volumes</SSCategory>
        <Type>Metaphor</Type>
        <Theme></Theme>
        <Comments>&amp;bull;I've included twice: Books and Closet</Comments>
        <Dictionary>Writing</Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>9492</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>3640</WorkID>
        <Metaphor>&quot; Conscience is Gods Vice-Roy in the Soul, / And all are liable to its controul.&quot;</Metaphor>
        <Text>The Conscience was ever, and is still&lt;BR&gt; The fountain of all actions, good or ill;&lt;BR&gt; And all the actings, whether foul or fair,&lt;BR&gt; Of men, are as their Consciences are.&lt;BR&gt; Conscience goes with us where e're we go,&lt;BR&gt; To bear record of whatsoe're we do.&lt;BR&gt;&lt;b&gt; Conscience is Gods Vice-Roy in the Soul,&lt;BR&gt; And all are liable to its controul.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;BR&gt; Conscience is Christs Vicar in mans heart,&lt;BR&gt; It keeps Court there, and acts the Judges part.&lt;BR&gt; Its verdict can be by no pow'r repeal'd,&lt;BR&gt; Its stroaks are wounds that never can be heal'd:&lt;BR&gt; It's the Souls Anchor, boldness it maintains&lt;BR&gt; In judgment, and is of unwearied pains.&lt;BR&gt; Conscience is most like God, it is supreme,&lt;BR&gt; But under God this Jewel, O esteem&lt;BR&gt; For its great worth, as rarest next to Christ;&lt;BR&gt; It is our Patron, our Apologist;&lt;BR&gt; It is impartial, active, and sincere,&lt;BR&gt; Gods Register in us; his Harbinger&lt;BR&gt; For to prepare his way; this is beside&lt;BR&gt; Mans faithful Surety, Treasurer and Guide.&lt;BR&gt; The evidence of a good Conscience will&lt;BR&gt; Find with the judge of hearts acceptance still;&lt;BR&gt; Good Conscience is the only Ark that can&lt;BR&gt; Ding down the &lt;i&gt;Dagons&lt;/i&gt; of all deeds prophane.&lt;BR&gt; A Conscience unstain'd with blushing crimes,&lt;BR&gt; Holds out in all changes of States and Times.&lt;BR&gt; Mount &lt;i&gt;Sion&lt;/i&gt; and good Conscience abide&lt;BR&gt; For ever, and tentations can deride.&lt;BR&gt; A Conscience that is kept free from blame,&lt;BR&gt; Laughs at the false reports of long-tongu'd fame.&lt;BR&gt; Good Conscience will speak within, when all breath,&lt;BR&gt; The doors are shut to ev'ry vocal call.&lt;BR&gt; When riches, husband, wife, parents, friends, breath,&lt;BR&gt; Life, patience, firm hope, assured faith&lt;BR&gt; Have left us; a good Conscience is so fast&lt;BR&gt; A friend, that it sticks to us till the last.&lt;BR&gt; A right good Conscience term this we may,&lt;BR&gt; To live therein until our dying day.&lt;BR&gt; Good Conscience still keeps Holy-day, is bent&lt;BR&gt; To feasting ev'ry day; there is no Lent,&lt;BR&gt; No Fasting-days that interrupt this Feast,&lt;BR&gt; But still the chear is more and more encreas'd.&lt;BR&gt; Who keeps his Conscience from offences clear,&lt;BR&gt; That man keeps &lt;i&gt;Hil'ry&lt;/i&gt; Term throughout the year&lt;BR&gt; But he that shipwracks a good Conscience shall&lt;BR&gt; Let in great riches, but the Devil withal.&lt;BR&gt; Good Conscience, as &lt;i&gt;Davids&lt;/i&gt; Instrument,&lt;BR&gt; Drives away th'evil Spirit of discontent.&lt;BR&gt; Good Conscience can suck content divine,&lt;BR&gt; From bitt'rest drugs, turn &lt;i&gt;Marah&lt;/i&gt; into Wine.&lt;BR&gt; Can sweetly smile, ev'n in afflictions sharp,&lt;BR&gt; This made &lt;i&gt;Pauls&lt;/i&gt; Prisons-songs, tun'd &lt;i&gt;Davids&lt;/i&gt; harp.&lt;BR&gt; It is a Paradise with pleasures fraught,&lt;BR&gt; All our best duties are without it naught.&lt;BR&gt; It's to the Castle of the Heart a Wall&lt;BR&gt; Of Brass: it is a Christians coat of Mail,&lt;BR&gt; How many do for want of it miscarry!&lt;BR&gt; It is a cordial Electuary:&lt;BR&gt; And very many good ingredients go&lt;BR&gt; Therein, Meat, Drink, Sleep, Ease, Refreshment too.&lt;BR&gt; Good Conscience on God it self can roul;&lt;BR&gt; 'Tis &lt;i&gt;Aquavit&amp;aelig;&lt;/i&gt; to the swouning soul.&lt;BR&gt; A Conscience that from wickedness is pure,&lt;BR&gt; Can in the Cannons mouth repose secure.&lt;BR&gt; No such provision 'gainst an evil day,&lt;BR&gt; As a good Conscience; this is they say&lt;BR&gt; A constant Feast; who hath a Conscience good,&lt;BR&gt; Fares well although he have no other Food.&lt;BR&gt; A sincere heart will not do any thing&lt;BR&gt; 'Gainst Conscience, is bold in suffering;&lt;BR&gt; But ah! fearful of sin, such as upright&lt;BR&gt; would walk, must have God always in their sight.&lt;BR&gt;</Text>
        <Category>Government</Category>
        <SubCategory>Viceroy</SubCategory>
        <Context></Context>
        <Provenance>Searching in HDIS (Poetry)</Provenance>
        <DoE>2005-06-07</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory></SSCategory>
        <Type>Personification</Type>
        <Theme>Conscience</Theme>
        <Comments>&amp;bull;Rich stanza.</Comments>
        <Dictionary>Inhabitant</Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>16281</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>6163</WorkID>
        <Metaphor>&quot; Could, with one thought, most beauteous castles build, / With tasteful furniture, all, instant, fill'd, / But could not monies coin, or form firm land / To make fond Fancy's mimic turrets stand!&quot;</Metaphor>
        <Text>He was a Bard with better prospects born;&lt;BR&gt; Too great to envy, and too good to scorn!&lt;BR&gt; Benevolence unbounded! matchless Taste!&lt;BR&gt; With Wealth to banish Want, but none to waste.&lt;BR&gt; His heart not free from Poet's common curse,&lt;BR&gt; Ambition, boundless! perch'd on feeble purse!&lt;BR&gt; Sublime conceptions, lodg'd in procreant pate,&lt;BR&gt; Which, magic schemes, could, ev'ry hour, create--&lt;BR&gt;&lt;b&gt; Could, with one thought, most beauteous castles build,&lt;BR&gt; With tasteful furniture, all, instant, fill'd,&lt;BR&gt; But could not monies coin, or form firm land&lt;BR&gt; To make fond Fancy's mimic turrets stand!&lt;/b&gt;&lt;BR&gt; Penurious Genius should, from Prudence, learn&lt;BR&gt; Fair lessons, Fancy's plans, and hopes, to spurn;&lt;BR&gt; In covert, close, frail Insufficience shroud,&lt;BR&gt; Nor show the World wild fabrics on a cloud.</Text>
        <Category>Uncategorized</Category>
        <SubCategory>imaginary Castles</SubCategory>
        <Context></Context>
        <Provenance>Searching &quot;coin&quot; and &quot;fancy&quot; in HDIS (Poetry)</Provenance>
        <DoE>2005-04-14</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory></SSCategory>
        <Type>Metaphor</Type>
        <Theme></Theme>
        <Comments></Comments>
        <Dictionary></Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>12692</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>4778</WorkID>
        <Metaphor>&quot; E'en stern ecclesiasticks laid aside / (To welcome him) their ruling passion, pride&quot;</Metaphor>
        <Text>Thus, by the nicer conduct of the brain,&lt;BR&gt; He gain'd a passage to &lt;i&gt;Valencia's&lt;/i&gt; plain.&lt;BR&gt; What ardent transports in their bosoms glow'd,&lt;BR&gt; When they beheld from far their guardian God?&lt;BR&gt; Joyful as angels when by fiends dismay'd&lt;BR&gt; The great &lt;i&gt;Messiah&lt;/i&gt; thunder'd to their aid.&lt;BR&gt;&lt;b&gt; E'en stern ecclesiasticks laid aside&lt;BR&gt; (To welcome him) their ruling passion, pride&lt;/b&gt;;&lt;BR&gt; Gaz'd on his form, in admiration lost,&lt;BR&gt; And strove with zeal who should applaud him most.&lt;BR&gt;</Text>
        <Category>Government</Category>
        <SubCategory>Rule and Subjection</SubCategory>
        <Context></Context>
        <Provenance>Searching &quot;ruling passion&quot; in HDIS (Restoration and C18)</Provenance>
        <DoE>2004-05-20</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory>Rule of Passion</SSCategory>
        <Type>Metaphor</Type>
        <Theme>Ruling Passion </Theme>
        <Comments></Comments>
        <Dictionary></Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>12020</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>4574</WorkID>
        <Metaphor>&quot; Each keeps the other's Image in his Breast, / As Wax preserves the Form a Seal imprest&quot;</Metaphor>
        <Text>What base, ungen'rous, selfish Souls are these?&lt;BR&gt; Mere Quacks, who turn ev'n Health into Disease;&lt;BR&gt; And but the darkest Side of Friendship find,&lt;BR&gt; To all its radiant Beams and Beauties blind.&lt;BR&gt; Two faithful Friends, in any State, may gain&lt;BR&gt; Comfort to heighten Joy, or lessen Pain:&lt;BR&gt; If weighty Cares the pensive Mind invade,&lt;BR&gt; They make the Burden light with mutual Aid;&lt;BR&gt; If Profit, or if Pleasure chears the Soul,&lt;BR&gt; The Blessing's common, each enjoys the whole:&lt;BR&gt; If Bus'ness calls them to some distant Place,&lt;BR&gt; Swift-pinion'd Love contracts the lengthen'd Space;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;b&gt; Each keeps the other's Image in his Breast,&lt;BR&gt; As Wax preserves the Form a Seal imprest.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;BR&gt;</Text>
        <Category>Uncategorized</Category>
        <SubCategory>Wax</SubCategory>
        <Context></Context>
        <Provenance>Searching &quot;breast&quot; and &quot;wax&quot; in HDIS (Poetry); found again &quot;seal&quot;</Provenance>
        <DoE>2005-04-11</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory>Seal</SSCategory>
        <Type>Metaphor</Type>
        <Theme></Theme>
        <Comments></Comments>
        <Dictionary></Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>16645</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>6293</WorkID>
        <Metaphor>&quot; For he not only beholds intensely the present as it is, and discovers those laws according to which present things ought to be ordered, but he beholds the future in the present, and his thoughts are the germs of the flower and the fruit of latest time&quot;</Metaphor>
        <Text>But poets, or those who imagine and express this indestructible order, are not only the authors of language and of music, of the dance, and architecture, and statuary, and painting: they are the institutors of laws, and the founders of civil society, and the inventors of the arts of life, and the teachers, who draw into a certain propinquity with the beautiful and the true that partial apprehension of the agencies of the invisible world which is called religion. Hence all original religions are allegorical, or susceptible of allegory, and, like Janus, have a double face of false and true. Poets, according to the circumstances of the age and nation in which they appeared, were called, in the earlier epochs of the world, legislators, or prophets: a poet essentially comprises and unites both these characters.&lt;b&gt; For he not only beholds intensely the present as it is, and discovers those laws according to which present things ought to be ordered, but he beholds the future in the present, and his thoughts are the germs of the flower and the fruit of latest time&lt;/b&gt;. Not that I assert poets to be prophets in the gross sense of the word, or that they can foretell the form as surely as they foreknow the spirit of events: such is the pretence of superstition, which would make poetry an attribute of prophecy, rather than prophecy an attribute of poetry. A poet participates in the eternal, the infinite, and the one; as far as relates to his conceptions, time and place and number are not. The grammatical forms which express the moods of time, and the difference of persons, and the distinction of place, are convertible with respect to the highest poetry without injuring it as poetry; and the choruses of Aeschylus, and the book of Job, and Dante's &quot;Paradise&quot; would afford, more than any other writings, examples of this fact, if the limits of this essay did not forbid citation. The creations of sculpture, painting, and music are illustrations still more decisive.</Text>
        <Category>Garden</Category>
        <SubCategory>Germs</SubCategory>
        <Context></Context>
        <Provenance>Reading</Provenance>
        <DoE>2006-10-03</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory></SSCategory>
        <Type>Metaphor</Type>
        <Theme></Theme>
        <Comments>&amp;bull;</Comments>
        <Dictionary></Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>15113</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>5658</WorkID>
        <Metaphor>&quot; For spells may be said to exist in that tone, / Whose graces can conquer all hearts--but her own&quot;</Metaphor>
        <Text>Its anodyne powers the sick'ning make cheery,&lt;BR&gt; And tears off the chain from the mind of the weary;&lt;BR&gt; By her soft, blissful sonnets, all bosoms inspiring,&lt;BR&gt; Even Spleen grows diseas'd--and, Despair lies expiring.&lt;BR&gt; As the lark chaunts at sun-rise his diurnal pray'r,&lt;BR&gt; All her loud liquid notes charge the babbling air;&lt;BR&gt; The sounds were not sweeter when Thebes' famous wall&lt;BR&gt; Obey'd the soft magic of Harmony's call;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;b&gt; For spells may be said to exist in that tone,&lt;BR&gt; Whose graces can conquer all hearts--but her own&lt;/b&gt;.&lt;BR&gt; Cecilia thus warbled the heaven-fraught line,&lt;BR&gt; For her song was ador'd ere the nymph was divine.&lt;BR&gt;</Text>
        <Category>War</Category>
        <SubCategory>Conquest</SubCategory>
        <Context></Context>
        <Provenance>Searching &quot;conque&quot; and &quot;heart&quot; in HDIS (Poetry)</Provenance>
        <DoE>2005-02-14</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory>Conquer Heart</SSCategory>
        <Type>Metaphor</Type>
        <Theme></Theme>
        <Comments></Comments>
        <Dictionary></Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>9918</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>3865</WorkID>
        <Metaphor>&quot; For Vertue in a Woman's Breast / Seldom by Title is possest, / And is no Tenant, but a wand'ring Guest.&quot;</Metaphor>
        <Text>She that is chast, is always fair,&lt;BR&gt;  No matter for her Hue,&lt;BR&gt;And though for form she were a Star,&lt;BR&gt;  She's ugly, if untrue:&lt;BR&gt;True Beauty alwayes lies within,&lt;BR&gt;Much deeper, than the outer skin,&lt;BR&gt;So deep, that in a Woman's mind,&lt;BR&gt;It will be hard, I doubt, to find;&lt;BR&gt;  Or if it be, she's so deriv'd,&lt;BR&gt;  And with so many doors contriv'd,&lt;BR&gt;Harder by much to keep it in&lt;b&gt;.&lt;BR&gt;  For Vertue in a Woman's Breast&lt;BR&gt;  Seldom by Title is possest,&lt;BR&gt;And is no Tenant, but a wand'ring Guest.&lt;/b&gt;</Text>
        <Category>Population</Category>
        <SubCategory>Guest</SubCategory>
        <Context>Stanza V</Context>
        <Provenance>Searching in HDIS (Poetry)</Provenance>
        <DoE>2006-12-18</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory></SSCategory>
        <Type>Personification</Type>
        <Theme></Theme>
        <Comments>&amp;bull;I've included twice: Tenant and Guest</Comments>
        <Dictionary></Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>9919</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>3865</WorkID>
        <Metaphor>&quot; For Vertue in a Woman's Breast / Seldom by Title is possest, / And is no Tenant, but a wand'ring Guest.&quot;</Metaphor>
        <Text>She that is chast, is always fair,&lt;BR&gt;  No matter for her Hue,&lt;BR&gt;And though for form she were a Star,&lt;BR&gt;  She's ugly, if untrue:&lt;BR&gt;True Beauty alwayes lies within,&lt;BR&gt;Much deeper, than the outer skin,&lt;BR&gt;So deep, that in a Woman's mind,&lt;BR&gt;It will be hard, I doubt, to find;&lt;BR&gt;  Or if it be, she's so deriv'd,&lt;BR&gt;  And with so many doors contriv'd,&lt;BR&gt;Harder by much to keep it in&lt;b&gt;.&lt;BR&gt;  For Vertue in a Woman's Breast&lt;BR&gt;  Seldom by Title is possest,&lt;BR&gt;And is no Tenant, but a wand'ring Guest.&lt;/b&gt;</Text>
        <Category>Population</Category>
        <SubCategory>Tenant</SubCategory>
        <Context>Stanza V</Context>
        <Provenance>Searching in HDIS (Poetry)</Provenance>
        <DoE>2006-12-18</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory></SSCategory>
        <Type>Personification</Type>
        <Theme></Theme>
        <Comments>&amp;bull;I've included twice: Tenant and Guest</Comments>
        <Dictionary></Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
    <metaphor>
        <MetaphorID>15655</MetaphorID>
        <WorkID>5896</WorkID>
        <Metaphor>&quot; For, Cupid, well thou know'st, the tender soul, / That Poesy inspires, is very wax / To Beauty's piercing ray&quot;</Metaphor>
        <Text>&lt;i&gt;Ven.&lt;BR&gt;&lt;/i&gt;Chang'd as he was, the youth repair'd to Lesbos,&lt;BR&gt; Where Sappho saw, and, need I add, ador'd him.&lt;BR&gt;&lt;b&gt; For, Cupid, well thou know'st, the tender soul,&lt;BR&gt; That Poesy inspires, is very wax&lt;BR&gt; To Beauty's piercing ray&lt;/b&gt;: the blooming boy,&lt;BR&gt; More raptur'd with her lyre than with her form,&lt;BR&gt; Feign'd real passion; swore eternal truth.&lt;BR&gt; Yet scarce the waning moon had heard his vows,&lt;BR&gt; Ere all those vows were broke, and perjur'd Phaon &lt;BR&gt; Parted for Sicily; where now he reigns&lt;BR&gt; Here like ourselves, my Son, all-absolute,&lt;BR&gt;Conquering each heart he lists, nor needs thy shafts&lt;BR&gt; To aid his victories.&lt;BR&gt;</Text>
        <Category>Uncategorized</Category>
        <SubCategory>Wax</SubCategory>
        <Context></Context>
        <Provenance>Searching &quot;wax&quot; and &quot;soul&quot; in HDIS (Poetry)</Provenance>
        <DoE>2005-03-27</DoE>
        <DoR>0000-00-00</DoR>
        <SSCategory></SSCategory>
        <Type>Metaphor</Type>
        <Theme></Theme>
        <Comments></Comments>
        <Dictionary></Dictionary>
    </metaphor>
</bpasanek_metabase_backup>
